<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Resilience as Positive Psychology &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/resilience-as-positive-psychology/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>How Much Positivity?</title>
		<link>/2012/06/07/how-much-positivity-2/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Jun 2012 21:27:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience as Positive Psychology]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1043</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Many scientifically based publications refer to a ratio of positive to negative experiences that you have to reach to live a happy, healthy, and successful life. Is there really such a critical ratio that is scientifically valid? We think there &#8230; <a href="/2012/06/07/how-much-positivity-2/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Many scientifically based publications refer to a ratio of positive to negative experiences that you have to reach to live a happy, healthy, and successful life. Is there really such a critical ratio that is scientifically valid?</p>
<p>We think there is.</p>
<p>We will describe several studies that have confirmed it. In a subsequent post, we plan to focus on some simple ways to improve your positivity to negativity ratio.</p>
<p><span id="more-1043"></span></p>
<p>The concept of the critical ratio was explored and developed by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcial_Losada">Marcial Losada</a> and his colleagues. He and his team meticulously studied 60 business teams in planning sessions, with observers recording everything that was said. There were three dimensions of interest</p>
<ol start="1">
<li>How positive or negative participants were.</li>
<li>Whether comments were self-focused or other-focused.</li>
<li>The degree to which statements were based on inquiry (asking questions) or advocacy (defending a point of view).</li>
</ol>
<p>The businesses were divided into three groups, based on the degree of positivity displayed in their meetings. He then assessed the degree to which the businesses were flourishing or stagnating. His criteria of flourishing included profitability, customer satisfaction, and ratings by superiors, peers, and subordinates.</p>
<p>Businesses in the top 25% were clearly flourishing. In contrast, those in the bottom 30% were stagnating or failing.</p>
<p>Losada developed a mathematical model of the relationship between the positivity/negativity ratio and business success. The model indicated that the “tipping point” was about <a href="http://enablersnetwork.com/2009/marcial-losada-explains-his-research-for-our-blog-readers/">3 positives for each negative</a>.</p>
<p>But does the 3 to 1 ratio apply generally or is it specific to business planning and business success?</p>
<p>Losada discovered Barbara Frederickson’s “<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broaden-and-build">broaden and build</a>” model of the effects of positivity. She has shown that, with positivity, people widen their perspective whereas those who are high in negativity tend to narrow their field of consciousness, and thus to lack creativity in solving problems.</p>
<p>Losada learned about Barbara Frederickson’s research on the effects of positivity, he wrote her to ask whether she would be interested in writing a joint paper that synthesized their work, she had just had a baby, so didn’t respond for a while, but fortunately, he persisted, and they eventually got together for what turned out to be a very exciting and creative meeting.</p>
<p>The next question was whether her own research findings did or did not confirm the prediction of his mathematical model, and the meeting was enough to lead her to devote her research time to exploring this possibility. (For academics, shifting the focus of their work is a really big deal; it is at the very core of their life commitments and their performance in their jobs).</p>
<p>Well it turned out that Frederickson’s data also indicated that a ratio of about 3 to 1 predicted whether people were flourishing or languishing in their lives. This work is all summarized in non-technical language in Dr. Fredrickson’s book “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Positivity-Top-Notch-Research-Reveals-Change/dp/0307393747/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1338927909&amp;sr=1-1">Positivity</a>”</p>
<p>The 3 to 1 ratio is the crucial point where the power of positivity in controlling the effects of negative becomes clear. Losada has said that he has seen ratios at high as 5.6 to 1. So positives anywhere from 3 times negatives to roughly twice that have been shown to result in success and well-being.</p>
<p>John Gottman, an eminent researcher on factors that make marriages succeed or fail, also found a ratio within that range that was related to marital success (5 to 1). If you are interested in successful marriage, (or, no doubt, successful relationships in general, you should take a minute to view this video of Gottman explaining in more detail, the ratio’s practical significance.</p>
<p><iframe width="640" height="480" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/Xw9SE315GtA?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>We are talking about things that are very important to most of us, job success and marital success, and a lot more, so it would be wise for all of us to learn how to increase our positivity and reduce our negativity so we at least reach that 3 to one ratio.</p>
<p>Sounds like something very difficult to do? This is partly because most of us have many positive things in our lives, but give scant attention to them. Or positive things we could easily do, but fail to take action. Negatives tend to be more memorable and when the big ones hit us, it is hard to keep our attention on the many positives we have or can easily call up.</p>
<p>In our next post we will discuss ways to improve your positivity/negativity ratio. In the meanwhile, click these three links to take a look at these earlier post on how to become more positive or less negative: 1, 2, 3.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2012%2F06%2F07%2Fhow-much-positivity-2%2F&amp;linkname=How%20Much%20Positivity%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>For Those Who Have to Struggle With Distress Just to Reach a “Normal” Life.</title>
		<link>/2012/01/31/for-those-who-have-to-struggle-with-distress-just-to-reach-a-normal-life/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2012 04:54:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience as Positive Psychology]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=939</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Someone wrote to us and asked, “what about those of us who have to struggle just to live a normal life?” Recently, Debbie and I discussed this question at length. Have we given the impression that we are only addressing &#8230; <a href="/2012/01/31/for-those-who-have-to-struggle-with-distress-just-to-reach-a-normal-life/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Someone wrote to us and asked, “what about those of us who have to struggle just to live a normal life?” Recently, Debbie and I discussed this question at length. Have we given the impression that we are only addressing people who want to go from good to great? Neither of us intended anything like that.</p>
<p>Improving resilience is valuable for people who are trying to go from good to great, but also for those who are struggling to barely stay above water. Neither your starting point nor how high you are aiming will exclude you from benefits of learning effective strategies to enhance your resilience.</p>
<p><span id="more-939"></span></p>
<p>Both Debbie and I have spent years helping people with serious illnesses make the best of their lives. Often, the most any of these courageous people could hope for was making the best of their final weeks or months. In other cases they were striving to live a good life despite serious chronic limitations that might go on for many years.</p>
<p>Anyone who works with people who are living at the outer boundaries of life will be humbled by the courage so many show in the face of dreadful obstacles. What we can offer them are strategies for living as well as possible in spite of their circumstances. We honor their courage, and we can bring to them what we have learned from decades of research and experience that provide strategies that work in getting the most out of life. Even if there are only hours left to live, it is still life, and the right frame of mind can make it better and more meaningful.</p>
<p>Lawrence LeShan wrote a book called “You Can Fight for Your Life” about his way of helping people who were dealing with deadly cancers. His approach emphasized helping people rediscover desires that had always been in their heart of hearts, and to find ways to work toward their really meaningful goals, even when those goals have long been put aside, and perhaps even forgotten.</p>
<p>LeShan wrote a revision, “<a title="Cancer as a Turning Point" href="http://www.cancerasaturningpoint.org/">Cancer as a Turning Point</a>” that I highly recommend. Notice I am not just recommending it to people who have potentially terminal illnesses. I am flat out recommending it for anybody.</p>
<p>Those of us who do not have terminal illnesses have more in common than we realize with those who have them. They are often like us with the self-deceptions put aside.  No one lives forever, and we all face temptations that can lure us away from what is really meaningful in our lives.</p>
<p>Why wait until we have a serious illness before we teach ourselves to live well?” Why not start <strong><em>now</em></strong> to learn how to live a life full of positivity and compassion for ourselves and others? What are we waiting for?</p>
<p>Living with resilience is living a less stressful, happier and better life than you otherwise would. Your starting point and any possible limitations on how far you are likely to go are pretty much irrelevant.</p>
<p>If people with serious diseases like cancers, can do well at carrying on their lives (and they definitely can), why shouldn’t the healthy learn to do the same?</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2012%2F01%2F30%2F939%2F&amp;linkname=For%20Those%20Who%20Have%20to%20Struggle%20With%20Distress%20Just%20to%20Reach%20a%20%E2%80%9CNormal%E2%80%9D%20Life." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Stressed or Not , Learning To Be More Resilient Can Enhance Your Life.</title>
		<link>/2011/02/03/stressed-or-not-learning-to-be-more-resilient-can-enhance-your-life/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2011 16:28:15 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience as Positive Psychology]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=559</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Slowly and painfully I have become aware that the term “resilience” seldom rings anybody’s chime. In this post I want to dig beneath the surface to show what improved resilience might mean to you. Some people are dealt a poor &#8230; <a href="/2011/02/03/stressed-or-not-learning-to-be-more-resilient-can-enhance-your-life/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Slowly and painfully I have become aware that the term “resilience” seldom rings anybody’s chime. In this post I want to dig beneath the surface to show what improved resilience might mean to you.</p>
<p>Some people are dealt a poor hand in life from the start of their lives. Some of those play the hand well, and others succumb to its limitations.</p>
<p>Most of us are dealt a poor hand from time to time, maybe even frequently. But it’s not the hand we are dealt that determines our happiness, success, or health. How well we play the hand is of central importance.</p>
<p>Learning to be more resilient teaches you how to get the most out of life even when it deals you one of these poor hands. But is also teaches you how to get more out of life even when the hand you are dealt is not particularly bad. This encompasses most of life’s activities.</p>
<p>I started out studying the relationship between stress and physical<em> </em>health. When I began looking into this topic, the evidence in favor of it was fairly primitive. Many studies had shown that illness tends to be preceded by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holmes_and_Rahe_stress_scale">periods of high stress</a>. Since then, over and over, studies have confirmed the <a href="http://whyfiles.org/039emotion/cohen.html">relationship between stress and health</a>. Now we have a large body of research supporting the idea that stress is related to many diseases from the common cold to <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2979339/?tool=pmcentrez">serious heart disease</a>.</p>
<p>Many found this relationship between mind and physical health hard to believe. We had no solid understanding of how a mental reaction could produce physical illness, so the relationship seemed beyond the pale of science.</p>
<p>Now we also have research showing a <a href="http://www.springerlink.com/content/qp61nj5v64445015/">powerful impact of stress on the body’s immune and endocrine systems</a>. For example, we now know that <a href="http://pni.osumc.edu/KG%20Publications%20%28pdf%29/102.pdf">stress influences the speed of wound healing</a>, and we also know a great deal about the <a href="http://pni.osumc.edu/KG%20Publications%20%28pdf%29/132.pdf">processes in the immune system that underlie the swifter healing</a>. Further, we know <a href="http://pni.osumc.edu/KG%20Publications%20%28pdf%29/065.pdf">that practicing deep relaxation <em>enhances</em> the ability of the body to heal</a>. Learning to relax deeply is a central aspect of learning to be more resilient.</p>
<p>Research on resilience has also revealed that it influences many other aspects of life and that it can compel you forward even if you haven’t been dealt a bad hand. For example, greater resilience has been linked to <a href="http://www.mindresources.net/marketing/website/profilingtools/MetLifeCaseStudyMRSSS.pdf">better performance of salespeople</a>, <a href="http://repository.upenn.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1003&amp;context=mapp_capstone">business managers</a>, and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Learned-Optimism-Change-Your-Mind/dp/0671019112">athletes</a>. It has also been linked to more <a href="http://pni.osumc.edu/KG%20Press%20Releases/OSU%20researchers%20identify%20predictors%20of%20divorce.htm">successful relationships</a>. And we could go on and on with examples from just about any facet of life.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2011%2F02%2F03%2Fstressed-or-not-learning-to-be-more-resilient-can-enhance-your-life%2F&amp;linkname=Stressed%20or%20Not%20%2C%20Learning%20To%20Be%20More%20Resilient%20Can%20Enhance%20Your%20Life." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Encouraging Positive Attitudes Can Enhance Your Resilience</title>
		<link>/2010/12/15/encouraging-positive-attitudes-can-enhance-your-resilience/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2010 04:38:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Benefits of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience as Positive Psychology]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=472</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Highlights: Resilient actions and resilient attitudes are centrally important to becoming more resilient. In this post we want to call your attention to the value of optimism. Research on the influence of optimism and pessimism has tended to be focused on three &#8230; <a href="/2010/12/15/encouraging-positive-attitudes-can-enhance-your-resilience/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong><br />
</strong></p>
<h3><em>Highlights:</em></h3>
<p><em>Resilient actions and resilient attitudes are centrally important to becoming more resilient.</em></p>
<p><em>In this post we want to call your attention to the value of optimism.</em></p>
<p><em>Research on the influence of optimism and pessimism has tended to be focused on three things:</em></p>
<ul>
<li><em>Job and Athletic Performance.</em></li>
<li><em>Relationship Success.</em></li>
<li><em>Health.</em></li>
</ul>
<p><em>***************************************************************************</em></p>
<p>A major way to improve your resilience is to learn the kinds of self-soothing skills we have been discussing, and turning them into habits. Developing habits of self-soothing in distressing situations and of relaxing deeply to replenish yourself are pivotal to improving resilience.</p>
<p>Equally important is shifting how you think, your attitudes. Positive attitudes improve resilience.</p>
<h3>More resilient people:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Are optimistic, consider interpretations of life events that are positive.</li>
<li>See problems as solvable.</li>
<li>See their lives as making sense, as meaningful.</li>
<li>Feel that they have valuable connections to others.</li>
</ul>
<p>Resilient actions and resilient attitudes are centrally important to becoming more resilient.</p>
<p>In this post we want to call your attention to the value of optimism.</p>
<p>Research on the influence of optimism and pessimism has tended to be focused on three things:</p>
<ul>
<li>Job and Athletic Performance.</li>
<li>Relationship Success.</li>
<li>Health.</li>
</ul>
<h3>To provide some examples:</h3>
<h3><em>Job Success</em></h3>
<ul>
<li>Optimists tend to get higher overall job performance ratings from their supervisors.</li>
<li>In a study of optimistic versus pessimistic insurance agents, the optimists sold more, were given higher ratings by managers, and were less likely to quit their jobs.</li>
<li>Tests of optimism and pessimism given during orientation sessions for new production workers at a manufacturing facility predicted later supervisor performance ratings. Pessimism was a particularly strong predictor of poorer performance.</li>
</ul>
<p><span id="more-472"></span></p>
<h3><em>Athletic Performance</em><em> </em></h3>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"> </span></p>
<ul>
<li>Optimistic athletes tend to perform better than pessimists.</li>
<li>Optimistic athletes tend to sustain their performance better than pessimists when faced with adversity, e.g. being behind behind in a game or playing a tough competitor after you have not performed up to expectations in a previous event.</li>
</ul>
<h3><em>Level of Physical Health and Coping with Illness</em></h3>
<ul>
<li>Optimists tend be more healthy than pessimists.</li>
<li>Optimists recover more quickly from major surgery, return to work sooner, end up with a higher post-surgical quality of life, and are less likely to be re-hospitalized.</li>
<li>Optimists have a higher quality of life and better biological markers of recovery if they undergo chemotherapy.</li>
<li>Optimists have a lower risk of all causes of death, especially death due to heart disease.</li>
<li>If required to become a long-term caregiver for a loved one who is seriously ill, optimists stay healthier, and the person they are caring for does too.</li>
<li>Pessimists are more likely than optimists to die prematurely.</li>
</ul>
<h3><em>Mental Health</em></h3>
<ul>
<li>Optimists are less likely to be depressed.</li>
<li>Optimists tend to be less anxious.</li>
<li>Optimists are more likely to have high satisfaction with their lives.</li>
<li>Optimistic mothers are less likely to suffer from post-partum depression.</li>
<li>Optimists tend to have more energy than pessimists.</li>
</ul>
<h3><em>Success in Relationships</em></h3>
<ul>
<li>Optimists tend to be more satisfied with their primary relationship.</li>
<li>Optimists who discuss one of their conflicts see the discussion as more constructive and, later, feel the conflict was better resolved.</li>
<li>Optimistic women treated for breast cancer feel more supported and more physically attractive than pessimists.</li>
</ul>
<p>These bulleted points are not mere opinions. They are all based in scientific studies, many of them available on line. Yet some prominent writers deny the value of optimism. We will take a close look at their objections in the next post.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2010%2F12%2F15%2Fencouraging-positive-attitudes-can-enhance-your-resilience%2F&amp;linkname=Encouraging%20Positive%20Attitudes%20Can%20Enhance%20Your%20Resilience" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
