<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Genes and Resilience &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/genes-and-resilience/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>How to Teach Your Worrier Brain to Function Like A Warrior Brain</title>
		<link>/2013/04/25/how-to-teach-your-worrier-brain-to-function-like-a-warrior-brain/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2013 19:17:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Genes and Resilience]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1359</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Our last two posts focused on research showing that there are two variants of a gene that result in your having either a “worrier brain” or a “warrior brain”. However, the research also shows that a “worrier” can function like &#8230; <a href="/2013/04/25/how-to-teach-your-worrier-brain-to-function-like-a-warrior-brain/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Our last two posts focused on research showing that there are two variants of a gene that result in your having either a “worrier brain” or a “warrior brain”. However, the research also shows that a “worrier” can function like a “warrior” with the right kind of training. Extensively exposing worriers to simulations of the stressors they need to face enabled many of them to deal with stress as effectively as warriors.</p>
<p>This “<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exposure_therapy">exposure training</a>” has been used widely by psychotherapists, and its efficacy is well established.</p>
<p>A second approach that improves performance under stress is “reappraisal”. An excellent example of reappraisal is teaching people about the helpful effects of our bodily stress responses. For example, blood glucose can be increased due to stress, and that can help when facing challenges like taking tests. Again, this is not new to psychotherapists; commonly they point out that what a person is experiencing as fear or anxiety can also be seen as “excitement”. This kind of shift in perspective has been shown to work.</p>
<p>In this post we want to point out some other things that both of us feel are particularly useful in dealing with stress.</p>
<p><span id="more-1359"></span></p>
<p>Debbie and I agreed to identify which methods we would add to the two described in the previous two posts. Debbie’s list was the best, so here is a summary of it.</p>
<ul>
<li>Exercise: Just about everyone these days knows about the body’s natural opiates that counter stress and even reduce pain. Exercise also produces <a href="/2012/05/09/physical-exercise-is-a-surefire-way-to-de-stress/">other, less well known, chemical changes</a> that are calming. Debbie also points out that exercise helps to shift our thoughts toward the positive.</li>
<li>Challenging negative thoughts, which commonly do you no good, and finding more useful, positive thoughts.</li>
<li>Practice being in the present moment rather than always anticipating and maybe even overthinking about possible bad things in the future.</li>
<li>Shift to a more positive frame by keeping a daily log of things that went well, and try to notice for a particular time period (e.g. a day), the things you like about other people.</li>
<li>One of the weaknesses of self-help is that most of us find it hard to do what we know is in our best interests. Debbie suggests “<a href="/2012/10/17/finding-a-path-to-a-more-resilient-life-the-devil-is-in-the-details/">Mental Contrasting</a>”, which has been shown to help people follow through on their good intentions. Mentally contrasting a future you want with present reality energizes us and encourages us to commit to the actions that will get us to our goal.</li>
</ul>
<p>The only thing I want to add to that list is controlled regulation of breathing. Details of how to do that are in <a href="/2011/12/14/dont-let-overwhelming-distress-take-you-down/">this post</a> and <a href="/2011/06/14/a-plain-vanilla-application-of-tactical-breathing-to-increase-resilience/">this one</a>.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F04%2F25%2Fhow-to-teach-your-worrier-brain-to-function-like-a-warrior-brain%2F&amp;linkname=How%20to%20Teach%20Your%20Worrier%20Brain%20to%20Function%20Like%20A%20Warrior%20Brain" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Your Stress Responses and the Wisdom of the Body</title>
		<link>/2013/04/10/your-stress-responses-and-the-wisdom-of-the-body/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2013 04:13:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Genes and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1348</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In our last post, we discussed genetic variations that result in our having either a “worrier” or a “warrior” brain. We also mentioned that worriers can handle stress effectively, even function at the level of Navy Seals, if they are &#8230; <a href="/2013/04/10/your-stress-responses-and-the-wisdom-of-the-body/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In our last post, we discussed genetic variations that result in our having either a “worrier” or a “warrior” brain. We also mentioned that worriers can handle stress effectively, even function at the level of Navy Seals, if they are properly trained. Sufficiently trained, worriers can deal with demanding situations as well as warriors.</p>
<p>What makes this possible? Despite the bodily stress reactions we have that are inborn, how we <strong><em>interpret</em></strong> those reactions can dramatically shift how we react.</p>
<p><span id="more-1348"></span></p>
<p>In the early 1960s, two psychologists, <a href="http://faculty.babson.edu/krollag/org_site/soc_psych/schachter_epineph.html">Stanley Schachter and Jerome Singer</a> showed that <strong><em>cueing</em></strong> people about how to view their experiences can dramatically shift how they actually react.</p>
<p>Their studies were complex, but, basically, they assessed how the effects of a drug that produced high arousal (standard pharmaceutical adrenalin) changed, depending on the context in which the drug was administered.</p>
<p>If people injected with pharmaceutical adrenalin, which produces a typical stress response with rapid heart rate, sweating, and so forth), were in a situation in which a stooge feigned anger, they were more likely to be angry. If the stooge feigned euphoria, they became more silly and playful.</p>
<p>Anything that changes how we view our bodily reactions has the power to determine whether we end up distressed and defeated or end up feeling euphoric, or heaven knows what else. The point is that the physiological reaction is not the boss. It has a vote, but it’s not the boss.</p>
<p>So if you have powerful feelings and symptoms when you face stress, you can still fall back on your thought patterns to use that power to support you.</p>
<p>Bodily responses to life’s demands commonly provide protection from threats. So getting rid of those reactions is not necessarily a good path to resilience. <a href="http://digitalcommons.unl.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1215&amp;context=psychfacpub">Important research</a> shows that those who are resilient have physiological responses to stress as intense as those who are less resilient.</p>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fight-or-flight_response">Walter Cannon</a>, the scientist who first identified the “fight or flight” stress response did so in a book he entitled “The Wisdom of the Body”.  Wisdom? Can it be that these hated feelings we try to fight off when taking a difficult test, walking on stage to give a speech, etc. are based on bodily “wisdom”?</p>
<p>For example, isn’t your heart pounding rapidly bad for you?</p>
<p>Commonly it is not. Your heart pounds when you exercise vigorously, have sex or ride on a rollercoaster, and we don’t think of that as bad for you. The heart’s reaction during positive states can actually be more intense than it is during negative ones.</p>
<p>It <strong><em>can</em></strong> be bad for you if you have serious heart disease, but that doesn’t mean it’s bad for most of us. Exercise that pushes the heart to be fast and effective is commonly recommended to make us healthier.</p>
<p>The physiological reactions themselves can change depending on how we interpret them. For example, when we interpret something as manageable, our heart’s efficiency tends to increase and our blood vessels relax. When we view them as a threat beyond our control, the opposite happens.</p>
<p>Harvard Professor Jeremy Jamieson and his colleagues have done valuable <a href="http://wendyberrymendes.com/cms/uploads/CDPS_reappraisal-1.pdf">research</a> confirming that how we appraise or interpret our bodily reactions to demanding situations can determine how well we perform under stress.</p>
<p>For example, in one study, in a high-stakes testing situation half of the test-takers were told before the test that stress reactions we have during important, difficult tests predict better, not worse performance. They were also told that they should not feel concerned about their body’s reactions, but instead should remind themselves that this arousal could be helping them do well.</p>
<p>The group taught to see stress reactions as beneficial scored 65 points higher than controls!</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=&amp;linkname=" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Genetic Variants That Can Determine Whether We Have a “Worrier Brain” or A “Warrior Brain” and What We Can Do About Them.</title>
		<link>/2013/03/19/genetic-variants-that-can-determine-whether-we-have-a-worrier-brain-or-a-warrior-brain-and-what-we-can-do-about-them/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2013 15:16:31 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Genes and Resilience]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1338</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This post is based on an article I recently found in the New York Times. It makes several important claims: There are two variants of a specific gene that influence how quickly we recover from stressful experiences. We get one &#8230; <a href="/2013/03/19/genetic-variants-that-can-determine-whether-we-have-a-worrier-brain-or-a-warrior-brain-and-what-we-can-do-about-them/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This post is based on an <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/10/magazine/why-can-some-kids-handle-pressure-while-others-fall-apart.html?pagewanted=all&amp;_r=0">article</a> I recently found in the New York Times. It makes several important claims:</p>
<ol start="1">
<li>There are two variants of a specific gene that influence how quickly we recover from stressful experiences.</li>
<li>We get one from our mother and the other from our father.</li>
<li>The pattern of these genes we inherit determines whether we will be “worriers” or “warriors”.</li>
<li>Worriers are people who have to struggle with stressful experiences and warriors are people for whom stress reactions quickly pass by.</li>
<li>Whether we have the genetic pattern that gives us a warrior brain or a worrier brain, there is at least one simple technique that can make us deal efficiently with stress.</li>
</ol>
<p><span id="more-1338"></span></p>
<p>First, I want to acknowledge that I am skeptical about much of the brain-mind research that has come to be widely accepted. I don’t want to get into that because it is way too technical. But I often ask, “What good does it do for people dealing with a stress problem to learn that they were genetically doomed to have trouble with stressors, e.g.to be a worrier?”</p>
<p>Today, Debbie had an opening in her usually busy schedule, and called to chat.  I was trying to write this post, and I posed this question to her. She paused briefly, and then said “It helps people to understand why they have to struggle with things that other people handle with apparent ease.” Good answer.</p>
<p>So here is my condensed description of the genetic issue. Dopamine is a brain chemical that is released in the lower part of the frontal lobes of our brain. The sooner it is cleared out, the sooner we recover from the stress. This is because that lower frontal part of the brain can control the parts of the brain that produce responses that are “raw emotions”.</p>
<p>We all have a gene that determines how fast we clear Dopamine out of that part of our brain, and, as we said above, one variant leads to quicker, actually something like 40 times quicker, cleanup of the dopamine “mess”.</p>
<p>For people whose brains cleanup that mess slowly, their brains and minds are likely to be overwhelmed by the surge.</p>
<p>The following is an important part of this study: the effects of the slow acting system have been demonstrated in a real-life stressful situation. Young people in Taiwan take a test that has a major influence on the trajectory of their lives. Those with the slow acting system score on average 8 percent lower than those with the fast-acting system.</p>
<p>However, people with the slow acting gene can handle extreme stress as long as they are well-trained. Even some Navy Seals have worrier genes.</p>
<p>This concept that training can trump genetic effects (or lifelong bad habits) is right at the core of our belief in the value of resilience training.</p>
<p>What kind of training do people with worrier brains need to function as well as those with warrior brains?</p>
<ul>
<li>Exposure to stress challenges. Worriers need to be taxed without being overwhelmed, and then have time for recovery. “Training, preparation, and repetition defuse the worrier’s curse”.</li>
<li>Labeling of stress can determine reactions to it. If worriers see their feelings of stress as something that can improve their performance, their performance improves. They learn to view the feelings we usually call “stress” as “excitement”.</li>
</ul>
<p>We plan to deal with the effects of such labeling or “reappraisal” in a future post.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=&amp;linkname=" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
