<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Jerry Sheridan &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/author/jerry-sheridan/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Surgical Preparation</title>
		<link>/2016/08/31/surgical-preparation/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2016 21:20:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2128</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tips for Resilient Aging 1</title>
		<link>/2016/01/28/tips-for-resilient-aging-1/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2016 18:15:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2023</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[It&#8217;s well known that the population of the US and other Developed Countries is getting older, and this shift has many consequences. A wide range of important stressors increase with age. Elderly people face many losses. Their friends and neighbors &#8230; <a href="/2016/01/28/tips-for-resilient-aging-1/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It&#8217;s well known that the population of the US and other Developed Countries is getting older, and this shift has many consequences.</p>
<p>A wide range of important stressors increase with age. Elderly people face many losses. Their friends and neighbors die, their appearance tends to drop below social standards for attractiveness, they typically become less agile and peppy. Eventually they often have to let go of their homes and many of their possessions; many people end up in assisted-living facilities with little beyond the things that fit into a small closet or chest.</p>
<p>This is, of course, only a tiny, hapharzardly selected, sample of stressors that tend to accompany the passage of years. Without regard to such details, the old quote from Bette Davis says it all &#8220;Getting old ain&#8217;t for sissies&#8221;. If you are smart, you will prepare for it.</p>
<p>Since it takes time and energy to develop techniques for enhancing resilience and turn them into personal habits, it is fortunate that resilience techniques are also have a myriad of benefits for dealing with any of life&#8217;s stages.</p>
<p>Several major studies have influenced our view of techniques that help us respond to aging with resilience. Our plan for this and the next few posts is to describe these influential bodies of evidence.</p>
<p>The first is based on research done by Herbert DeVries and colleagues. and summarized in a book entitled &#8220;Vigor Regained&#8221;.</p>
<p>DeVries determined &#8220;scientifically whether carefully planned and controlled exercise can help restore vigor to older people&#8221;, and solidly affirmed that it could. He found that sedentary people, even in their 70s,80s,or 90s were, after training, able to run a nonstop mile.</p>
<p><span id="more-2023"></span></p>
<p>His sedentary elders were given a slowly increasing program that started with walking at a comfortable pace, eventually punctuating the walks with short periods of jogging, which were slowly increased to full jogging.</p>
<p>Could it be that some losses thought to be due to aging are to a greater extent, due to a shortage of exercise? DeVries points out that in a previous study called &#8220;Operation Sacktime&#8221;, college-age people who had been payed to stay entirely inactive over a period of two or three weeks lost their ability to adjust to strenuous activity as indicated in measures of the reactions of heart, lungs, circulation, and muscles. Physiological indicators of fitness were like those of sedentary elders.</p>
<p>How can you make use of this information? You could get a copy of Vigor Regained. It is out of print, but we searched for it and our first hit offered a copy for less than a dollar. Try <a href="http://www.amazon.com/">Amazon</a> or <a href="http://www.abebooks.com/">Abebooks.com</a>.</p>
<p>The book is a bit technical in spots, but it isn&#8217;t necessary to focus on those details. Really, any source of information on how to develop a mild exercise program that can be slowly increased will probably do. Our main warnings are to be sure you are well enough to do the exercise before starting (ask your doctor), and avoid pushing too hard and turning it into grueling &#8220;Type A exercise&#8221;. (We see &#8220;Type A&#8217;s&#8221; at a park near our home, often many pounds overweight, running as hard as they can with dumbbells in their hands, oblivious to the harm they may be doing to themselves).</p>
<p>Make the experience positive. See if you can find a supportive friend to enjoy the experience with you.</p>
<p>Stretching was also an important part of his program. We think it&#8217;s a good idea to learn some yoga positions that provide stretching in a well-tested way. Signing up for a beginner&#8217;s yoga class is a good way to do that.</p>
<p>A third component of the program is relaxation. However, Devries did not develop a specific method of relaxation. To review some effective methods, just do a search for the term &#8220;relaxation&#8221; in this blog. Devries mentions Edmund Jacobson&#8217;s method of progressive relaxation, but does not provide a simple, self-taught way to induce deep relaxation. This is probably because he had discovered that a 15 minute brisk walk was more effective in producing relaxation than a tranquillizer.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=&amp;linkname=Tips%20for%20Resilient%20Aging%201" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Recovery from Stress: Use Resilience Resources You Already Have to Calm and Sooth Yourself.</title>
		<link>/2014/02/27/recovery-from-stress-use-resilience-resources-you-already-have-to-calm-and-sooth-yourself/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2014 21:18:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1617</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Your mental and biological reactions to stress are attempts to help you survive and go on to live a rich life. Stress left unchecked can destroy you. On the other hand, experiencing a level of stress from which you can &#8230; <a href="/2014/02/27/recovery-from-stress-use-resilience-resources-you-already-have-to-calm-and-sooth-yourself/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Your mental and biological reactions to stress are attempts to help you survive and go on to live a rich life. Stress left unchecked can destroy you. On the other hand, experiencing a level of stress from which you can fairly quickly recover can even make you stronger and more resilient.</p>
<p>The often disturbing mental and biological reactions to stress can be hard to take, but they reflect the best solutions you, and even your biological ancestors, have been able to come up with to deal with life’s challenges.</p>
<p>If you cannot imagine that the stress reactions are helpful and adaptive, think of regular exercise. Exercise is good for you, but is also stressful. It is good for you <strong><em>because </em></strong>it is stressful, and you <strong><em>can handle it.</em></strong></p>
<p>When you exercise, you trigger basic aspects of the classic “fight or flight response”. But if you choose your exercise wisely, you can recover quickly and fully, and your mind and body will eventually change in ways that enable you to take that level of stress in your stride.</p>
<p>If you crank the exercise stress up slowly you are likely to improve your resilience. If you push yourself too much, you can expect to exceed the protective influence of your current resilience skills. If you keep that up, you will eventually experience some kind of breakdown.</p>
<p>On the other hand if you pace yourself carefully, you can improve how quickly and fully you recover from stress. You can become more resilient.</p>
<p>We only mean to use exercise as an <em>example</em> of controlled stress. Though exercise is, indeed, a valuable way to deal with stress, that is not our main message in this post.</p>
<p>Our main point is that, unless stress is extreme and/or perpetuated for a long time, whether you know how to calm down stress reactions, to return to your normal baseline quickly and fully is far more important  than the stress itself to determine whether stress leaves you stronger or breaks you.</p>
<p>In the last few posts, we have focused on techniques that have been tested in people’s lives sometimes for centuries, and have also been shown to be effective when tested scientifically. Specifically, we have explained how to do mantra meditation, and how to practice “loving kindness”. Both of these have been shown to make for a better life.</p>
<p>Before you can use these methods, there is a “learning curve” you must go through to use them. We strongly advocate that you learn how to use them. But there are also methods that most people already know how to use, but that are often not given the respect they deserve. We have described some of these methods <a href="/2010/11/04/natural-stress-defeaters/">here</a>. They include things that do not require you to learn new skills. We derived them by keeping track, over more than a decade, of publications that show how ordinary people, without any special training,  deal with stress.</p>
<p><span id="more-1617"></span></p>
<p>Briefly, examples include:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong><em>Contact comfort with pets or with people</em></strong>, e.g. cuddling with a pet or loved one; getting a massage.</li>
<li><strong><em>Pleasant, engrossing distraction</em></strong>, e.g. watching comedies, getting out into nature.</li>
<li><strong><em>Soothing sensory stimulation</em></strong>, e.g. taking a hot bath or shower, listening to calming music.</li>
<li><strong><em>Physical activity</em></strong>, e.g. dancing, taking a walk or exercising until you are tired.</li>
<li><strong><em>Contemplative relaxation</em></strong>, e.g. meditation, Yoga.</li>
<li><strong><em>Spiritual activities</em></strong>, e.g. praying, attending religious services.</li>
</ul>
<p>You can add to this whatever you already know works for you. Think over things that have calmed you in the past, and use them when you are distressed.</p>
<p>The trick is to get yourself to actually DO them. For advice on how to do that, click <a href="/2010/12/06/getting-yourself-to-act-on-what-you-learn-about-building-resilience/">here</a>.</p>
<p>The take-home message is to learn the real value of simple things that calm and sooth you, and to make sure you actually do those things when you need them.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F02%2F27%2Frecovery-from-stress-use-resilience-resources-you-already-have%2F&amp;linkname=Recovery%20from%20Stress%3A%20Use%20Resilience%20Resources%20You%20Already%20Have%20to%20Calm%20and%20Sooth%20Yourself." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Simple Way to Sooth and Comfort Yourself.</title>
		<link>/2014/01/15/a-simple-way-to-sooth-and-comfort-yourself/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2014 04:11:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1574</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[(Oops! This was supposed to be uploaded earlier, before the previous post.) Our last post discussed listening to “sweet talk” and contrasted it with actually learning to be more resilient. This post will discuss self-soothing, which is a way to &#8230; <a href="/2014/01/15/a-simple-way-to-sooth-and-comfort-yourself/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><!--[if gte mso 9]><xml>
<o:OfficeDocumentSettings>
<o:AllowPNG/>
</o:OfficeDocumentSettings>
</xml><![endif]--></p>
<p><!--[if gte mso 9]><xml>
<w:WordDocument>
<w:View>Normal</w:View>
<w:Zoom>0</w:Zoom>
<w:TrackMoves/>
<w:TrackFormatting/>
<w:PunctuationKerning/>
<w:ValidateAgainstSchemas/>
<w:SaveIfXMLInvalid>false</w:SaveIfXMLInvalid>
<w:IgnoreMixedContent>false</w:IgnoreMixedContent>
<w:AlwaysShowPlaceholderText>false</w:AlwaysShowPlaceholderText>
<w:DoNotPromoteQF/>
<w:LidThemeOther>EN-US</w:LidThemeOther>
<w:LidThemeAsian>X-NONE</w:LidThemeAsian>
<w:LidThemeComplexScript>X-NONE</w:LidThemeComplexScript>
<w:Compatibility>
<w:BreakWrappedTables/>
<w:SnapToGridInCell/>
<w:WrapTextWithPunct/>
<w:UseAsianBreakRules/>
<w:DontGrowAutofit/>
<w:SplitPgBreakAndParaMark/>
<w:EnableOpenTypeKerning/>
<w:DontFlipMirrorIndents/>
<w:OverrideTableStyleHps/>
</w:Compatibility>
<m:mathPr>
<m:mathFont m:val="Cambria Math"/>
<m:brkBin m:val="before"/>
<m:brkBinSub m:val="&#45;-"/>
<m:smallFrac m:val="off"/>
<m:dispDef/>
<m:lMargin m:val="0"/>
<m:rMargin m:val="0"/>
<m:defJc m:val="centerGroup"/>
<m:wrapIndent m:val="1440"/>
<m:intLim m:val="subSup"/>
<m:naryLim m:val="undOvr"/>
</m:mathPr></w:WordDocument>
</xml><![endif]--><!--[if gte mso 9]><xml>
<w:LatentStyles DefLockedState="false" DefUnhideWhenUsed="true"
DefSemiHidden="true" DefQFormat="false" DefPriority="99"
LatentStyleCount="267">
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="0" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Normal"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="heading 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 7"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 8"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 9"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 7"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 8"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 9"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="35" QFormat="true" Name="caption"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="10" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Title"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="1" Name="Default Paragraph Font"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="11" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Subtitle"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="22" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Strong"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="20" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Emphasis"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="59" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Table Grid"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Placeholder Text"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="1" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="No Spacing"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Revision"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="34" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="List Paragraph"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="29" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Quote"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="30" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Intense Quote"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="19" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Subtle Emphasis"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="21" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Intense Emphasis"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="31" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Subtle Reference"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="32" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Intense Reference"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="33" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Book Title"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="37" Name="Bibliography"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" QFormat="true" Name="TOC Heading"/>
</w:LatentStyles>
</xml><![endif]-->(Oops! This was supposed to be uploaded earlier, before the previous post.)</p>
<p>Our last post discussed listening to “sweet talk” and contrasted it with actually learning to be more resilient. This post will discuss self-soothing, which is a way to become more calm and shut down your physiological stress response.</p>
<p>Right off, we can tell you that self-soothing inevitably includes shifting the physiological reactions in your body toward what Harvard Cardiologist, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herbert_Benson#Mind_body_medicine">Herbert Benson</a>, called “the Relaxation Response”, and away from the “Fight or Flight Response” (a central physiological response when you are under stress).</p>
<p>Self-Soothing also primes your mind to become more aware of good things that are happening in your everyday life.</p>
<p>There are many tested techniques for shifting from stress to a relaxation response. Benson tested a method of meditation that was modeled after “<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transcendental_Meditation">Transcendental Meditation</a>”, which is a component of Yoga.</p>
<p>He tested his method and found no physiological evidence that it was inferior to Transcendental Meditation itself.</p>
<p>Transcendental Meditation and Benson’s technique are both forms of “mantra” meditation. A mantra is a word or sound that is the focus of your meditation. A mantra that is familiar to many people from the West is “OM” (also spelled “AUM”). In Transcendental meditation, you are given a personal mantra, but Benson simply used the word “one” for everyone.</p>
<p>Here is a simple way of doing mantra meditation:</p>
<p><span id="more-1574"></span></p>
<p>It takes only a matter of minutes to induce the desired shift to the relaxation response, and the relaxation gets deeper and deeper with practice.</p>
<p>In addition to relaxation, anyone who has tried the method can tell you that there are <a href="http://www.youmeworks.com/gentlyreturning.html">many additional benefits</a>. Meditation calms your mind, which, when no longer cluttered becomes much more efficient. You become more perceptive, and your mind becomes sharper.</p>
<p>Your goal in doing meditation may be to relax, but, in addition to relaxing, you are likely to notice your mind seeing beauty in your experiences that previously went unnoticed. The quieting of the mind reduces the “noise” in the brain and thereby provides the clarity needed to experience things that had previously been lost in the mental jabber.</p>
<p>You only have to do mantra meditation for a short period (ten or fifteen minutes) on a regular basis to reduce your vulnerability to stress. It’s free, and we recommend that you give it a try.</p>
<p>Here is how to do it:</p>
<p>MANTRA MEDITATION</p>
<p>1. Get in a relaxed, comfortable position.</p>
<p>2. Close your eyes.</p>
<p>3. Turn your attention gently to the word “one”.</p>
<p>4. If your mind wanders, that is okay; observing your wandering mind is actually an important part of the meditation.</p>
<p>5. When you notice your mind on something other than the mantra, “one”, gently return to the mantra</p>
<p>6. It is not necessary to <strong><em>say</em></strong> the word “one”. You can visualize it, imagine hearing it, or even just be aware of its presence, without regard to whether it is imagined as seen, heard, or anything else.</p>
<p>7. One of the most important things is to take a passive attitude, simply observing the various changes that take place in your mind without inviting them to stay or making an effort to drive them away.</p>
<p>8. Do this for 10 or 15 minutes once or twice a day and keep track of changes you see in yourself.</p>
<p>9. In the beginning, you may have to meditate for shorter periods of time. That’s fine. Meditation is not a race.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F01%2F15%2Fa-simple-way-to-sooth-and-comfort-yourself%2F&amp;linkname=A%20Simple%20Way%20to%20Sooth%20and%20Comfort%20Yourself." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Overthinking No More.</title>
		<link>/2013/05/13/overthinking-no-more/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2013 15:46:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Compassion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Understanding]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1370</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I don’t remember where I first ran into the concept of overthinking, but it appealed to me. Both Debbie and I understand the limitations of the parts of the brain that underlie thinking. We also are aware of the often &#8230; <a href="/2013/05/13/overthinking-no-more/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><!--[if gte mso 9]><xml>
<o:OfficeDocumentSettings>
<o:AllowPNG/>
</o:OfficeDocumentSettings>
</xml><![endif]--></p>
<p><!--[if gte mso 9]><xml>
<w:WordDocument>
<w:View>Normal</w:View>
<w:Zoom>0</w:Zoom>
<w:TrackMoves/>
<w:TrackFormatting/>
<w:PunctuationKerning/>
<w:ValidateAgainstSchemas/>
<w:SaveIfXMLInvalid>false</w:SaveIfXMLInvalid>
<w:IgnoreMixedContent>false</w:IgnoreMixedContent>
<w:AlwaysShowPlaceholderText>false</w:AlwaysShowPlaceholderText>
<w:DoNotPromoteQF/>
<w:LidThemeOther>EN-US</w:LidThemeOther>
<w:LidThemeAsian>X-NONE</w:LidThemeAsian>
<w:LidThemeComplexScript>X-NONE</w:LidThemeComplexScript>
<w:Compatibility>
<w:BreakWrappedTables/>
<w:SnapToGridInCell/>
<w:WrapTextWithPunct/>
<w:UseAsianBreakRules/>
<w:DontGrowAutofit/>
<w:SplitPgBreakAndParaMark/>
<w:EnableOpenTypeKerning/>
<w:DontFlipMirrorIndents/>
<w:OverrideTableStyleHps/>
</w:Compatibility>
<m:mathPr>
<m:mathFont m:val="Cambria Math"/>
<m:brkBin m:val="before"/>
<m:brkBinSub m:val="&#45;-"/>
<m:smallFrac m:val="off"/>
<m:dispDef/>
<m:lMargin m:val="0"/>
<m:rMargin m:val="0"/>
<m:defJc m:val="centerGroup"/>
<m:wrapIndent m:val="1440"/>
<m:intLim m:val="subSup"/>
<m:naryLim m:val="undOvr"/>
</m:mathPr></w:WordDocument>
</xml><![endif]--><!--[if gte mso 9]><xml>
<w:LatentStyles DefLockedState="false" DefUnhideWhenUsed="true"
DefSemiHidden="true" DefQFormat="false" DefPriority="99"
LatentStyleCount="267">
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="0" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Normal"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="heading 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 7"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 8"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 9"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 7"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 8"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 9"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="35" QFormat="true" Name="caption"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="10" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Title"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="1" Name="Default Paragraph Font"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="11" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Subtitle"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="22" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Strong"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="20" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Emphasis"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="59" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Table Grid"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Placeholder Text"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="1" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="No Spacing"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Revision"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="34" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="List Paragraph"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="29" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Quote"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="30" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Intense Quote"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="19" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Subtle Emphasis"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="21" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Intense Emphasis"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="31" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Subtle Reference"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="32" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Intense Reference"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="33" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Book Title"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="37" Name="Bibliography"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" QFormat="true" Name="TOC Heading"/>
</w:LatentStyles>
</xml><![endif]--><!--[if gte mso 10]>


<style>
 /* Style Definitions */
 table.MsoNormalTable
	{mso-style-name:"Table Normal";
	mso-tstyle-rowband-size:0;
	mso-tstyle-colband-size:0;
	mso-style-noshow:yes;
	mso-style-priority:99;
	mso-style-parent:"";
	mso-padding-alt:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;
	mso-para-margin:0in;
	mso-para-margin-bottom:.0001pt;
	mso-pagination:widow-orphan;
	font-size:10.0pt;
	font-family:"Calibri","sans-serif";}
</style>

<![endif]--></p>
<p>I don’t remember where I first ran into the concept of overthinking, but it appealed to me. Both Debbie and I understand the limitations of the parts of the brain that underlie thinking. We also are aware of the often unrecognized strengths of the “emotional brain”, which is commonly regarded as a giving birth to mere “fluff”.</p>
<p>Emotion is certainly not “fluff”.<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Descartes-Error-Emotion-Reason-Human/dp/014303622X/ref=sr_1_3?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1368458741&amp;sr=1-3&amp;keywords=antonio+damasio"> Antonio and Hannah Da Massio</a> have shown that we need cooperation between the emotional brain and the thinking brain in order to deal with the real world. They showed that people with brain injuries that left both their thinking and their emotional brains intact, but blocked them from cooperating with each other resulted in smart people with extremely poor judgment.</p>
<p>These people could do very well on IQ tests, and even give intelligent answers to questions like “How many giraffes are there in the United States” that require creative and complicated thinking strategies.</p>
<p>So, when I ran into several articles about overthinking, I already knew that placing too much emphasis on thinking and too little on feeling and emotions would lead to poor outcomes. So the word “overthinking” grabbed my attention.</p>
<p>The go-to book on overthinking is one called “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Women-Who-Think-Too-Much/dp/0805075259/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1368459003&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=women+who+think+too+muchhttp://">Women Who Think Too Much</a>” by Prof. Susan Noel-Hoeksema. (Why just women? She pointed out that women are more likely than men to overthink. That is true, but actually, the few available research <a href="http://www.refocuser.com/2009/08/9-ways-to-stop-overthinking-everything/">sources</a> indicate a small, though statistically significant difference. So the book is also useful for guys).</p>
<p>As I began working my way through the book, I was impressed, and I recommended it to Debbie.</p>
<p>But, eventually I saw that reading the book is like taking a ride on a roller coaster, with the excitement and fun of learning alternating with pages of tedium. (This was my experience, not necessarily the objective truth.)</p>
<p>The best thing about the book is that it is full of methods for reducing overthinking.</p>
<p>So, here is my take:</p>
<p><span id="more-1370"></span></p>
<p>What is overthinking? Professor Noel-Hoeksema describes it as “going over and over your negative thoughts and feelings, kneading them like dough. She applies the term the “yeast effect”.  “Just as yeasty bread dough will double in size after it’s been kneaded, our negative thoughts expand, grow, and begin to take up all the space around them in our minds.”</p>
<p>We have always emphasized the damaging effects of stress amplification in limiting resilience. That last thing you should do when times are harsh is to alienate your supporters, tear yourself down, exaggerate your hopelessness… You get the idea- when you are in a distressing situation, you need someone who is on your side, but also smart about what helps and what hurts.</p>
<p>Clearly it doesn’t sound like a good thing to overthink. Research has linked it to depression. “When sadness is amplified instead of managed, it can take you down paths to hopelessness, self-hate, and immobility.”</p>
<p>It also increases anxiety, which can lead to a nasty physiological and psychological avalanche, ending in chronic arousal that “wears down the body” and eventually makes it hard for you to deal with even mildly challenging situations. All we can say is “Amen”.</p>
<p>So what can you do about overthinking? Here is a mix of examples from her book and some others that we think are also useful:</p>
<ul>
<li>Look for interpretations of distressing events that are not as damning as the ones that first come to mind.  Could nasty, critical comments about you be wrong, even silly and more about the critic than about you?</li>
<li>You should accept and attend to your negative feelings. But don’t be ruled by them. This is possibly the most important thing you can learn about scary feelings; you can have them and just keep going with what you judge to be in your best interest.</li>
<li>Don’t wait for someone else to rescue you; get going on ways to take care of yourself. Focus on what you can do for yourself, and if someone else helps, be thankful for their caring, but realize that it is the delicious frosting on the cake.</li>
<li>Brainstorm for possible ways to change your situation. The first few solutions you come up with are probably a tiny fraction of what you can discover if you unleash your creativity.</li>
<li>Start with something small. Small change adds up.</li>
<li>Don’t let uncertainly stop you from acting. Move forward even though you are uncertain about whether your solution will work. Doing <strong><em>something</em></strong> at the very least gives you dignity.</li>
<li>When you are having catastrophic thoughts about yourself, ask if these thoughts are merely echoing the unsupportive words of others who spoke without looking out for your interests.</li>
<li>Focus on your <strong><em>feelings</em></strong>, attend to what you are feeling in your body. This is usually the best source of what you really need to know in order to find an answer that can help you.</li>
<li>Don’t forget to exercise, even if it is for only a few minutes per day. Exercise improves
<ul>
<li>Stress-related aspects of your physiology.</li>
<li>The positivity and clarity of your thoughts.</li>
<li>Your level of calmness.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F05%2F13%2Foverthinking-no-more%2F&amp;linkname=Overthinking%20No%20More." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Your Stress Responses and the Wisdom of the Body</title>
		<link>/2013/04/10/your-stress-responses-and-the-wisdom-of-the-body/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2013 04:13:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Genes and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1348</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In our last post, we discussed genetic variations that result in our having either a “worrier” or a “warrior” brain. We also mentioned that worriers can handle stress effectively, even function at the level of Navy Seals, if they are &#8230; <a href="/2013/04/10/your-stress-responses-and-the-wisdom-of-the-body/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In our last post, we discussed genetic variations that result in our having either a “worrier” or a “warrior” brain. We also mentioned that worriers can handle stress effectively, even function at the level of Navy Seals, if they are properly trained. Sufficiently trained, worriers can deal with demanding situations as well as warriors.</p>
<p>What makes this possible? Despite the bodily stress reactions we have that are inborn, how we <strong><em>interpret</em></strong> those reactions can dramatically shift how we react.</p>
<p><span id="more-1348"></span></p>
<p>In the early 1960s, two psychologists, <a href="http://faculty.babson.edu/krollag/org_site/soc_psych/schachter_epineph.html">Stanley Schachter and Jerome Singer</a> showed that <strong><em>cueing</em></strong> people about how to view their experiences can dramatically shift how they actually react.</p>
<p>Their studies were complex, but, basically, they assessed how the effects of a drug that produced high arousal (standard pharmaceutical adrenalin) changed, depending on the context in which the drug was administered.</p>
<p>If people injected with pharmaceutical adrenalin, which produces a typical stress response with rapid heart rate, sweating, and so forth), were in a situation in which a stooge feigned anger, they were more likely to be angry. If the stooge feigned euphoria, they became more silly and playful.</p>
<p>Anything that changes how we view our bodily reactions has the power to determine whether we end up distressed and defeated or end up feeling euphoric, or heaven knows what else. The point is that the physiological reaction is not the boss. It has a vote, but it’s not the boss.</p>
<p>So if you have powerful feelings and symptoms when you face stress, you can still fall back on your thought patterns to use that power to support you.</p>
<p>Bodily responses to life’s demands commonly provide protection from threats. So getting rid of those reactions is not necessarily a good path to resilience. <a href="http://digitalcommons.unl.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1215&amp;context=psychfacpub">Important research</a> shows that those who are resilient have physiological responses to stress as intense as those who are less resilient.</p>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fight-or-flight_response">Walter Cannon</a>, the scientist who first identified the “fight or flight” stress response did so in a book he entitled “The Wisdom of the Body”.  Wisdom? Can it be that these hated feelings we try to fight off when taking a difficult test, walking on stage to give a speech, etc. are based on bodily “wisdom”?</p>
<p>For example, isn’t your heart pounding rapidly bad for you?</p>
<p>Commonly it is not. Your heart pounds when you exercise vigorously, have sex or ride on a rollercoaster, and we don’t think of that as bad for you. The heart’s reaction during positive states can actually be more intense than it is during negative ones.</p>
<p>It <strong><em>can</em></strong> be bad for you if you have serious heart disease, but that doesn’t mean it’s bad for most of us. Exercise that pushes the heart to be fast and effective is commonly recommended to make us healthier.</p>
<p>The physiological reactions themselves can change depending on how we interpret them. For example, when we interpret something as manageable, our heart’s efficiency tends to increase and our blood vessels relax. When we view them as a threat beyond our control, the opposite happens.</p>
<p>Harvard Professor Jeremy Jamieson and his colleagues have done valuable <a href="http://wendyberrymendes.com/cms/uploads/CDPS_reappraisal-1.pdf">research</a> confirming that how we appraise or interpret our bodily reactions to demanding situations can determine how well we perform under stress.</p>
<p>For example, in one study, in a high-stakes testing situation half of the test-takers were told before the test that stress reactions we have during important, difficult tests predict better, not worse performance. They were also told that they should not feel concerned about their body’s reactions, but instead should remind themselves that this arousal could be helping them do well.</p>
<p>The group taught to see stress reactions as beneficial scored 65 points higher than controls!</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=&amp;linkname=" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Genetic Variants That Can Determine Whether We Have a “Worrier Brain” or A “Warrior Brain” and What We Can Do About Them.</title>
		<link>/2013/03/19/genetic-variants-that-can-determine-whether-we-have-a-worrier-brain-or-a-warrior-brain-and-what-we-can-do-about-them/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2013 15:16:31 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Genes and Resilience]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1338</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This post is based on an article I recently found in the New York Times. It makes several important claims: There are two variants of a specific gene that influence how quickly we recover from stressful experiences. We get one &#8230; <a href="/2013/03/19/genetic-variants-that-can-determine-whether-we-have-a-worrier-brain-or-a-warrior-brain-and-what-we-can-do-about-them/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This post is based on an <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/10/magazine/why-can-some-kids-handle-pressure-while-others-fall-apart.html?pagewanted=all&amp;_r=0">article</a> I recently found in the New York Times. It makes several important claims:</p>
<ol start="1">
<li>There are two variants of a specific gene that influence how quickly we recover from stressful experiences.</li>
<li>We get one from our mother and the other from our father.</li>
<li>The pattern of these genes we inherit determines whether we will be “worriers” or “warriors”.</li>
<li>Worriers are people who have to struggle with stressful experiences and warriors are people for whom stress reactions quickly pass by.</li>
<li>Whether we have the genetic pattern that gives us a warrior brain or a worrier brain, there is at least one simple technique that can make us deal efficiently with stress.</li>
</ol>
<p><span id="more-1338"></span></p>
<p>First, I want to acknowledge that I am skeptical about much of the brain-mind research that has come to be widely accepted. I don’t want to get into that because it is way too technical. But I often ask, “What good does it do for people dealing with a stress problem to learn that they were genetically doomed to have trouble with stressors, e.g.to be a worrier?”</p>
<p>Today, Debbie had an opening in her usually busy schedule, and called to chat.  I was trying to write this post, and I posed this question to her. She paused briefly, and then said “It helps people to understand why they have to struggle with things that other people handle with apparent ease.” Good answer.</p>
<p>So here is my condensed description of the genetic issue. Dopamine is a brain chemical that is released in the lower part of the frontal lobes of our brain. The sooner it is cleared out, the sooner we recover from the stress. This is because that lower frontal part of the brain can control the parts of the brain that produce responses that are “raw emotions”.</p>
<p>We all have a gene that determines how fast we clear Dopamine out of that part of our brain, and, as we said above, one variant leads to quicker, actually something like 40 times quicker, cleanup of the dopamine “mess”.</p>
<p>For people whose brains cleanup that mess slowly, their brains and minds are likely to be overwhelmed by the surge.</p>
<p>The following is an important part of this study: the effects of the slow acting system have been demonstrated in a real-life stressful situation. Young people in Taiwan take a test that has a major influence on the trajectory of their lives. Those with the slow acting system score on average 8 percent lower than those with the fast-acting system.</p>
<p>However, people with the slow acting gene can handle extreme stress as long as they are well-trained. Even some Navy Seals have worrier genes.</p>
<p>This concept that training can trump genetic effects (or lifelong bad habits) is right at the core of our belief in the value of resilience training.</p>
<p>What kind of training do people with worrier brains need to function as well as those with warrior brains?</p>
<ul>
<li>Exposure to stress challenges. Worriers need to be taxed without being overwhelmed, and then have time for recovery. “Training, preparation, and repetition defuse the worrier’s curse”.</li>
<li>Labeling of stress can determine reactions to it. If worriers see their feelings of stress as something that can improve their performance, their performance improves. They learn to view the feelings we usually call “stress” as “excitement”.</li>
</ul>
<p>We plan to deal with the effects of such labeling or “reappraisal” in a future post.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=&amp;linkname=" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Can Foreseeing a Dark Future Result in Less Disability and Lower Likelihood of Death?</title>
		<link>/2013/03/07/can-foreseeing-a-dark-future-result-in-less-disability-and-lower-likelihood-of-death/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2013 18:16:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Harvard Grant Study]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1334</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[About a week ago, Debbie came back from her morning run and said she heard on the radio that a study had been published supporting the idea that pessimism is more conducive to physical health than optimism. She went on &#8230; <a href="/2013/03/07/can-foreseeing-a-dark-future-result-in-less-disability-and-lower-likelihood-of-death/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>About a week ago, Debbie came back from her morning run and said she heard on the radio that a study had been published supporting the idea that pessimism is more conducive to physical health than optimism.</p>
<p>She went on to say that, based on the description of what was being called “pessimism”, it struck her as “anticipation”, which is a well-known successful way of coping with life. Anticipation means looking ahead to the future so that you can avoid being blind-sided by events.</p>
<p>There is abundant research showing that optimism is much more helpful than pessimism, e.g. this article. If there are circumstances in which pessimism beats optimism, we need to know about them.</p>
<p>In this post we will tell you about the results of our search for the details of this study and our interpretation of the results.</p>
<p><span id="more-1334"></span></p>
<p>Please be patient; it will take a few paragraphs to explain how the study was done.</p>
<p>It was done on a representative sample of 10,000 Germans. This means that they had an unusually large sample and respondents were selected in a pattern that matched the population of their country. Participants were tested and retested for eleven years. Most studies are one-shot deals, so duration of the study is a plus.</p>
<p>They were asked at the beginning of the study and in each subsequent year to rate their current quality of life, and to predict the quality of life they expected five years in the future.</p>
<p>If they predicted less life satisfaction than actually occurred, they were categorized as pessimistic (a pretty good common sense measure of optimism versus pessimism).</p>
<p>If their actual life satisfaction was worse than they had predicted, they were deemed optimistic; their expectations were more positive than what really happened. If they accurately predicted their future life satisfaction, they were deemed realistic.</p>
<p>The study divided participants in age categories ranging from Young adults (18-39 years), Middle-aged adults (40-64 years), and Older adults (65+ years).</p>
<p>Their outcome measures, i.e. what the study sought to predict, was disability or death.</p>
<p>They found that “Older adults” who underestimated how satisfying their future lives would be had less disability or death than those who were optimistic or realistic in their predictions. However, this worked only for the older adults, and the people rated as pessimistic were only 2 to 3 percent less likely to be disabled or dead than realists or optimists. In addition, the older adult sample included 856 people, whereas the other age groups each included 3 to 4 thousand.</p>
<p>Conclusion</p>
<p>This study had an unusual measure of optimism versus pessimism. A much more tested one, which is a very good predictor of future health can be found here. It is free, and you can take it and score it yourself.</p>
<p>The years from 65 up are a period of rapid change, much like the years from birth to young adulthood. Older people routinely have parents, friends, relatives, etc. they have seen develop various illnesses and losing a range of capacities they once had, and also dying. A common lament of older people is that so many, or even all, of their friends have died. And many worry about observed loss of various cognitive function, e.g. “a senior moment”.</p>
<p>An older adult who is alert is likely to realize what is in their future, and prepare for it. That is anticipation. I think Debbie had it right.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F03%2F07%2Fcan-foreseeing-a-dark-future-result-in-less-disability-and-lower-likelihood-of-death%2F&amp;linkname=Can%20Foreseeing%20a%20Dark%20Future%20Result%20in%20Less%20Disability%20and%20Lower%20Likelihood%20of%20Death%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Does Secure Attachment to Others Lead to High Resilience?</title>
		<link>/2013/02/21/does-secure-attachment-to-others-lead-to-high-resilience/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2013 04:15:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[How Hard Is It To Change Resilience?]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1321</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[There is interesting research showing that how securely we attach to our caregivers as young children plays an important role in our resilience as adults. Children who develop a secure attachment to their mother (or other caregiver) tend, as adults, &#8230; <a href="/2013/02/21/does-secure-attachment-to-others-lead-to-high-resilience/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There is interesting research showing that how securely we attach to our caregivers as young children plays an important role in our resilience as adults. Children who develop a secure attachment to their mother (or other caregiver) tend, as adults, to be resilient in the face of challenges.</p>
<p>Does this mean that your level of resilience became a settled matter when you were little, and nothing can be done about it now? We don’t think so.</p>
<p><span id="more-1321"></span></p>
<p>Attachment style is developed in very early childhood, and has been extensively studied. Usually there are deemed to be three basic styles, Secure, Anxious-Ambivalent, and Avoidant. This attachment style developed in early childhood appears to stay with us throughout our lives.</p>
<p>Those who are “Secure”, apparently had a good fit between their inborn temperament and parental responses that enabled them to build inner resources. These inner resources enable them to connect well with others, and to feel confident in potentially scary, unfamiliar environments. Both the Anxious-Ambivalent and the Avoidant people are less effective in dealing with such environments.</p>
<p>Avoidant people appear to be comfortable without close relationships, and avoid dependency on others. This is viewed as a defense, and can, under enough distress, break down.</p>
<p>Avoidant people may seem to be secure unless the environment is too challenging, and under those circumstances, they can seem more like those who are Anxious-Ambivalent.</p>
<p>Anxious-Ambivalent people long for emotionally close relationships, but tend to feel uncomfortable with them. It is hard for them to trust or depend on others.</p>
<p>For our purposes here, we can look at those who are just “Secure” or “Non-Secure”.</p>
<p>Mario Mikulincer and Victor Florian have <a href="http://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=hWe5-aSgZmcC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA143&amp;dq=mikulincer+florian&amp;ots=zjtx_xOZK5&amp;sig=KVc2PtHo1ap0q86eXi5AyA9k3SU#v=onepage&amp;q=mikulincer%20florian&amp;f=false (">summarized the research on how Secures and Non-Secures react to a wide range of demanding circumstances</a>, and have consistently shown that Secures are more resilient than Non-Secures.</p>
<p>Their review includes studies of reactions to significant life challenges. Very consistently they indicate that Secures handle such challenges better than Non-Secures. Here are examples:</p>
<ul>
<li>In the military training, Anxious Ambivalents perceived more threat, felt a greater sense of personal inadequacy and helplessness in dealing with the training.</li>
<li>When facing the threat of death, Secures had less fear.</li>
<li>In time of war, when threatened with missile attacks, Secures sought more support from others and had fewer symptoms of post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD).</li>
<li>Prisoners of War who were Secures had fewer symptoms of PTSD than Non Secures.</li>
<li>Secures handled loss of significant others better than Non-Secures.</li>
<li>In experiments testing reactions to personal failure, Secures handled the failures better.</li>
<li>Women facing the challenges of new <strong>motherhood </strong>who were secure handled them better than non-secures.</li>
<li>Mothers with handicapped children dealt with the extra challenges better if they were Secures.</li>
<li>People coping with chronic pain who are secure react much more effectively than those who are insecure.</li>
</ul>
<p>So, here is more evidence that resilience helps us deal with life’s challenges. But, if attachment style is determined when we are no more than toddlers, doesn’t it seem we are either blessed or doomed by early experiences to be resilient or not?</p>
<p>One interesting fact in the work of Mikulincer and Florian provides considerable room for hope. In Israel, during the first Persian Gulf War, some people had to deal with Scuds missile attacks. They had to face the possibility of instant death, and had no personal control over the source of that threat.</p>
<p>Yet the less resilient people reacted the same way as those who were resilient. Why? Presumably because public service messages consistently told them to check on each other during and after the attacks. With these instructions, anxious ambivalent and avoidant people reacted by reaching out to others, just as secure people would likely have done without the instructions.</p>
<p>So mere instructions from the government were able to override the knee jerk reactions of insecures to either hem and haw (anxious-ambivalents) or deal with the threats solely on their own (avoidant).</p>
<p>We can reasonably expect that real resilience training can be even more effective than mere instructions.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F02%2F21%2Fdoes-secure-attachment-to-others-lead-to-high-resilience%2F&amp;linkname=Does%20Secure%20Attachment%20to%20Others%20Lead%20to%20High%20Resilience%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Some Things You Can Learn From Abraham Lincoln about How to Manage Your Life.</title>
		<link>/2013/02/05/some-things-you-can-learn-from-abraham-lincoln-about-how-to-manage-your-life/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2013 18:08:12 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1307</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[A recent article in the New York Times showed that Abraham Lincoln’s methods of managing the country can serve as a guide to managing a business. It struck me that each of us is the CEO of her or his &#8230; <a href="/2013/02/05/some-things-you-can-learn-from-abraham-lincoln-about-how-to-manage-your-life/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A <a href="../Dropbox/New%20folder/Abraham%20Lincoln,%20as%20Management%20Guru%20-%20NYTimes.com.htm">recent article</a> in the New York Times showed that Abraham Lincoln’s methods of managing the country can serve as a guide to managing a business.</p>
<p>It struck me that each of us is the CEO of her or his own life. Could it be that Lincoln’s way of managing the country can teach us something about managing our own lives?</p>
<p>I think it can, and the purpose of this post is to explain why I believe that, and to show how you can try it out.</p>
<p><span id="more-1307"></span></p>
<p>At one point in the New York Times article, it pointed out that Lincoln displayed the ability to learn and grow amidst great calamity. I had never thought of it this way, but that is really a pretty good way to describe resilience.</p>
<p>People who are not resilient cannot “learn and grow amidst great calamity”, largely because, in the face of calamity, they tend to do things that amplify and spread the impact of the calamity. Don’t do that!</p>
<p>We have to train ourselves to minimize the impact of calamity. Otherwise, all of our mental resources are drained as we imagine catastrophic possible outcomes, focus on who is to blame, or consult with people who will concur with our worst expectations about what is going to happen.</p>
<p>It is important to practice talking to yourself in an optimistic and hopeful way rather than catastrophizing over imagined bad outcomes, most of which never happen.</p>
<p>You should train yourself to relax enough to keep a clear head when things go badly. There are many ways to relax deeply; a very simple, easy one is <a href="/2010/12/06/a-key-step-in-resilience-training-is-learning-deep-relaxation/">here</a>. All you have to do is get in a reasonably quiet place, then listen the audio, following the instructions. It’s best to do that regularly for a few weeks, and then use it as needed.</p>
<p>Lincoln suffered from horrible losses while he was taking responsibility for the Civil War. His generals failed him, sometimes miserably. His 11 year old son died, triggering events that deprived him of much support from his wife, instead demanding that he direct his personal resources to helping her get through the pain and distress, when he must have had few resources to spare.</p>
<p>He also suffered from severe depression. Still, he continued to make effective and responsible decisions. He exemplified an important aspect of resilience: we are not ruled by our moods and emotions. We can let ourselves be aware of them yet still know that they are not the arbiters of reality and we are not enslaved by them.</p>
<p>It is easy to say that we are not ruled by our moods and emotions, but putting that view into practice is hard, and is best done by regularly training yourself to have a clear sense that feelings are there, but they are just feelings that come and go.</p>
<p>Meditation is a path to developing clarity about the role of our emotions. Currently “mindfulness meditation” is very much in vogue, and it works. <a href="/2011/03/02/basic-mindfulness-technique/">Here</a> is a short description of a way to do this kind of meditation.</p>
<p>Lincoln tended to ponder a great deal before making decisions. He did not just lock himself in a room and think about how to turn facts he already knew into a decision. He sought out the views of others, making sure that a wide range of perspectives were included in the raw material he used for making decisions.</p>
<p>This does not mean that he ended up indecisive. He distilled those many perspectives into the closest thing to realism he could reach and then made his decisions firmly.</p>
<p>For all of us, it can be tempting to avoid information that might not fit into our mental model of the world. Sometimes that works for a while, but sooner or later we have to face reality. Lincoln provides a good template for how to reach the best match to reality you can.</p>
<p>Notice that Lincoln understood the importance of reaching out to others. This is an important aspect of living well.</p>
<p>One last principle for managing our lives gleaned from Lincoln is that we should stay true to a higher purpose. I recall many years ago reading about psychologist, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abraham_Maslow">Abraham Maslow</a>, who pointed out that many of the people who came to him for treatment really did not have an illness. He felt that they just needed to “take on a task worthy of themselves”.</p>
<p>Now I know many readers will believe that they cannot have such lofty goals, that all they have the time and energy for is to slog through wretched days that come upon them. Contrary to that belief, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viktor_Frankl">Victor Frankl</a> pointed out that finding meaning in life as a prisoner in a Nazi Concentration Camp was essential to survival.</p>
<p>It’s very doubtful that our painful situations are as bad as one of those camps. And finding meaning in your life will not drain you. It will energize you.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F02%2F05%2F1307%2F&amp;linkname=" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
