<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Avoiding Self-Criticism &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/avoiding-self-criticism/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>A Path Beyond Self-Criticism to Loving Kindness</title>
		<link>/2014/02/01/a-path-beyond-self-criticism-to-loving-kindness/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2014 23:21:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Self-Criticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Compassion]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1604</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[One of the keys to feeling and functioning better lies in how we talk to ourselves. By changing our self-talk, we can alter both our feelings and our behavior. This is not mere opinion. Psychological research has confirmed it for &#8230; <a href="/2014/02/01/a-path-beyond-self-criticism-to-loving-kindness/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One of the keys to feeling and functioning better lies in how we talk to ourselves. By changing our self-talk, we can alter both our feelings and our behavior. This is not mere opinion. Psychological research has confirmed it for many years, even decades.</p>
<p>Many people believe that talking to themselves in nasty, critical ways will keep them in line, and somehow make them safe and prevent criticism from others. But it is in fact very damaging to your resilience, and is at the heart of our second most important factor influencing resilience.</p>
<p>We have already done a number of posts on reducing self-criticism (for example,click <a href="/2013/07/10/resilience-factor-two-hypersensitivity-self-criticism-and-what-you-can-do-about-them/">here</a>), so there is no need to repeat ourselves. In brief, you have to become more aware of your self-critical remarks, then challenge them and devise more supportive remarks that are closer to the truth and/or more useful ways of thinking about yourself and the world.</p>
<p>This second factor was a problem because it had to be scored in “reverse”. That means you are less resilient the higher you score on that factor. When you criticize and tear yourself down, you make your reactions to stress worse, and that is the opposite of resilience.</p>
<p>We have long searched for the positive pole of this factor. When research on self-compassion came to our attention, it seemed to be that positive pole. But, more recently, we have realized that reducing self-criticism, which is very valuable, is, nevertheless, only a step in the direction of self-compassion.</p>
<p>To be compassionate toward yourself you have to go beyond reducing self-criticism and learn to be loving, caring, and understanding toward yourself.</p>
<p>In this series of posts, we are focused on taking steps beyond mere “sweet talk”, showing specific methods for getting to where you need to go.</p>
<p>For this post, we have chosen the Buddhist method of developing loving kindness toward yourself, then including others, then more and more of the beings in our world. This has worked for meditators for centuries, but there have also been quite a few experimental tests supporting the idea that it works.</p>
<p>The Buddha emphasized that you need only believe things that, when you try them, work out in your own life. So give this a try and decide for yourself.</p>
<p>We owe this video to the capabilities and generosity of <a title="Sharon Salzberg" href="http://www.sharonsalzberg.com/">Sharon Salzberg</a>. (Expect a pretty long time lag before the video shows).</p>
<p><iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/W3uLqt69VyI" frameborder="0" width="560" height="315"></iframe></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F02%2F01%2Fa-path-beyond-self-criticism-to-loving-kindness%2F&amp;linkname=A%20Path%20Beyond%20Self-Criticism%20to%20Loving%20Kindness" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Some Common Ways People Make Stress Worse</title>
		<link>/2014/01/08/some-common-ways-people-make-stress-worse/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2014 18:52:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Self-Criticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1568</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Rather than soothing themselves, it is very common for people to react to stress in ways that make things worse. Here are two key reactions that amplify instead minimizing reactions to stress: To treat yourself in ways that increase the &#8230; <a href="/2014/01/08/some-common-ways-people-make-stress-worse/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rather than soothing themselves, it is very common for people to react to stress in ways that make things worse. Here are two key reactions that amplify instead minimizing reactions to stress:</p>
<ol start="1">
<li>To treat yourself in ways that increase the stress or undermine your ability to cope with it. Usually this involves exaggerating the power of the stressful event or blaming and attacking yourself, thus turning your capacity for aggression against yourself at the very time when you need to hear a supportive, helpful voice, even if it is your own voice.</li>
<li>To treat people who are likely sources of help in ways that lead them to withdraw their support, or even to strike back at you and pile on another source of stress.</li>
</ol>
<p>There are two main ways you can treat yourself that make things worse.  You can:</p>
<p>1.            Catastrophize</p>
<p>2.            Attack yourself with criticism</p>
<p>In this post we will discuss the first of these ways, those involved in how you treat yourself. We will also explain what you can do to avoid undermining of yourself.</p>
<p>In later posts we will cover the issues about 1. overcoming any tendency you may have to criticize yourself, and 2. Learning how to help your supporters support you.</p>
<p><span id="more-1568"></span></p>
<p>Catastrophizing has to do with the ways you talk to yourself when trouble comes your way.</p>
<p>A person who amplifies stress might say that what has happened is not just bad. It is “awful” “outrageous” “unbearable”, “catastrophic”. You can probably extend this list yourself. It is basically a matter of over-estimating the power of the distressing event.</p>
<p>The antidote is to learn to tell yourself, more realistically, that you “really don’t like this, but can manage it”, “hate it, but have enough grit to deal with it” or that it is “inconvenient”,“annoying”, or “hurtful” but not catastrophic.</p>
<p>Basically, to escape the pattern of catastrophizing is a matter of examining and disputing the evidence you have in favor of the idea that “This is catastrophic”. If you are catastrophizing, that evidence will be slim or even missing. If so, you have to develop a more realistic interpretation of what happened, and then find more useful self-statements.</p>
<p>Then you must resolutely guide your mind to the interpretations that are more realistic and more helpful.</p>
<p>If you have a habit of catastrophizing, you may have to “drill the new interpretations into your head”, repeatedly drawing your mind back to them whenever it drifts to the more familiar, catastrophizing mode.</p>
<p>Whenever you find yourself catastrophizing, you can say “This is my cue to start talking to myself in more realistic and more helpful ways”.</p>
<p>No one learns in primary school that how you talk to yourself has a major effect on how you react to the events of your life. That is too bad. The reality of this has been understood since ancient times, and repeatedly rediscovered. Currently it is an approach that psychotherapists have found helpful over many years, supported with a substantial body of scientific research. It goes under various names, such as “cognitive therapy” or “cognitive behavioral therapy”.</p>
<p>You may need help from a therapist to change your habitual way of dealing with yourself, but often you can improve substantially on your own.  If self-help doesn’t work, consider getting help from a therapist. If you think that implies that you are “crazy”, you are amazingly out of date.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why Do So Many Successful People Praise Failure?</title>
		<link>/2013/09/11/why-do-so-many-successful-people-praise-failure/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2013 03:23:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Self-Criticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Compassion]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1479</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Nobody wants to fail, or, worse, BE a failure. Failure is associated with shame, financial ruin, living a harder life, diminished status, not being able to contribute to your family’s resources.… Yet, we often see and hear what appears to &#8230; <a href="/2013/09/11/why-do-so-many-successful-people-praise-failure/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Nobody wants to fail, or, worse, BE a failure. Failure is associated with shame, financial ruin, living a harder life, diminished status, not being able to contribute to your family’s resources.…</p>
<p>Yet, we often see and hear what appears to be praise for failure. What could this be about?</p>
<p><span id="more-1479"></span></p>
<p>People who praise failure are not really talking about a lust for failure; they are talking about an important role of failure in teaching paths to success.</p>
<p>They are also talking about how avoidance of failure, or refusal to acknowledge failure can keep you from understanding what went wrong with your ineffective tries, and thus from seeing how to do better.</p>
<p>Here is an example: Debbie and I often watch Fareed Zakaria’s weekly TV show, “<a href="http://globalpublicsquare.blogs.cnn.com/category/gps-episodes/">GPS</a>” (Global Public Square).  A week or so ago, he interviewed Sara Blakely, an attractive young woman who went from cold call sales of copy machines to creating a business that made her a billionaire. She invented Spanx, an undergarment  she says makes women look better. Obviously many women agree with her.</p>
<p>In that interview, Ms. Blakely talked about the important role of her father in teaching her what it takes to succeed. He taught his children to boldly try new things, and, when they failed praised them for the try and gave them a “high five”.  He taught them not to avoid risk, and to see failure as a positive aspect of life, a key aspect of adaptation to the world as it is.</p>
<p>When Charlie Rose interviewed renowned golf champion, Ben Hogan, he asked Hogan about how he reacted to one of his greatest tournament failures. Hogan said it was the best thing that ever happened to him.  He embraced his mistakes, and learned from them. Many other golf masters have made similar comments.</p>
<p>Placed in the context of the resilience factors we have been discussing in the recent blog posts, these highly accomplished people are expressing  attitudes that are resilient with respect to Factor One (Resilient Attitudes and Skills).  They respond to failures with resilient attitudes  of <span style="text-decoration: underline;">positivity</span> and <span style="text-decoration: underline;">a problem-solving perspective</span>.</p>
<p>In addition, they do not cut their legs out from under themselves with unreasonable self-criticism. So they have resilient qualities reflected in Factor Two (Self-Compassion versus Self-Criticism).</p>
<p>So what the “pro-failure” people are really saying is that we need to grant ourselves the space to learn from our mistakes. If we pass up opportunities in order to avoid risk, or deny our role in failure, we will not learn to adapt to the world we live in.</p>
<p>Making mistakes does not make us “losers”, but we have the option of interpreting our mistakes either in ways that make us lose or in ways that help us win.</p>
<p>Once again, we see the power of “<a href="/2013/04/25/how-to-teach-your-worrier-brain-to-function-like-a-warrior-brain/">Reappraisal</a>”. If we see failure as an opportunity to learn, failure can be a positive influence. If we see it as humiliating, even unspeakable, or give ourselves no option other than to deny that it was our mistake, our adaptation to life will be thwarted.</p>
<p>We do not have to be afraid of making mistakes. Dealing with them is a known path to doing better in life.</p>
<p>Zorba the Greek said “Life is trouble. Only death is not. To be alive is to undo your belt and *look* for trouble.”</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F09%2F11%2Fwhy-do-so-many-successful-people-praise-failure%2F&amp;linkname=Why%20Do%20So%20Many%20Successful%20People%20Praise%20Failure%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Resilience Factor Two: Hypersensitivity, Self-Criticism and What You Can Do About Them.</title>
		<link>/2013/07/10/resilience-factor-two-hypersensitivity-self-criticism-and-what-you-can-do-about-them/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2013 03:03:36 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Hypersensitivity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Perfectionism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Self-Criticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Compassion]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1413</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The second most important resilience factor has to do with some very self-defeating things that people do that make them less resilient. It involves amplifying stress instead of getting it in control. I see it all the time; something distressing &#8230; <a href="/2013/07/10/resilience-factor-two-hypersensitivity-self-criticism-and-what-you-can-do-about-them/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The second most important resilience factor has to do with some very self-defeating things that people do that make them less resilient. It involves amplifying stress instead of getting it in control.</p>
<p>I see it all the time; something distressing happens and people react by tearing themselves down with self-criticism, and often go on to spread the criticism to, and generate fights with the very people who could help them recover quickly, which would be the path of resilience and both mental and physical health.</p>
<p>The core pattern of the factor was over-reacting to even small errors or failings by worrying about what we have done and how other people might react to our missteps. This leads to worrying about and criticizing ourselves for real or imagined failings.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QE1vnHfOcnU">This animation</a>, voiced by Jennifer Lopez, may help you to see the kinds of criticisms and attacks we have in mind. Similar examples can be found <a href="/2011/03/22/self-compassion-and-resilience/">here</a>.</p>
<p><span id="more-1413"></span></p>
<p>Our focus is on resilience, the positive things you can do to deal with stress and live a better life, so we are not interested in lamenting what is wrong with things we do, but with how we stay strong, healthy, and live well even if we have messed up.</p>
<p>We pondered and discussed Factor 2 (which we dubbed, perhaps clumsily, “Hypersensitivity, Self-Criticism/Perfectionism) for many years, frequently attempting to pinpoint the positive, resilience-promoting patterns implied by its negative, depleting ways.</p>
<p>Doing this blog and constantly looking for new approaches to enhance resilience led us to see what that resilience-promoting factor was.</p>
<p>We discovered an important body of research on self-compassion. If you are self-compassionate, you are not likely to be severely and unreasonably critical of your mistakes.</p>
<p>Self-compassion is the closest we are likely to find to the opposite of the intense and unreasonable self-criticism and demanding perfectionism reflected in Factor 2.</p>
<p>To give you a better sense of what factor two is about, here are some patterns embedded in it.</p>
<p>If you change on any of these patterns, you are also changing your standing on the factor itself. Here are more details:</p>
<ul>
<li>Self-Evaluations that are Critical and Unreasonably Demanding versus Reasonable Self-Compassion, and Realistic yet Loving, and Accepting Self-Evaluations.</li>
<li>Worry/Rumination versus, Focusing on the Present, and Taking Things One at a Time.</li>
<li>Unreasonable Expectations/Perfectionism. The more resilient polarity of this is recognizing that we all have limitations and that errors are natural in human life and deserve compassion. Failures, handled well, can even help by teaching us better ways of managing our lives.</li>
</ul>
<p>Knowing the factors is useful, but knowing ways you can change where you stand on them is more important. In a number of our previous blog posts we have discussed what to do if you need to improve on these patterns:</p>
<ol start="1">
<li>Learn how to offer yourself warmth and non-judgmental understanding rather than belittling your pain or berating yourself with self-criticism. <a href="/2012/01/03/from-negative-thinking-and-self-criticism-to-positive-thinking-and-self-compassion/?#more-891">This previous post</a> explains a useful way to reduce your self-negativity.</li>
<li>The ordinary human mind is chaotic; there is ancient expression that “The mind is a drunken monkey”. If you are a strong self-critic, you need to help yourself become more even-minded, and meditation will do that. <a href="/2011/03/02/basic-mindfulness-technique/">Here</a> is one of our earlier posts on a very popular, effective method of meditation.</li>
<li>Some things you can do to help with perfectionism are in <a href="/2011/02/20/to-increase-your-resilience-avoid-being-too-hard-on-yourself/">this post</a>.</li>
</ol>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=&amp;linkname=Resilience%20Factor%20Two%3A%20Hypersensitivity%2C%20Self-Criticism%20and%20What%20You%20Can%20Do%20About%20Them." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Depressed, Anxious, Being Hard on Yourself? New Insights about the Value of Learning to Be both Self-Compassionate and Self-Soothing.</title>
		<link>/2012/02/16/depressed-anxious-being-hard-on-yourself-new-insights-about-the-value-of-learning-to-be-both-self-compassionate-and-self-soothing/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2012 04:10:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Self-Criticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mindfulness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Physical Contact]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Compassion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=956</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Most of us are aware that we have an inner critic that can make it hard to enjoy life, and, in the more severe instances, induce such things as anxiety and depression. We have written several posts about the inner &#8230; <a href="/2012/02/16/depressed-anxious-being-hard-on-yourself-new-insights-about-the-value-of-learning-to-be-both-self-compassionate-and-self-soothing/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Most of us are aware that we have an inner critic that can make it hard to enjoy life, and, in the more severe instances, induce such things as anxiety and depression.</p>
<p>We have written several posts about the inner critic and how to deal with it through changing your inner self-talk.</p>
<p>We have also encouraged the use of <em>mindfulness meditation. </em>With mindfulness we observe the flow of our experiences with compassion and acceptance, the opposite of self-criticism.</p>
<p>This post is about an important new insight into what it may take to stop unhelpful self-criticism. It involves learning to be compassionate toward the inner critic, which is, after all, an aspect of ourselves. This means to understand that the self-criticism is something you learned in order to adapt to the environment in which you grew up.</p>
<p>In addition we must also learn ways to sooth ourselves.</p>
<p><span id="more-956"></span></p>
<p>According to British psychologist, <a href="http://www.compassionatemind.co.uk/resources/Compassion_Group_Therapy_Paper.pdf">Paul Gilbert</a>, besides reducing the critical self-talk, we need to shift from feelings of “self-directed hostility, contempt, and self-loathing” to   “feelings of self-reassurance, warmth, and self-soothing”.</p>
<p>“Some high self-critics could understand the logic of CBT and generate alternative thoughts to self-criticism but rarely felt reassured by such efforts”.  (CBT is cognitive behavior therapy; a self-help version can be found <a href="../../../../../2011/02/20/to-increase-your-resilience-avoid-being-too-hard-on-yourself/">here</a>.)</p>
<p>In his view, besides changing our self-talk, many of us need to learn ways to sooth ourselves, and thus to experience the warm feelings that accompany self-compassion and self-soothing.</p>
<p>But how do we do that?  Check out our post on “<a href="../../../../../2010/11/04/natural-stress-defeaters/">Natural Stress Defeaters</a>” for some simple methods of self-soothing that have worked for others, and that you can easily bring into your own life. Also <a href="../../../../../2010/12/06/a-key-step-in-resilience-training-is-learning-deep-relaxation/">deep relaxation</a> produces feelings of relaxation and warmth, and it, too, is easy to fit into your life. The previous link has a free audio that is designed to help you to feel warmer and more at peace.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.compassionatemind.co.uk/8.html">Dr. Gilbert</a> provides many mental exercises crafted to induce the desired feelings of warmth and peacefulness. They can be found in his book “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Compassionate-Mind-Approach-Lifes-Challenges/dp/1572248408/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1329364432&amp;sr=1-1">The Compassionate Mind</a>”.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2012%2F02%2F16%2Fdepressed-anxious-being-hard-on-yourself-new-insights-about-the-value-of-learning-to-be-both-self-compassionate-and-self-soothing%2F&amp;linkname=Depressed%2C%20Anxious%2C%20Being%20Hard%20on%20Yourself%3F%20New%20Insights%20about%20the%20Value%20of%20Learning%20to%20Be%20both%20Self-Compassionate%20and%20Self-Soothing." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>From Negative Thinking and Self-Criticism to Positive Thinking and Self-Compassion</title>
		<link>/2012/01/03/from-negative-thinking-and-self-criticism-to-positive-thinking-and-self-compassion/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2012 16:41:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Self-Criticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Compassion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=891</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In this post we provide some guidance on how to deal with your inner critic. Being self-critical rather than being compassionate toward yourself is the second greatest component of resilience. Yet most people suffer from the persistent though often questionable &#8230; <a href="/2012/01/03/from-negative-thinking-and-self-criticism-to-positive-thinking-and-self-compassion/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this post we provide some guidance on how to deal with your inner critic. Being self-critical rather than being compassionate toward yourself is the second greatest component of resilience. Yet most people suffer from the persistent though often questionable claims of their “inner critic”.</p>
<p>This <a href=" http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QE1vnHfOcnU" target="_self">video</a> exposes the inner critic at work.</p>
<p>When I first heard the criticisms in this animation, I was almost overwhelmed by them. It took a while for me to see how to fight back against them. It is one thing to hear the words, but the emotional tone greatly intensifies their power.</p>
<p>Lest you think this is an unrealistic portrayal of self-criticism, here are things Major League pitchers used to describe themselves: “idiot,” “loser,” “dummy,” “gutless,” and “I stink,” “I can’t,” “I don’t have it,” and “I’m clueless.” Keep in mind that major league pitchers are a VERY highly selected for their outstanding talent and performance.</p>
<p>Obviously, it is demoralizing to have statements like these hurled at you, even though you are the person who hurls them.</p>
<p>The legendary Rabbi Hillel said “”If I am not for myself, who will be for me? And if I am only for myself, what am I? And if not now, when?”</p>
<p>Almost anyone can see this is wisdom in its clearest form. Yet, so many of us are not “for ourselves”.</p>
<p>What can we do about this?</p>
<p><span id="more-891"></span></p>
<p>The research and clinical experience of psychologists shows us several ways to deal with negativity and self-criticism.</p>
<ol>
<li>First we have to bring our      negative, self-critical  thoughts      into the light of consciousness in order to learn whether they make sense      and have a reasonable claim to guiding us.</li>
<li>Next we have to target the      ones that undermine us the most, and boldly question whether they are      solidly based In reality and can lead to realistic changes in how we live our      lives.</li>
</ol>
<p>Take the accusation, <strong><em>“You’re too fat”</em></strong>.</p>
<p>Is it true? Anorexics think they are too fat, and they are as emaciated as people in concentration camps; they are literally starving themselves to death.</p>
<p>I used to teach college classes that included the topics of obesity and weight control. Students, particularly women, who appeared to be of normal weight seemed more intensely interested in this topic than any other that I covered.</p>
<p>Even if we are overweight, shouldn’t people be judged by the content of their character, not the appearance of their body?</p>
<p>Assuming you rationally decide you’re too fat, what good is it to criticize yourself? People can spend a lifetime telling themselves they are too fat, and still gain weight all along. What evidence is there that attacking yourself helps you lose fat? There is actually a lot of evidence that such “aversive control” is remarkably ineffective.</p>
<p>There is also a lot of evidence that our thoughts are often a poor reflection of reality. We fail miserably to estimate how bad we will feel when things fail to go the way we want, and how good we will feel when things go the way we want them to go. Nobel prize winning psychologist Daniel Kahneman has written a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Thinking-Fast-Slow-Daniel-Kahneman/dp/0374275637/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1325608360&amp;sr=8-1">currently best-selling book</a> chock full of examples of how far our minds fall short of what is real. So if our thoughts aren’t USEFUL to us, it makes sense to question their value.</p>
<p>The accusation <strong><em>“You’re stupid. STUPID!”</em></strong></p>
<p>What is the evidence for this? Did you get adequate grades in school? Is there <em>anything </em>you do competently? On the surface this accusation sounds like an assessment of your intelligence, but the underlying meaning is that the critic despises you and wants to undermine your confidence.</p>
<p>And <strong><em>“You’re too ugly, to short, no fun. Loser! LOSER!!”</em></strong></p>
<p>Hmm. To me these accusations follow a familiar pattern in which someone grabs anything they can think of to hurt you. Sometimes they even say irrelevant things Like “Your uncle John is a liar and a thief!”</p>
<p>The novelist, Somerset Maugham had a club foot. He once said that when he was in conflict with others, they had all, without exception, made mention of his club foot. When attacking others or themselves people tend to reach for anything, real or imagined, that is likely to hurt.</p>
<p>Many people think that they have to be self-critical lest they become under-achievers. The evidence for this is, to say the least, weak.</p>
<p>On the other hand, the opposite of self-criticism, <strong><em>self-compassion</em></strong>, is known to have positive results. Here are the two best things you can do to shift from self-criticism to self-compassion:</p>
<ol>
<li>Train yourself to critique      the claims of you inner critic.</li>
<li>Develop and put into      practice skills of <a href="/2010/11/04/natural-stress-defeaters/" target="_self">self-soothing</a>.</li>
</ol>
<p>To deal effectively with life, we must learn to reject unsupported claims against us, even when they come from inside our heads, and to develop habits of calming and soothing ourselves.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2012%2F01%2F03%2Ffrom-negative-thinking-and-self-criticism-to-positive-thinking-and-self-compassion%2F&amp;linkname=From%20Negative%20Thinking%20and%20Self-Criticism%20to%20Positive%20Thinking%20and%20Self-Compassion" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sleeplessness: Should You Medicate of Meditate?</title>
		<link>/2011/11/15/sleeplessness-should-you-medicate-of-meditate/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2011 16:28:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Perfectionism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Self-Criticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mindfulness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Understanding]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Women's Resilience]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=858</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I think it is safe to say that a large majority of us gravely underestimate the powers of our minds and overestimate the powers of medicine. Whether your problem is sleeplessness, pain or some other potentially overwhelming challenge, your mind, &#8230; <a href="/2011/11/15/sleeplessness-should-you-medicate-of-meditate/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think it is safe to say that a large majority of us gravely underestimate the powers of our minds and overestimate the powers of medicine. Whether your problem is sleeplessness, pain or some other potentially overwhelming challenge, your mind, especially if you train and develop its powers, can work wonders in corralling and controlling your problem.</p>
<p>Fortunately the title of this post implies a false dichotomy. Why not meditate AND medicate? Why not do what you can to control your problem by training your mind and then minimize the use of medical interventions.</p>
<p>Why should you take the trouble to train your mind? Well, the human body is a complex ecosystem. Every attempt to control such a system by tampering with its inner workings triggers an avalanche of unpredictable results. Our body’s complexity makes it subject to what has been called “<a href="http://www.imho.com/grae/chaos/chaos.html">the butterfly effect</a>”.  The butterfly effect refers to the fact that the tiny effect of a butterfly flapping its wings in China may change the weather in, say, Los Angeles. (Click the link above for a more detailed explanation.)</p>
<p>This effect implies that complex systems can be heavily influenced by tiny variations in factors that scientists would usually see as negligible. The butterfly effect clarifies why all medicines have “side effects”, and also why It is wise to minimize the risks of putting alien substances into our bodies.</p>
<p>In light of this, I had a strong reaction to a recent article in the New York Times <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/06/fashion/mothers-and-sleep-medication.html?_r=2&amp;src=rechp">referring to sleep medications as “mother’s little helper”.</a></p>
<p>There are useful non-medical ways to deal with sleeplessness and they can powerfully improve the effects of medical treatment while minimizing the risks entailed in taking medication. For example most of the sleepless mothers described in the New York Times article could not sleep because they were obsessively ruminating over tasks that needed to be done.</p>
<p>Meditation can help reduce such rumination. While meditating you deal with mental distractions by gently and compassionately returning your mind to the object on which you are meditating.</p>
<p>Think of it in terms of deeply ingrained stimulus-response bonds; the thought is the stimulus and it demands that you respond. One illustrative example from the Times article is a mother who said “There’s always the worry another e-mail has come in” (stimulus). &#8220;It’s hard to resist getting up and checking your emai&#8221;l (response).</p>
<p>But when you meditate, you learn over and over not to do things like taking that last peek; instead you train your mind to go back to your chosen object of meditation. This breaks the stimulus-response bond. Think of it, there are probably thousands of thoughts that create in you an urge to take action, but your meditation breaks the bond between thought and action.  It reduces the linkage to the point where the response becomes optional instead of compulsive. That will make you calmer.</p>
<p>Earlier we posted <a href="../../../../../2011/03/02/basic-mindfulness-technique/">a traditional way of doing mindfulness meditation</a>, and also an <a href="../../../../../2010/12/06/a-key-step-in-resilience-training-is-learning-deep-relaxation/">audio</a> that can have a similar effect. Nether of these aids take up much of your time. You should consider trying one or both of them.</p>
<p>This is only one small way of changing how your mind works. We will be discussing many more in later posts.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2011%2F11%2F15%2Fsleeplessness-should-you-medicate-of-meditate%2F&amp;linkname=Sleeplessness%3A%20Should%20You%20Medicate%20of%20Meditate%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Controlling Distress and Boosting Success: The top 8 things you can do right now to build your personal resilience.</title>
		<link>/2011/08/22/controlling-distress-and-boosting-success-the-top-8-things-you-can-do-right-now-to-build-your-personal-resilience/</link>
		<comments>/2011/08/22/controlling-distress-and-boosting-success-the-top-8-things-you-can-do-right-now-to-build-your-personal-resilience/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2011 20:23:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Self-Criticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=819</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Debbie and I have been immersed in resilience training for decades, and we agreed to make a list of the top five or so actions we would recommend if someone asked us to outline a basic project to improve their &#8230; <a href="/2011/08/22/controlling-distress-and-boosting-success-the-top-8-things-you-can-do-right-now-to-build-your-personal-resilience/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Debbie and I have been immersed in resilience training for decades, and we agreed to make a list of the top five or so actions we would recommend if someone asked us to outline a basic project to improve their resilience. There was a lot of overlap between our lists, but, blending them, we ended up with eight instead of five.</p>
<p>These methods are supported by scientific evidence, and also by our personal experience. They are definitely worth a try. Typically, they are also enjoyable.</p>
<ol>
<li>Think back on what has      helped you succeed in pulling out of stress in the past. Make a list of things      that worked, and begin doing those things regularly.</li>
<li>Review our <a href="../../../../../2010/11/04/natural-stress-defeaters/">list      of things other people have found effective in recovering from stressful      days</a>. Select one or two to try for yourself. Don’t just put the list      in a drawer! Really try them out.</li>
<li>Learn how to relax deeply.      For a start, download the free relaxation audio we provided at the end of      our earlier <a href="../../../../../2010/12/06/a-key-step-in-resilience-training-is-learning-deep-relaxation/">post      on deep relaxation</a>. Listen to it several days each week for at least      two weeks.</li>
<li>If you haven’t been      exercising regularly, pick an exercise method that appeals to you and do      the exercise several days per week for at least two weeks. If possible,      find someone you like spending time with and invite them to join you. Or      bring along an energetic pet.</li>
<li>Take a <a href="../../../../../2011/08/09/handling-distress-the-power-of-optimism-hope-and-a-problem-solving-attitude/">Problem      Solving attitude</a> toward problems, stressors and frustrations.      Solutions that lead to success may be nearer at hand than you think.</li>
<li>When you find yourself with      a self -critical attitude or thinking negatively</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Consider that it’s no time to start reviewing your failings when you are having trouble dealing with distress. Re-focus on problem solving. What can you do right now to make things better? What path has promise as a path to success. Check tip number 5 above.</li>
<li>Don’t just roll over and accept self- criticism or negative thinking. Imagine what a defense attorney might do to challenge them, and be your own defense attorney. Defense attorneys interpret what their clients do in the best way possible. It’s a perspective that you should at least consider. It is probably more sensible than the often nutty negative thoughts most of us come up with under stress.</li>
<li>Learn to accept yourself through a method of meditation, like <a href="../../../../../2011/03/02/basic-mindfulness-technique/">mindfulness meditation</a>, that emphasizes acceptance and self-compassion.</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Seek out people who make      you feel better about yourself or who are good models of resilience. Find      a way to spend time with them.</li>
<li>Select an easy, relaxing      method of deep <a href="../../../../../2011/06/14/a-plain-vanilla-application-of-tactical-breathing-to-increase-resilience/">controlled      breathing</a> and use it several times a day. Then use it when you really      need it.</li>
</ol>
<p>We have previously said a lot about many of these things, as you will see if you click the links in this post. We will have more to say about the rest later.</p>
<p>Try out some of them, and let us know your results.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2011%2F08%2F22%2Fcontrolling-distress-and-boosting-success-the-top-8-things-you-can-do-right-now-to-build-your-personal-resilience%2F&amp;linkname=Controlling%20Distress%20and%20Boosting%20Success%3A%20The%20top%208%20things%20you%20can%20do%20right%20now%20to%20build%20your%20personal%20resilience." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2011/08/22/controlling-distress-and-boosting-success-the-top-8-things-you-can-do-right-now-to-build-your-personal-resilience/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Self-Compassion and Resilience</title>
		<link>/2011/03/22/self-compassion-and-resilience/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2011 19:03:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Hypersensitivity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Perfectionism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Self-Criticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Compassion]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=614</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Earlier, I explained that there are three factors that indicate whether people are resilient. For this post, I want to go back to the second resilience factor, discussed previously, about not being too hard on yourself. Many of us attack &#8230; <a href="/2011/03/22/self-compassion-and-resilience/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Earlier, I explained that there are <a href="../../../../../2011/01/11/the-three-core-factors-that-can-make-you-more-resilient/">three factors that indicate whether people are resilient</a>. For this post, I want to go back to the second resilience factor, discussed previously, about <a href="../../../../../2011/02/20/to-increase-your-resilience-avoid-being-too-hard-on-yourself/">not being too hard on yourself</a>.</p>
<p>Many of us attack ourselves when we are down. Here are some words <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Mental-ABCs-Pitching-Performance-Enhancement/dp/1888698292/ref=sr_1_3?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1300375346&amp;sr=1-3">Harvey Dorfman</a>, a major league pitching coach heard his extremely talented athletes apply to themselves: “idiot,” “loser,” “dummy,” “gutless,” and “I stink,” “I can’t,” “I don’t have it,” and “I’m clueless.” Notice that these are nasty and inaccurate. Even if on a given occasion they had made a mistake, they wouldn’t be major league pitchers if they were losers, idiots, etc.</p>
<p>Recently Glamor Magazine did a <a href="http://www.glamour.com/health-fitness/2011/02/shocking-body-image-news-97-percent-of-women-will-be-cruel-to-their-bodies-today">survey of women’s attitudes toward their bodies</a>, and here are some things the surveyed women had to say about themselves: “You are a fat, worthless pig.” “You’re too thin. No man is ever going to want you.” “Ugly. Big. Gross.” Ninety-seven percent of surveyed women had at least one such thought per day and, on average, the women had close to one of these thoughts per waking hour.</p>
<p>As a full-time professor I used to lecture on overweight, obesity, and weight loss. I always marveled at the intense attention students, especially women, gave as I spoke. Very lovely, well-formed women whom any sensible person would see as attractive were intensely interested in how to lose weight. And they were more than willing to listen to a paunchy professor tell them how to do that!</p>
<p>People who tend to speak abusively to themselves diminish their level of resilience, and so presumably lose at least some of the many advantages of being resilient. We are talking, after all, about the second most important resilience factor.</p>
<p>If, when under stress, we are nasty to ourselves, we just ratchet up the mental and physical stress reactions, and slow our recovery.</p>
<p>Recently the New York Times ran an article centering on <a href="http://well.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/02/28/go-easy-on-yourself-a-new-wave-of-research-urges/">the work of Kristin Neff on Self-Compassion</a>. By going to <a href="https://webspace.utexas.edu/neffk/pubs/listofpublications.htm">Dr. Neff’s website</a>, I saw that this topic has been the subject of a lot of research, not just by her, but by many others. Somehow I had missed it, despite my constant efforts to find <em>everything</em> relevant to resilience.</p>
<p>Her work took me one step further in clarifying what that second resilience factor is. It is about being compassionate toward yourself. To me that feels richer than merely putting an end to being mean to yourself. Compassion is not just the absence of meanness. It implies treating yourself in a caring, understanding, and loving way.</p>
<p>I am going to end this post with a valuable quotation from a <a href="https://webspace.utexas.edu/neffk/pubs/JRP.pdf">paper by Dr. Neff</a> that clarifies the concept of self-compassion:</p>
<p>“If individuals are self-compassionate when confronting suffering, inadequacy or failure, it means that they offer themselves warmth and non-judgmental understanding rather than belittling their pain or berating themselves with self-criticism.”</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2011%2F03%2F22%2Fself-compassion-and-resilience%2F&amp;linkname=Self-Compassion%20and%20Resilience" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>To Increase Your Resilience, Avoid Being Too Hard On Yourself.</title>
		<link>/2011/02/20/to-increase-your-resilience-avoid-being-too-hard-on-yourself/</link>
		<comments>/2011/02/20/to-increase-your-resilience-avoid-being-too-hard-on-yourself/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 20 Feb 2011 17:42:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Perfectionism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Self-Criticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Compassion]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=598</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In a previous post we described the three core factors that underlie resilience. Mostly we have talked about the first factor. The second factor has to do with: Treating your minor mistakes as awful and catastrophic. Being excessively self-critical. Setting &#8230; <a href="/2011/02/20/to-increase-your-resilience-avoid-being-too-hard-on-yourself/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In a previous post we described the three core factors that underlie resilience. Mostly we have talked about the first factor. The second factor has to do with:</p>
<ol>
<li>Treating your minor      mistakes as awful and catastrophic.</li>
<li>Being excessively self-critical.</li>
<li>Setting unrealistically      high standards that are usually unattainable.</li>
</ol>
<p>In plain language, it is being too hard on yourself. It is very likely to make you less resilient and more vulnerable.</p>
<p>The three item list above is identical to what many researchers who explore this topic simply call “perfectionism” or “maladaptive perfectionism”.</p>
<p>Perfectionists cannot tolerate even the smallest mistakes, berate themselves for any slip ups, and view results that are less than perfect as completely unacceptable. Clearly, perfectionism can make <strong><em>anything</em></strong> stressful.</p>
<p>The resilience-training alternatives to these three items are</p>
<p>1.                <em>Learning</em> to treat your minor mistakes realistically, with tolerance and acceptance.</p>
<p>2.                <em>Learning</em> to question and forcefully challenge the self-critical voice inside you, replace the criticism with ideas about how to do better in the future.</p>
<p>3.                <em>Learning</em> that having unrealistically high standards is not admirable or a path to success.</p>
<p>There are many levels of perfectionism. The severe ones are best dealt with in treatment with a qualified therapist. For example, perfectionistic people who are so thwarted that they have become severely depressed should consider therapy. That doesn’t exclude self-training. In fact, therapists commonly refer clients to our resilience training, as an adjunct to their therapy.</p>
<p>Most of us who stress ourselves by being too perfectionistic can improve considerably in one of two ways:</p>
<p>1.                Regularly and steadfastly challenging thoughts that point to unfair and unrealistic internal demands. If, when you make a mistake, your inner critic claims you are stupid or your action is going to result in catastrophic losses, or even that you would be better off dead, don’t take that lying down. Be your own defense attorney and demand solid evidence for the critic&#8217;s claims.</p>
<p>2.                Practicing some form of mindfulness meditation.</p>
<p>Here is a <a href="http://hubpages.com/hub/Dont-Be-Beaten-Down-by-Self-Critical-Thoughts">good account of how to challenge and diminish your self-critical thoughts</a>. In the next post we will describe our preferred method of mindfulness meditation. You should also take a look at the book “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Pursuit-Perfect-Chasing-Perfection-Happier/dp/0071608826">The Pursuit of Perfect: How to Stop Chasing Perfection and Start Living a RICHER, HAPPIER Life</a>”, by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tal_Ben-Shahar">Tal Ben-Shahar</a>. It is a book with heart, combining a narrative of his personal struggle to overcome perfectionism with science-based, helpful techniques.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2011%2F02%2F20%2Fto-increase-your-resilience-avoid-being-too-hard-on-yourself%2F&amp;linkname=To%20Increase%20Your%20Resilience%2C%20Avoid%20Being%20Too%20Hard%20On%20Yourself." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2011/02/20/to-increase-your-resilience-avoid-being-too-hard-on-yourself/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
