<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Attitudes of Resilience &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/attitudes-of-resilience/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Tips on Resilient Aging 3</title>
		<link>/2016/03/17/tips-on-resilient-aging-3/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2016 18:05:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Harvard Grant Study]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2041</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[&#160; (Note: we are dealing with a long chain of  technological failures, so this post was prepared on our iPad. Please forgive errors.) &#160; This is the third of a series of groundbreaking studies dealing with aging that we are &#8230; <a href="/2016/03/17/tips-on-resilient-aging-3/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>(Note: we are dealing with a long chain of  technological failures, so this post was prepared on our iPad. Please forgive errors.)</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>This is the third of a series of groundbreaking studies dealing with aging that we are covering in this blog-the Harvard Grant Study.</p>
<p>I For many decades there has been a study going on of characteristics leading to overall life success of Harvard students. To give you a sense of how long the study has been taking place, President John Kennedy was one of the undergraduates studied, and it is still going on.</p>
<p>The meaning of &#8220;overall life success&#8221; was borrowed from Freud, who defined it as the ability to love and to work, i.e. to develop stable loving relationships and a productive, satisfying career.</p>
<p>For many years, the head of the Grant Study was George Vaillant and he published &#8220;Adaptation to Life&#8221;, a very useful book for anyone interested in details on how others have lived happy, fruitful lives.</p>
<p>Vaillant described several adaptive styles that led to success. Here is a list of them:</p>
<p>1. Anticipation: being aware of future challenges and planning how you will avoid being blinded by them.<br />
2. Suppression: After doing what can be done about difficult circumstances, being able to put them aside and direct your attention to things that are in your control.<br />
3. Humor: People who used humor to help deal with stress did better than the humorless.<br />
4. Altruism: Taking the needs of others seriously, and letting them be important to you in the ways your own needs are important.<br />
5. Sublimation: Fulfilling unconscious yet unacceptable urges by putting your energy into doing something that is socially useful and acceptable that fulfills those urges. Two participants in the study illustrated this contrast. Both went hungry in their youth. One of them became determined to never be deprived again. The other sublimated his feelings by working<br />
for the US Department of Agriculture in the area of food aid.</p>
<p>How can you make use of this information?</p>
<p>Vaillant interpreted the studies within a Freudian framework. He saw these adaptive styles as &#8220;defense mechanisms&#8221;, which are ways we control our anxieties and keep undesirable desires out of our conscious awareness. Normally defense mechanisms are not seen as controllable by the conscious mind. Our purpose in this blog has never been to do psychotherapy,especially not depth therapy,like psychoanalysis,that attempts to uncover thoughts and feelings from the unconscious. Instead,we teach people to change their thoughts and habits,and even environments,to ones that help them do well in life. Looking at the five items in our list above, here are some ways to put some of them to use without venturing into depth psychology.</p>
<p>Anticipation</p>
<p>Anticipation is looking ahead, and planning for ways we might be able to get control of predictable stressors,then using the results of our planning to maximize good outcomes and minimize bad ones.</p>
<p>Try this: Imagine how you would like to be in the future(for example, six months or a year from now). Imagine the obstacles that might get in the way of your reaching your goals.Pick one of the barriers and plan ways to get past it. When opportunities arise to do this again, repeat with another barrier. Continue this until you can clearly imagine a reasonably smooth path to success.</p>
<p>Suppression:</p>
<p>Suppression is allowing yourself to be aware of your feelings without acting on them. An example of useful suppression: The idea that &#8220;I&#8217;ll cry tomorrow&#8221; allows you to be aware of your sadness, but also allows you to do what you need to do until the time is right for expressing the feeling.</p>
<p>Humor</p>
<p>A few decades ago, Norman Cousins, had a disease that his doctors could not cure. He decided to cure himself by watching films that made him laugh. He wrote a book about how this worked out, and felt it was quite successful.</p>
<p>The research literature on the healing effects of laughter, or of humor in general, despite having some evidence of such healing effects, does not lead to sound conclusions. However the use of laughter in common experiences lends support to the idea that laughter is beneficial. Laughter can engage us in ways that enable us to put aside painful thoughts, for a time even painful realities. In the meanwhile our resilience resources can replenish us and give us the stamina to settle the situation.</p>
<p>We need more and better research on various aspects of humor before reaching solid conclusions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Path to Greater Resilience: From Attitudes to Skills and to Habits.</title>
		<link>/2015/09/09/the-path-to-greater-resilience-from-attitudes-to-skills-and-to-habits/</link>
		<comments>/2015/09/09/the-path-to-greater-resilience-from-attitudes-to-skills-and-to-habits/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2015 20:41:26 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Attitudes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Habits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1982</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[When we discussed the Sense of Coherence in our previous post, we said that it was a match for the first factor in our three factor model of resilience. In both popular culture (e.g. Rev. Normal Vincent Peale’s “The Power &#8230; <a href="/2015/09/09/the-path-to-greater-resilience-from-attitudes-to-skills-and-to-habits/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When we discussed the Sense of Coherence in our previous post, we said that it was a match for the first factor in our three factor model of resilience.</p>
<p>In both popular culture (e.g. Rev. Normal Vincent Peale’s “The Power of Positive Thinking” which had a huge impact in the United States and elsewhere) and scientifically developed theory (e.g. Barbara Frederickson’s book, “Positivity”), the value of positivity has been recognized as playing a major role in lives well-lived.</p>
<p>But we see a distinction between attitudes of positivity and positive skills that are closely connected to those attitudes.</p>
<p>Probably most people would predict that positive attitudes and thoughts are related to resilience. But having skills such as knowing ways to calm and soothe yourself when distressed have been given less attention. In addition, many of us possess the needed skills, but do not implement them.</p>
<p>Once we take the skills to the point where we actually implement them when they are needed, we have reached the third level of using resilience tools, the level of habit.</p>
<p>In sum, we have to go from attitudes to skills and on to habits.</p>
<p>Isn’t this a lot of work? It can be, but for the most part the process is very enjoyable, even exhilarating at times.</p>
<p>Do we need to say that we think you should give it a try?</p>
<p>If you decide to do that, <a href="/2014/12/22/prepare-for-your-later-life-by-accumulating-skills-and-habits-of-resilience/">this</a> and <a href="/2014/10/08/build-your-toughness-and-become-more-resilient/">this</a> will help get you started.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2015%2F09%2F09%2Fthe-path-to-greater-resilience-from-attitudes-to-skills-and-to-habits%2F&amp;linkname=The%20Path%20to%20Greater%20Resilience%3A%20From%20Attitudes%20to%20Skills%20and%20to%20Habits." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2015/09/09/the-path-to-greater-resilience-from-attitudes-to-skills-and-to-habits/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mental Contrasting: An Important Technique for Reaching Your Goals.</title>
		<link>/2014/12/07/mental-contrasting-an-important-technique-for-reaching-your-goals/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2014 22:02:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Habits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mental contrasting]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1785</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In this post we hope to show you the value of a technique called “mental contrasting”. We want to explain that concept, to cite evidence that mental contrasting really helps people change their habits to healthier and more productive ones, &#8230; <a href="/2014/12/07/mental-contrasting-an-important-technique-for-reaching-your-goals/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this post we hope to show you the value of a technique called “mental contrasting”. We want to explain that concept, to cite evidence that mental contrasting really helps people change their habits to healthier and more productive ones, and to tell you what you need to know in order to use it yourself.</p>
<p><span id="more-1785"></span></p>
<p>In an<a title="earlier post" href="/2010/12/06/getting-yourself-to-act-on-what-you-learn-about-building-resilience/"> earlier post </a>we discussed Gabrielle Oettingen’s method of “mental contrasting” as a way to keep yourself practicing resilience skills. If you want to build these skills and turn them into habits you have to practice. But it is hard to change habits, and we all have trouble getting ourselves to persist in habit-changing practices until we reach our goals.</p>
<p>Mental contrasting has a very credible basis to claim that it is an important technique to help us persist in needed practices.</p>
<p>An article written by Oettingen <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/10/26/opinion/sunday/the-problem-with-positive-thinking.html?_r=0">appeared in the October 24<sup>th</sup> New York Times</a>, and has been in our “to do” folder ever since. This week, we had a good opportunity to digest its content.</p>
<p>If you find a better summary of mental contrasting and its uses, please let us know. This one is excellent. It identifies research done on mental contrasting, showing that it helps “college students wanting a date, hip-replacement patients hoping to get back on their feet, graduate students looking for a job, (and) schoolchildren wishing to get good grades.” In addition, the study we cited earlier was on helping women lose weight. It helps.</p>
<p>So it’s clear that this is a technique that is both effective and widely applicable. It has helped people reach a variety of goals; in addition, the studies were done in both the United States and Germany. So the methods work in a variety of contexts.</p>
<p>The final test is: Do they work for you?</p>
<p>Would you like to try it for one of your goals? Here is Oettingen’s description of how to do that:</p>
<p>“…Think of a wish. For a few minutes, imagine the wish coming true, letting your mind wander and drift where it will. Then shift gears. Spend a few more minutes imagining the obstacles that stand in the way of realizing your wish.”</p>
<p>It’s as simple as that. If you try it, let us know how it works for you. We will share the results with a lot of other people.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F12%2F05%2Fmental-contrasting-an-important-technique-for-reaching-your-goals%2F&amp;linkname=Mental%20Contrasting%3A%20An%20Important%20Technique%20for%20Reaching%20Your%20Goals." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Facing Situations That You May Not Be Able to Handle? Develop a Problem Solving Attitude.</title>
		<link>/2014/06/25/facing-situations-that-you-may-not-be-able-to-handle-develop-a-problem-solving-attitude/</link>
		<comments>/2014/06/25/facing-situations-that-you-may-not-be-able-to-handle-develop-a-problem-solving-attitude/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2014 18:30:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Benefits of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1667</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Having a “problem solving attitude” is an important influence on resilience. This attitude is a form of positivity, which is a well-known key to resilience. It is a facet of the first and most influential factor influencing resilience. It is &#8230; <a href="/2014/06/25/facing-situations-that-you-may-not-be-able-to-handle-develop-a-problem-solving-attitude/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Having a “problem solving attitude” is an important influence on resilience. This attitude is a form of positivity, which is a well-known key to resilience. It is a facet of the <a href="/2011/01/11/the-three-core-factors-that-can-make-you-more-resilient/">first and most influential factor influencing resilience</a>. It is linked to “positivity”, which is a key to resilience.</p>
<p>What, exactly is a “problem-solving attitude”? The best way to explain this is to describe what people with this attitude are likely to believe about life’s challenges.</p>
<p>People with this kind of attitude tend to react to mistakes by trying to figure out how to avoid them in the future.</p>
<p>You might say, “Isn’t that what everybody does?”</p>
<p><span id="more-1667"></span></p>
<p>No! It is very common for people to spend much more time looking for who is to blame for what happened, and, in particular, trying to convince themselves and others that nothing they did contributed to the bad outcome. That results in learning nothing about how to make things better.</p>
<p>Are there steps you can take to improve your problem solving attitude?</p>
<p>One thing you should do when faced with difficult situations is mentally take a step back and review the nature of the problem. Too often people jump into active attempts to solve a problem without first reviewing the details of the situation that are giving rise to the problem.</p>
<p>A good example is how people react when their computer or mobile device will not respond the way it should. It is all too common to become frustrated and angry, maybe muttering expletives while quickly trying out various solutions without really thinking through what is likely to work. Muttering expletives doesn’t repair electronic equipment.</p>
<p>It’s best to settle down and think through the nature of the problem and then select a few potential solutions to try out. Then try them out, being sure to keep track of what you are trying and of the results.</p>
<p>Don’t start telling yourself how bad it will be if you fail to come up with a quick solution. The problem is likely to be less consequential than it seems when you are immersed in it. As Nobel Prize winning psychologist, Daniel Kahneman said “Nothing in life is as important as you think it is, while you are thinking about it”.</p>
<p>Emphasize that this is a <em>problem</em> to be <em>solved</em> and there may well be many solutions. Do not fall into the trap of thinking the problem simply cannot be solved.</p>
<p>Think of the centuries in which people insisted that it was impossible for humans to fly. Then the Wright brothers built their flying machine and then, over the next several years developed it into a stable way of flying. After that, many more ways of flying came to light.</p>
<p>One thing you should train yourself <strong><em>not </em></strong>to do is focus on criticizing yourself for making mistakes. If you do that, it is likely to engulf you, leaving little or no mental space for thinking about how to make things better. Attacking yourself is a matter of changing the subject from how to solve the problem to a mental discussion of your worth. At that point, you stop problem solving.</p>
<p>Avoid being one of the many people who actually <em>insist on hopelessness</em>. The last thing you should do is adopt any resilience-draining approach of quickly deciding that nothing can be done to improve results. That is the path of hopelessness.</p>
<p>You don’t have to be a baseball fan to appreciate the following story:</p>
<p>In his book “The Mental ABC’s of Pitching: A Handbook for Performance Enhancement”, Major League pitching coach and sports psychologist, Harvey Dorfman, provided a clarifying example of how easy it may be to succeed if you just focus your mind on looking for solutions.</p>
<p>He describes an encounter with a pitcher, Steve Mura, who had spent six seasons in the Major Leagues and won 12 games for the 1983 Cardinals He was the starting pitcher for that night’s game.</p>
<p>Dorfman was chatting with him, and Mura shook his head silently. When asked what that was about, he said, “I can never win on this mound.” In the ensuing discussion, Dorfman told Mura, “There is a difference between, ‘I have not won and I cannot win’.” After all, there are many things we accomplish for the first time. Otherwise there would be no such thing as breaking one’s personal record.</p>
<p>Dorfman was already guiding Mura toward a problem solving approach by disabusing him of the illusion that past failures <strong><em>must</em></strong> continue forever. Can you see what a silly idea that is? To start with, how many things in life, whether good or bad, last forever?</p>
<p>When questioned further, Mura complained about the height and slope of the pitching mound. Dorfman asked him what kind of adjustments he could make to deal with that. Mura thought it over and came up with a strategy. He had never thought that way before. Instead he had spent his energy telling himself that he couldn’t win in that ballpark.</p>
<p>Mura pitched seven innings that night and gave up only two runs on hits. For those of you who don’t understand baseball, that is a very respectable performance.</p>
<p>Mura began in a state of pessimism and hopelessness. He wasn’t even applying the power of his mind to find solutions. As Dorfman pointed out, why should anyone think about solving the problem if failure is foreordained? And if they do not even begin problem solving, they obviously cannot persist in finding a way to succeed.</p>
<p>Once Mura shifted from pessimism and hopelessness to a problem-solving mode, it took only a few minutes to develop a plan of adjustments that led to success.</p>
<p>We are not saying that it will always be that easy, but you are much more likely to find solutions if you invest your energy in looking for them</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=&amp;linkname=Facing%20Situations%20That%20You%20May%20Not%20Be%20Able%20to%20Handle%3F%20Develop%20a%20Problem%20Solving%20Attitude." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2014/06/25/facing-situations-that-you-may-not-be-able-to-handle-develop-a-problem-solving-attitude/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Path Beyond Self-Criticism to Loving Kindness</title>
		<link>/2014/02/01/a-path-beyond-self-criticism-to-loving-kindness/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2014 23:21:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Self-Criticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Compassion]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1604</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[One of the keys to feeling and functioning better lies in how we talk to ourselves. By changing our self-talk, we can alter both our feelings and our behavior. This is not mere opinion. Psychological research has confirmed it for &#8230; <a href="/2014/02/01/a-path-beyond-self-criticism-to-loving-kindness/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One of the keys to feeling and functioning better lies in how we talk to ourselves. By changing our self-talk, we can alter both our feelings and our behavior. This is not mere opinion. Psychological research has confirmed it for many years, even decades.</p>
<p>Many people believe that talking to themselves in nasty, critical ways will keep them in line, and somehow make them safe and prevent criticism from others. But it is in fact very damaging to your resilience, and is at the heart of our second most important factor influencing resilience.</p>
<p>We have already done a number of posts on reducing self-criticism (for example,click <a href="/2013/07/10/resilience-factor-two-hypersensitivity-self-criticism-and-what-you-can-do-about-them/">here</a>), so there is no need to repeat ourselves. In brief, you have to become more aware of your self-critical remarks, then challenge them and devise more supportive remarks that are closer to the truth and/or more useful ways of thinking about yourself and the world.</p>
<p>This second factor was a problem because it had to be scored in “reverse”. That means you are less resilient the higher you score on that factor. When you criticize and tear yourself down, you make your reactions to stress worse, and that is the opposite of resilience.</p>
<p>We have long searched for the positive pole of this factor. When research on self-compassion came to our attention, it seemed to be that positive pole. But, more recently, we have realized that reducing self-criticism, which is very valuable, is, nevertheless, only a step in the direction of self-compassion.</p>
<p>To be compassionate toward yourself you have to go beyond reducing self-criticism and learn to be loving, caring, and understanding toward yourself.</p>
<p>In this series of posts, we are focused on taking steps beyond mere “sweet talk”, showing specific methods for getting to where you need to go.</p>
<p>For this post, we have chosen the Buddhist method of developing loving kindness toward yourself, then including others, then more and more of the beings in our world. This has worked for meditators for centuries, but there have also been quite a few experimental tests supporting the idea that it works.</p>
<p>The Buddha emphasized that you need only believe things that, when you try them, work out in your own life. So give this a try and decide for yourself.</p>
<p>We owe this video to the capabilities and generosity of <a title="Sharon Salzberg" href="http://www.sharonsalzberg.com/">Sharon Salzberg</a>. (Expect a pretty long time lag before the video shows).</p>
<p><iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/W3uLqt69VyI" frameborder="0" width="560" height="315"></iframe></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F02%2F01%2Fa-path-beyond-self-criticism-to-loving-kindness%2F&amp;linkname=A%20Path%20Beyond%20Self-Criticism%20to%20Loving%20Kindness" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why Do So Many Successful People Praise Failure?</title>
		<link>/2013/09/11/why-do-so-many-successful-people-praise-failure/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2013 03:23:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Self-Criticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Compassion]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1479</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Nobody wants to fail, or, worse, BE a failure. Failure is associated with shame, financial ruin, living a harder life, diminished status, not being able to contribute to your family’s resources.… Yet, we often see and hear what appears to &#8230; <a href="/2013/09/11/why-do-so-many-successful-people-praise-failure/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Nobody wants to fail, or, worse, BE a failure. Failure is associated with shame, financial ruin, living a harder life, diminished status, not being able to contribute to your family’s resources.…</p>
<p>Yet, we often see and hear what appears to be praise for failure. What could this be about?</p>
<p><span id="more-1479"></span></p>
<p>People who praise failure are not really talking about a lust for failure; they are talking about an important role of failure in teaching paths to success.</p>
<p>They are also talking about how avoidance of failure, or refusal to acknowledge failure can keep you from understanding what went wrong with your ineffective tries, and thus from seeing how to do better.</p>
<p>Here is an example: Debbie and I often watch Fareed Zakaria’s weekly TV show, “<a href="http://globalpublicsquare.blogs.cnn.com/category/gps-episodes/">GPS</a>” (Global Public Square).  A week or so ago, he interviewed Sara Blakely, an attractive young woman who went from cold call sales of copy machines to creating a business that made her a billionaire. She invented Spanx, an undergarment  she says makes women look better. Obviously many women agree with her.</p>
<p>In that interview, Ms. Blakely talked about the important role of her father in teaching her what it takes to succeed. He taught his children to boldly try new things, and, when they failed praised them for the try and gave them a “high five”.  He taught them not to avoid risk, and to see failure as a positive aspect of life, a key aspect of adaptation to the world as it is.</p>
<p>When Charlie Rose interviewed renowned golf champion, Ben Hogan, he asked Hogan about how he reacted to one of his greatest tournament failures. Hogan said it was the best thing that ever happened to him.  He embraced his mistakes, and learned from them. Many other golf masters have made similar comments.</p>
<p>Placed in the context of the resilience factors we have been discussing in the recent blog posts, these highly accomplished people are expressing  attitudes that are resilient with respect to Factor One (Resilient Attitudes and Skills).  They respond to failures with resilient attitudes  of <span style="text-decoration: underline;">positivity</span> and <span style="text-decoration: underline;">a problem-solving perspective</span>.</p>
<p>In addition, they do not cut their legs out from under themselves with unreasonable self-criticism. So they have resilient qualities reflected in Factor Two (Self-Compassion versus Self-Criticism).</p>
<p>So what the “pro-failure” people are really saying is that we need to grant ourselves the space to learn from our mistakes. If we pass up opportunities in order to avoid risk, or deny our role in failure, we will not learn to adapt to the world we live in.</p>
<p>Making mistakes does not make us “losers”, but we have the option of interpreting our mistakes either in ways that make us lose or in ways that help us win.</p>
<p>Once again, we see the power of “<a href="/2013/04/25/how-to-teach-your-worrier-brain-to-function-like-a-warrior-brain/">Reappraisal</a>”. If we see failure as an opportunity to learn, failure can be a positive influence. If we see it as humiliating, even unspeakable, or give ourselves no option other than to deny that it was our mistake, our adaptation to life will be thwarted.</p>
<p>We do not have to be afraid of making mistakes. Dealing with them is a known path to doing better in life.</p>
<p>Zorba the Greek said “Life is trouble. Only death is not. To be alive is to undo your belt and *look* for trouble.”</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F09%2F11%2Fwhy-do-so-many-successful-people-praise-failure%2F&amp;linkname=Why%20Do%20So%20Many%20Successful%20People%20Praise%20Failure%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Resilience Factor Two: Hypersensitivity, Self-Criticism and What You Can Do About Them.</title>
		<link>/2013/07/10/resilience-factor-two-hypersensitivity-self-criticism-and-what-you-can-do-about-them/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2013 03:03:36 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Hypersensitivity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Perfectionism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Self-Criticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Compassion]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1413</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The second most important resilience factor has to do with some very self-defeating things that people do that make them less resilient. It involves amplifying stress instead of getting it in control. I see it all the time; something distressing &#8230; <a href="/2013/07/10/resilience-factor-two-hypersensitivity-self-criticism-and-what-you-can-do-about-them/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The second most important resilience factor has to do with some very self-defeating things that people do that make them less resilient. It involves amplifying stress instead of getting it in control.</p>
<p>I see it all the time; something distressing happens and people react by tearing themselves down with self-criticism, and often go on to spread the criticism to, and generate fights with the very people who could help them recover quickly, which would be the path of resilience and both mental and physical health.</p>
<p>The core pattern of the factor was over-reacting to even small errors or failings by worrying about what we have done and how other people might react to our missteps. This leads to worrying about and criticizing ourselves for real or imagined failings.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QE1vnHfOcnU">This animation</a>, voiced by Jennifer Lopez, may help you to see the kinds of criticisms and attacks we have in mind. Similar examples can be found <a href="/2011/03/22/self-compassion-and-resilience/">here</a>.</p>
<p><span id="more-1413"></span></p>
<p>Our focus is on resilience, the positive things you can do to deal with stress and live a better life, so we are not interested in lamenting what is wrong with things we do, but with how we stay strong, healthy, and live well even if we have messed up.</p>
<p>We pondered and discussed Factor 2 (which we dubbed, perhaps clumsily, “Hypersensitivity, Self-Criticism/Perfectionism) for many years, frequently attempting to pinpoint the positive, resilience-promoting patterns implied by its negative, depleting ways.</p>
<p>Doing this blog and constantly looking for new approaches to enhance resilience led us to see what that resilience-promoting factor was.</p>
<p>We discovered an important body of research on self-compassion. If you are self-compassionate, you are not likely to be severely and unreasonably critical of your mistakes.</p>
<p>Self-compassion is the closest we are likely to find to the opposite of the intense and unreasonable self-criticism and demanding perfectionism reflected in Factor 2.</p>
<p>To give you a better sense of what factor two is about, here are some patterns embedded in it.</p>
<p>If you change on any of these patterns, you are also changing your standing on the factor itself. Here are more details:</p>
<ul>
<li>Self-Evaluations that are Critical and Unreasonably Demanding versus Reasonable Self-Compassion, and Realistic yet Loving, and Accepting Self-Evaluations.</li>
<li>Worry/Rumination versus, Focusing on the Present, and Taking Things One at a Time.</li>
<li>Unreasonable Expectations/Perfectionism. The more resilient polarity of this is recognizing that we all have limitations and that errors are natural in human life and deserve compassion. Failures, handled well, can even help by teaching us better ways of managing our lives.</li>
</ul>
<p>Knowing the factors is useful, but knowing ways you can change where you stand on them is more important. In a number of our previous blog posts we have discussed what to do if you need to improve on these patterns:</p>
<ol start="1">
<li>Learn how to offer yourself warmth and non-judgmental understanding rather than belittling your pain or berating yourself with self-criticism. <a href="/2012/01/03/from-negative-thinking-and-self-criticism-to-positive-thinking-and-self-compassion/?#more-891">This previous post</a> explains a useful way to reduce your self-negativity.</li>
<li>The ordinary human mind is chaotic; there is ancient expression that “The mind is a drunken monkey”. If you are a strong self-critic, you need to help yourself become more even-minded, and meditation will do that. <a href="/2011/03/02/basic-mindfulness-technique/">Here</a> is one of our earlier posts on a very popular, effective method of meditation.</li>
<li>Some things you can do to help with perfectionism are in <a href="/2011/02/20/to-increase-your-resilience-avoid-being-too-hard-on-yourself/">this post</a>.</li>
</ol>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=&amp;linkname=Resilience%20Factor%20Two%3A%20Hypersensitivity%2C%20Self-Criticism%20and%20What%20You%20Can%20Do%20About%20Them." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Map of the Path to Increased Resilience.</title>
		<link>/2013/06/20/a-map-of-the-path-to-increased-resilience/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2013 05:19:14 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Attitudes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1392</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Underlying our posts is a three-factor model of resilience which was derived from research done as part of my role as a professor. Our posts tend to be on specific attitudes or actions that are statistically confirmed aspects of one &#8230; <a href="/2013/06/20/a-map-of-the-path-to-increased-resilience/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Underlying our posts is a three-factor model of resilience which was derived from research done as part of my role as a professor. Our posts tend to be on specific attitudes or actions that are statistically confirmed aspects of one of the three factors. That is not because we select them only if they match our model. Our model just matches the data.</p>
<p>The blog was not started to publicize or support the model. It started as an outlet to keep me from constantly adding new findings to a book Debbie and I wrote to teach people how to improve their resilience.</p>
<p>To identify the core factors that underlie resilience we used a method called factor analysis. Done correctly, it can reveal the deep structure of whatever you are studying. So, for example, if you used it on three dimensional objects, like boxes, it would tell you that there are three dimensions, height, width and length.</p>
<p>We determined the dimensions of resilience and found that there were three. We also replicated that finding in two additional studies, and both of them confirmed the three dimensions.</p>
<p>To explain the factors here would be redundant, since we have already done that in <a href="/2011/01/11/the-three-core-factors-that-can-make-you-more-resilient/">this post</a>.</p>
<p>For now, we will discuss the number one factor that improves resilience.</p>
<h2>What good is this to you?</h2>
<p>Knowing the core dimensions will help you pinpoint all you can do to improve your resilience.</p>
<p>The number one influence on resilience is developing resilience-promoting  <strong><em>attitudes</em></strong> and <strong><em>skills</em></strong>.  These account for so much of resilience that, for a while, I was tempted to think of Factor One alone as just plain resilience, and ignore the other two factors. But too much evidence showed that those factors can be crucial for many people.</p>
<p>So what are the attitudes and skills you should try to develop?</p>
<p><span id="more-1392"></span></p>
<ul>
<li>Being optimistic and hopeful instead of pessimistic and hopeless.</li>
<li>Seeing distressing or painful life events as problems to be solved instead of things to be lamented and cursed.</li>
<li>Looking for and maybe even finding meaning in what we do and what we experience instead of just slogging through life.</li>
<li>Learning how to sooth, calm and replenish yourself, and then <strong><em>applying what you have learned </em></strong>to your everyday life when you are distressed, and also when you are feeling okay. (The latter is important in order to develop <strong><em>habits</em></strong> of resilience.).</li>
</ul>
<p>Some of the attitudes under factor one that help us be more resilient are</p>
<ol start="1">
<li>Being optimistic and hopeful versus viewing life with pessimism or despair.</li>
</ol>
<p>Here are posts that tell you how to do that:</p>
<p><a href="/2011/01/01/less-pessimism-and-more-optimism-will-build-your-resilience/">Increasing your optimism.</a></p>
<p><a href="/2012/08/02/reducing-negativity-in-your-mind-and-your-life/">Decreasing your negativity.</a></p>
<ol start="2">
<li>Viewing our lives, our choices, and our actions as meaningful versus seeing them as meaningless.</li>
</ol>
<p>Here is a post to help you do that.</p>
<p><a href="/2011/11/28/finding-meaning-and-purpose-can-help-you-deal-with-distress-no-matter-how-extreme/">Finding  meaning.</a></p>
<ol start="3">
<li>Taking a problem-solving attitude toward stressful situations and anticipating predictable complications.</li>
</ol>
<p>Here is a post that shows you how to do that:</p>
<p><a href="/2012/08/02/reducing-negativity-in-your-mind-and-your-life/">Problem-Solving Attitude.</a></p>
<ol start="4">
<li>Learning and applying  the skills that sooth and replenish you instead of taking actions that make things worse.</li>
</ol>
<p>There are many posts that show how to do that:</p>
<p><a href="/2011/03/02/basic-mindfulness-technique/">Training yourself in mindfulness.</a></p>
<p><a href="/2011/06/02/tactical-breathing-can-stop-stress-on-the-spot/">Breath control for resilience.</a></p>
<p><a href="/2010/12/06/a-key-step-in-resilience-training-is-learning-deep-relaxation/">Learning deep relaxation.</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F06%2F20%2Fa-map-of-the-path-to-increased-resilience%2F&amp;linkname=A%20Map%20of%20the%20Path%20to%20Increased%20Resilience." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Genetic Variants That Can Determine Whether We Have a “Worrier Brain” or A “Warrior Brain” and What We Can Do About Them.</title>
		<link>/2013/03/19/genetic-variants-that-can-determine-whether-we-have-a-worrier-brain-or-a-warrior-brain-and-what-we-can-do-about-them/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2013 15:16:31 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Genes and Resilience]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1338</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This post is based on an article I recently found in the New York Times. It makes several important claims: There are two variants of a specific gene that influence how quickly we recover from stressful experiences. We get one &#8230; <a href="/2013/03/19/genetic-variants-that-can-determine-whether-we-have-a-worrier-brain-or-a-warrior-brain-and-what-we-can-do-about-them/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This post is based on an <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/10/magazine/why-can-some-kids-handle-pressure-while-others-fall-apart.html?pagewanted=all&amp;_r=0">article</a> I recently found in the New York Times. It makes several important claims:</p>
<ol start="1">
<li>There are two variants of a specific gene that influence how quickly we recover from stressful experiences.</li>
<li>We get one from our mother and the other from our father.</li>
<li>The pattern of these genes we inherit determines whether we will be “worriers” or “warriors”.</li>
<li>Worriers are people who have to struggle with stressful experiences and warriors are people for whom stress reactions quickly pass by.</li>
<li>Whether we have the genetic pattern that gives us a warrior brain or a worrier brain, there is at least one simple technique that can make us deal efficiently with stress.</li>
</ol>
<p><span id="more-1338"></span></p>
<p>First, I want to acknowledge that I am skeptical about much of the brain-mind research that has come to be widely accepted. I don’t want to get into that because it is way too technical. But I often ask, “What good does it do for people dealing with a stress problem to learn that they were genetically doomed to have trouble with stressors, e.g.to be a worrier?”</p>
<p>Today, Debbie had an opening in her usually busy schedule, and called to chat.  I was trying to write this post, and I posed this question to her. She paused briefly, and then said “It helps people to understand why they have to struggle with things that other people handle with apparent ease.” Good answer.</p>
<p>So here is my condensed description of the genetic issue. Dopamine is a brain chemical that is released in the lower part of the frontal lobes of our brain. The sooner it is cleared out, the sooner we recover from the stress. This is because that lower frontal part of the brain can control the parts of the brain that produce responses that are “raw emotions”.</p>
<p>We all have a gene that determines how fast we clear Dopamine out of that part of our brain, and, as we said above, one variant leads to quicker, actually something like 40 times quicker, cleanup of the dopamine “mess”.</p>
<p>For people whose brains cleanup that mess slowly, their brains and minds are likely to be overwhelmed by the surge.</p>
<p>The following is an important part of this study: the effects of the slow acting system have been demonstrated in a real-life stressful situation. Young people in Taiwan take a test that has a major influence on the trajectory of their lives. Those with the slow acting system score on average 8 percent lower than those with the fast-acting system.</p>
<p>However, people with the slow acting gene can handle extreme stress as long as they are well-trained. Even some Navy Seals have worrier genes.</p>
<p>This concept that training can trump genetic effects (or lifelong bad habits) is right at the core of our belief in the value of resilience training.</p>
<p>What kind of training do people with worrier brains need to function as well as those with warrior brains?</p>
<ul>
<li>Exposure to stress challenges. Worriers need to be taxed without being overwhelmed, and then have time for recovery. “Training, preparation, and repetition defuse the worrier’s curse”.</li>
<li>Labeling of stress can determine reactions to it. If worriers see their feelings of stress as something that can improve their performance, their performance improves. They learn to view the feelings we usually call “stress” as “excitement”.</li>
</ul>
<p>We plan to deal with the effects of such labeling or “reappraisal” in a future post.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=&amp;linkname=" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Does Secure Attachment to Others Lead to High Resilience?</title>
		<link>/2013/02/21/does-secure-attachment-to-others-lead-to-high-resilience/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2013 04:15:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[How Hard Is It To Change Resilience?]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1321</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[There is interesting research showing that how securely we attach to our caregivers as young children plays an important role in our resilience as adults. Children who develop a secure attachment to their mother (or other caregiver) tend, as adults, &#8230; <a href="/2013/02/21/does-secure-attachment-to-others-lead-to-high-resilience/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There is interesting research showing that how securely we attach to our caregivers as young children plays an important role in our resilience as adults. Children who develop a secure attachment to their mother (or other caregiver) tend, as adults, to be resilient in the face of challenges.</p>
<p>Does this mean that your level of resilience became a settled matter when you were little, and nothing can be done about it now? We don’t think so.</p>
<p><span id="more-1321"></span></p>
<p>Attachment style is developed in very early childhood, and has been extensively studied. Usually there are deemed to be three basic styles, Secure, Anxious-Ambivalent, and Avoidant. This attachment style developed in early childhood appears to stay with us throughout our lives.</p>
<p>Those who are “Secure”, apparently had a good fit between their inborn temperament and parental responses that enabled them to build inner resources. These inner resources enable them to connect well with others, and to feel confident in potentially scary, unfamiliar environments. Both the Anxious-Ambivalent and the Avoidant people are less effective in dealing with such environments.</p>
<p>Avoidant people appear to be comfortable without close relationships, and avoid dependency on others. This is viewed as a defense, and can, under enough distress, break down.</p>
<p>Avoidant people may seem to be secure unless the environment is too challenging, and under those circumstances, they can seem more like those who are Anxious-Ambivalent.</p>
<p>Anxious-Ambivalent people long for emotionally close relationships, but tend to feel uncomfortable with them. It is hard for them to trust or depend on others.</p>
<p>For our purposes here, we can look at those who are just “Secure” or “Non-Secure”.</p>
<p>Mario Mikulincer and Victor Florian have <a href="http://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=hWe5-aSgZmcC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA143&amp;dq=mikulincer+florian&amp;ots=zjtx_xOZK5&amp;sig=KVc2PtHo1ap0q86eXi5AyA9k3SU#v=onepage&amp;q=mikulincer%20florian&amp;f=false (">summarized the research on how Secures and Non-Secures react to a wide range of demanding circumstances</a>, and have consistently shown that Secures are more resilient than Non-Secures.</p>
<p>Their review includes studies of reactions to significant life challenges. Very consistently they indicate that Secures handle such challenges better than Non-Secures. Here are examples:</p>
<ul>
<li>In the military training, Anxious Ambivalents perceived more threat, felt a greater sense of personal inadequacy and helplessness in dealing with the training.</li>
<li>When facing the threat of death, Secures had less fear.</li>
<li>In time of war, when threatened with missile attacks, Secures sought more support from others and had fewer symptoms of post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD).</li>
<li>Prisoners of War who were Secures had fewer symptoms of PTSD than Non Secures.</li>
<li>Secures handled loss of significant others better than Non-Secures.</li>
<li>In experiments testing reactions to personal failure, Secures handled the failures better.</li>
<li>Women facing the challenges of new <strong>motherhood </strong>who were secure handled them better than non-secures.</li>
<li>Mothers with handicapped children dealt with the extra challenges better if they were Secures.</li>
<li>People coping with chronic pain who are secure react much more effectively than those who are insecure.</li>
</ul>
<p>So, here is more evidence that resilience helps us deal with life’s challenges. But, if attachment style is determined when we are no more than toddlers, doesn’t it seem we are either blessed or doomed by early experiences to be resilient or not?</p>
<p>One interesting fact in the work of Mikulincer and Florian provides considerable room for hope. In Israel, during the first Persian Gulf War, some people had to deal with Scuds missile attacks. They had to face the possibility of instant death, and had no personal control over the source of that threat.</p>
<p>Yet the less resilient people reacted the same way as those who were resilient. Why? Presumably because public service messages consistently told them to check on each other during and after the attacks. With these instructions, anxious ambivalent and avoidant people reacted by reaching out to others, just as secure people would likely have done without the instructions.</p>
<p>So mere instructions from the government were able to override the knee jerk reactions of insecures to either hem and haw (anxious-ambivalents) or deal with the threats solely on their own (avoidant).</p>
<p>We can reasonably expect that real resilience training can be even more effective than mere instructions.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F02%2F21%2Fdoes-secure-attachment-to-others-lead-to-high-resilience%2F&amp;linkname=Does%20Secure%20Attachment%20to%20Others%20Lead%20to%20High%20Resilience%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
