<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>mental contrasting &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/mental-contrasting/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>How to Develop Habits that Increase Resilience</title>
		<link>/2015/10/08/how-to-develop-habits-that-increase-resilience/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2015 16:34:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Habits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mental contrasting]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1989</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Ultimately, resilience training should result in new habits that make you more resistant to stress. We have pointed out a number of times that listening to a lecture or reading an article on coping with stress is not likely to &#8230; <a href="/2015/10/08/how-to-develop-habits-that-increase-resilience/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ultimately, resilience training should result in new habits that make you more resistant to stress.</p>
<p>We have pointed out a number of times that listening to a lecture or reading an article on coping with stress is not likely to be enough to result in more resilient habits. You may get useful information, maybe even inspiration, both of which can be valuable, but that is not enough to produce new habits.</p>
<p>Usually we recommend “practice, practice, practice”. We also described “<a href="/2014/12/07/mental-contrasting-an-important-technique-for-reaching-your-goals/">mental contrasting</a>”, a method that asks you to imagine yourself as you are now, and to alternate that with imagining yourself after you have developed a new resilience habit. This differs from a widely used method of simply imagining yourself as having achieved the desired goal. The latter method has proven to be ineffective.</p>
<p>Research shows that mental contrasting improves results. For example, see Amit Amin’s paper here. Details of how to practice mental contrasting were published in the Harvard Business Review<a href="https://hbr.org/2011/02/nine-things-successful-people"> here</a>.</p>
<p>We now have the concept of the habit loop, which can act as a guide on how to develop new habits. This model of habit change contrasts with a long familiar approach of just giving yourself rewards when you engage in the behavior you want to make habitual. Instead, it focuses heavily on turning attention to the cues or triggers that elicit the behavior.<span id="more-1989"></span> </p>
<p>The power of cues is striking. We had a friend (now deceased) who never smoked in front of his parents. For a long time, he could not quit smoking. But when he visited his parents, often for long periods, he told us that he never felt an urge to smoke. The cue or cues were missing, so the urge never appeared.</p>
<p>It is important to look for the cues that trigger your behaviors because, by manipulating the cues you can control habits.</p>
<p>It is also important to develop cues to trigger habits you are trying to develop. Shawn Achor provided a very good illustration of effectively developing <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Happiness-Advantage-Principles-Psychology-Performance/dp/0307591549/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1444256134&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=the+happiness+advantage">a cue to trigger practicing on his guitar.</a></p>
<p>Achor wanted to learn to play the guitar. At first he put the guitar in a closet. He could get it out in a matter of seconds. Yet, after some time he noted that he had not practiced guitar at all! So he took it out of the closet and placed it in the living room. Then, the guitar acted as a cue for him to practice, and soon he had developed a well-cued habit.</p>
<p>Several writers who wanted to develop a steady habit of exercising have put exercise clothing next to the bed. The clothing triggers a response of dressing for the workout and then doing it.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2015%2F10%2F07%2Fhow-to-develop-habits-that-increase-resilience%2F&amp;linkname=How%20to%20Develop%20Habits%20that%20Increase%20Resilience" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Role of Resilience in Making Failure a Stepping Stone to Success</title>
		<link>/2015/02/04/the-role-of-resilience-in-making-failure-a-stepping-stone-to-success/</link>
		<comments>/2015/02/04/the-role-of-resilience-in-making-failure-a-stepping-stone-to-success/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2015 17:02:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[mental contrasting]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1832</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[They say that “dog bites man” is not worth reporting, but “man bites dog” is newsworthy. Some of our blog posts started as cases of “man bites dog”.   After decades in which “positive thinking” was generally accepted, those posts took &#8230; <a href="/2015/02/04/the-role-of-resilience-in-making-failure-a-stepping-stone-to-success/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>They say that “dog bites man” is not worth reporting, but “man bites dog” is newsworthy.</p>
<p>Some of our blog posts started as cases of “man bites dog”.   After decades in which “positive thinking” was generally accepted, those posts took a close look at a growing view that “negativity may be good for you”.  But we ended up concluding that arguments for negativity commonly turn out to be based on mere matters of how you <strong><em>define</em></strong> negativity.</p>
<p>Upon close examination, at least some claims for negativity appear to be simple matters of treating <strong><em>realism</em></strong> as negative thinking. For example, thinking through obstacles that might get in the way of reaching a desired goal is <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/10/26/opinion/sunday/the-problem-with-positive-thinking.html">considered negativity</a>.</p>
<p><span id="more-1832"></span></p>
<p>That realism helps us to reach our goals is clearly not a “man bites dog” story. Who would be intrigued by a story like that?</p>
<p>So must we conclude that positivity is simply good and negativity is simply bad? What about the many writings that affirm the value of failure?</p>
<p>It isn’t easy to dismiss the <a href="http://www.calebwojcik.com/blog/2012/01/30/quotes-overcome-fear-of-failure">statements of the highly successful</a> that <a href="http://www.goodreads.com/quotes/tag/failure">failure has been a central contributor</a> to their success.</p>
<p>But didn’t it require a lot of positivity to confront their mistakes, learn from them, and then take the chances that ultimately resulted in success? Surely hope, optimism, problem-solving, and other aspects of positivity were needed to enable persistence through failure on to the point of success.</p>
<p>Hope, optimism, and a problem-solving attitude are all important aspects of resilience. And there is research confirming that resilience makes success more likely.</p>
<p>Martin Seligman in his classic book, “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Learned-Optimism-Change-Your-Mind/dp/1400078393/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1423027034&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=learned+optimism">Learned Optimism</a>” has whole chapters describing how what he calls an “optimistic explanatory style” is linked to success in difficult sales jobs (Chapter 6) and in various aspects of athletic competition (Chapter 9).</p>
<p>The work on athletics is particularly relevant to our present discussion of the role of failure. Seligman found that athletes and teams with optimistic styles were more likely than others to come back and win after being behind in the game. They were able to snatch victory from what appeared to be a coming defeat.</p>
<p>One thing for sure is that a failure need not be a reason to give up on anything; not on reaching your goals and, most importantly, not on yourself.</p>
<p>Failures, painful as they may be, are opportunities to learn what doesn’t work and plan the next steps better informed than you were when you first planned how to reach your goals.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=&amp;linkname=" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2015/02/04/the-role-of-resilience-in-making-failure-a-stepping-stone-to-success/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mental Contrasting: An Important Technique for Reaching Your Goals.</title>
		<link>/2014/12/07/mental-contrasting-an-important-technique-for-reaching-your-goals/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2014 22:02:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Habits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mental contrasting]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1785</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In this post we hope to show you the value of a technique called “mental contrasting”. We want to explain that concept, to cite evidence that mental contrasting really helps people change their habits to healthier and more productive ones, &#8230; <a href="/2014/12/07/mental-contrasting-an-important-technique-for-reaching-your-goals/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this post we hope to show you the value of a technique called “mental contrasting”. We want to explain that concept, to cite evidence that mental contrasting really helps people change their habits to healthier and more productive ones, and to tell you what you need to know in order to use it yourself.</p>
<p><span id="more-1785"></span></p>
<p>In an<a title="earlier post" href="/2010/12/06/getting-yourself-to-act-on-what-you-learn-about-building-resilience/"> earlier post </a>we discussed Gabrielle Oettingen’s method of “mental contrasting” as a way to keep yourself practicing resilience skills. If you want to build these skills and turn them into habits you have to practice. But it is hard to change habits, and we all have trouble getting ourselves to persist in habit-changing practices until we reach our goals.</p>
<p>Mental contrasting has a very credible basis to claim that it is an important technique to help us persist in needed practices.</p>
<p>An article written by Oettingen <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/10/26/opinion/sunday/the-problem-with-positive-thinking.html?_r=0">appeared in the October 24<sup>th</sup> New York Times</a>, and has been in our “to do” folder ever since. This week, we had a good opportunity to digest its content.</p>
<p>If you find a better summary of mental contrasting and its uses, please let us know. This one is excellent. It identifies research done on mental contrasting, showing that it helps “college students wanting a date, hip-replacement patients hoping to get back on their feet, graduate students looking for a job, (and) schoolchildren wishing to get good grades.” In addition, the study we cited earlier was on helping women lose weight. It helps.</p>
<p>So it’s clear that this is a technique that is both effective and widely applicable. It has helped people reach a variety of goals; in addition, the studies were done in both the United States and Germany. So the methods work in a variety of contexts.</p>
<p>The final test is: Do they work for you?</p>
<p>Would you like to try it for one of your goals? Here is Oettingen’s description of how to do that:</p>
<p>“…Think of a wish. For a few minutes, imagine the wish coming true, letting your mind wander and drift where it will. Then shift gears. Spend a few more minutes imagining the obstacles that stand in the way of realizing your wish.”</p>
<p>It’s as simple as that. If you try it, let us know how it works for you. We will share the results with a lot of other people.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F12%2F05%2Fmental-contrasting-an-important-technique-for-reaching-your-goals%2F&amp;linkname=Mental%20Contrasting%3A%20An%20Important%20Technique%20for%20Reaching%20Your%20Goals." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
