<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Resilience and Health &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/resilience-and-health/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Prepare for Your Later Life by Accumulating Skills and Habits of Resilience</title>
		<link>/2014/12/22/prepare-for-your-later-life-by-accumulating-skills-and-habits-of-resilience/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2014 17:41:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Benefits of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience and Health]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1801</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Why should we invest in improving our resilience? Usually it is because we want to: Avoid having painful, distressing reactions to potentialy jarring occurrences that come up in our lives, and instead to stay reasonably calm and cool in the &#8230; <a href="/2014/12/22/prepare-for-your-later-life-by-accumulating-skills-and-habits-of-resilience/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Why should we invest in improving our resilience? Usually it is because we want to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Avoid having painful, distressing reactions to potentialy jarring occurrences that come up in our lives, and instead to stay reasonably calm and cool in the face of such experiences.</li>
<li>Avoid ending up lastingly impaired by such experiences. That often quoted saying “Whatever doesn’t kill me makes me stronger” Is only true when permanent or long-term damage isn’t done. (Think of Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder.)</li>
<li>If we fail to avoid being impaired, minimize the damage by developing effective “work-arounds”, and thus maintain our quality of life.</li>
</ul>
<p>Researchers have provided us with many studies that show striking positive effects of resilience. A remarkable example that comes to mind is research showing that optimism predicts  <a title="better outcomes of surgery, including recovery from a coronary bypass" href="http://www.psy.miami.edu/faculty/ccarver/documents/10_CPR_Optimism.pdf">better outcomes of surgery, including recovery from a coronary bypass</a>.</p>
<p>Still, studies in real life situations with large samples of real people that trace the effects of resilience over fairly long periods of time are rare. The work of <a title="Lydia Manning" href="http://newoldage.blogs.nytimes.com/2014/09/12/tougher-than-they-look/" target="_blank">Lydia Manning</a> and her colleagues is one of the rare exceptions.<span id="more-1801"></span></p>
<p>This team assessed the impact of resilience on the lives of older people (ranging from their fifties to their late nineties). She and her colleagues gave a remarkably large sample of more than 10,000 older people a simple measure of resilience, then tracked them for two years.</p>
<p>People in their study who started out more resilient were less likely to lose functions that enable them to live independently. When you are elderly and dealing with stress, you are not just at risk of feeling uncomfortable; you are at risk of losing control of your life. Resilience makes it more likely that you will stand up to the stresses of life, or, failing that, at least find ways you can stay in control of your life.</p>
<p>Many of you may feel that research on old people’s ability to avoid needing help to do everyday tasks of life has little or nothing to do with you. Well, 100 percent of young people who don’t die young end up old. Even before they get old, people who are important to them may face the vulnerabilities of old age. So this research is important to most of us.</p>
<p>If we want to meet the challenges of elder life with a strong armamentarium of resilience skills and habits, the best thing is to learn those skills and develop those habits early on so they are ingrained in us and can be called on whether you are young or old.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F12%2F22%2Fprepare-for-your-later-life-by-accumulating-skills-and-habits-of-resilience%2F&amp;linkname=Prepare%20for%20Your%20Later%20Life%20by%20Accumulating%20Skills%20and%20Habits%20of%20Resilience" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lessons for the Old and the Young on Recovering from Nasty Challenges</title>
		<link>/2014/09/22/lessons-for-the-old-and-the-young-on-recovering-from-nasty-challenges/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2014 03:28:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Benefits of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience and Health]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1748</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Elderly people can have devastating consequences, including death, from injuries such as breaking bones. Broken hips are hard for any of us to deal with, but often can be fatal to elders. Recently research on the factors that predict recovery &#8230; <a href="/2014/09/22/lessons-for-the-old-and-the-young-on-recovering-from-nasty-challenges/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Elderly people can have devastating consequences, including death, from injuries such as breaking bones. Broken hips are hard for any of us to deal with, but often can be fatal to elders.</p>
<p>Recently research on the factors that predict recovery after falls for the elderly has shown that <a href="http://newoldage.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/11/15/predicting-a-falls-aftermath/?_php=true&amp;_type=blogs&amp;_r=0">those who were more fit before the fall were significantly more likely to recover</a>.</p>
<p>Our take on this is that elderly people who have a lifestyle that makes them more fit are more resilient in the face of mortal threats.</p>
<p>Many countries, including ours, have populations that are increasingly older. But if you take away from this recent finding that you should stay fit as you grow older, you are right, but you are, at the same time, missing the heart of the matter.</p>
<p>The main thing to take away is that the more you, whether old or yourng, cultivate your resilience, the more likely you are to come out well after any of life’s nasty challenges, and the more likely you are to recover a good life.</p>
<p>Nietszche said “Whatever does not kill me makes me stronger”.  Another, less dramatic and less poetic, way to phrase that is, if you have developed resilience skills, you are more likely to grow strong after nasty challenges instead of being taken down by them. And this is true no matter how old you are, or what kind of damage you are facing.</p>
<p>The take-home message is “start NOW to build your physical, and mental resilience”. It will help you through all the phases of your life.</p>
<p>This is YOUR LIFE we are talking about.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F09%2F22%2Flessons-for-the-old-and-the-young-on-recovering-from-nasty-challenges%2F&amp;linkname=Lessons%20for%20the%20Old%20and%20the%20Young%20on%20Recovering%20from%20Nasty%20Challenges" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Can We Make Ourselves Biologically Younger?</title>
		<link>/2013/10/17/can-we-make-ourselves-biologically-younger/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2013 05:47:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Benefits of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mindfulness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience and Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1516</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Some years ago we became aware of the important role of telomeres in aging, and the role of stress in speeding up the aging process. Telomeres are genetic components that are linked to biological aging. Usually, the older you are &#8230; <a href="/2013/10/17/can-we-make-ourselves-biologically-younger/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Some years ago we became aware of the important role of telomeres in aging, and the role of stress in speeding up the aging process. Telomeres are genetic components that are linked to biological aging. Usually, the older you are the shorter your telomeres become.</p>
<p>What did this have to do with resilience? Well, resilience controls stress, and it turns out that higher levels of stress result in increased shortening of telomeres. So your calendar age is not the only determinant of how old your cells are. Stress is a highly significant influence.</p>
<p>In fact, women who reported being highly stressed were biologically, as indexed by telomere length, about ten years older than those who did not report high stress.</p>
<p>In one of our early resilience workshops, one person in the group asked an obvious question that hadn’t occurred to us. “Is there anything that can enable us to <strong><em>lengthen</em></strong> our telomeres?&#8221; We paused, and had to say that we did not know.</p>
<p>Since that time, a good deal of research has shown that we can indeed lengthen our telomeres through lifestyle changes.</p>
<p>We were working on our usual exhaustive examination of the scientifically respectable evidence that people can lengthen their telomeres when we discovered the following interview of Dr. Dean Ornish, who recently completed a study on how the telomeres can be lengthened. We decided to re-post his video, which does a very good job of explaining what we need to do to lengthen our telomeres. We weren&#8217;t likely to improve, in a short post, on what he says in this interview. And it isn&#8217;t just a promotion of his own work; he talks about a wide range or research pointing in the same direction as his.</p>
<p><iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/QPpJU8Je-lE" frameborder="0" width="420" height="315"></iframe></p>
<p>It appears that telomeres can indeed be lengthened, and that well established healthy lifestyle changes can produce the lengthening.</p>
<p>Naturally attempts are being made to develop a kind of &#8220;Fountain of Youth&#8221; pill that can lengthen telomeres. We would recommend that such pills be viewed with great caution. It&#8217;s one thing to do things we already know are good for you and thus lengthen telomeres and quite another to take a new pill that needs lengthy testing.</p>
<p>As we have pointed out previously in this blog, the body is a highly complex, interactive ecosystem. Change one thing and many other unpredictable changes are likely to occur. The enzyme, telomerase stimulates growth of telomeres. But there is a lot of telomerase in certain malignant tumors. So who can say what kinds of side effects might result from artificial tampering?</p>
<p>On the other hand, sensible exercise, eating a healthy diet, learning to live peacefully with others, and calming ourselves through meditation have been around for centuries, and we know that their side effects improve lives</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F10%2F17%2Fcan-we-make-ourselves-biologically-younger%2F&amp;linkname=Can%20We%20Make%20Ourselves%20Biologically%20Younger%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Recovery and Adaptation</title>
		<link>/2013/09/25/recovery-and-adaptation/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2013 19:47:51 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience and Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Why Resilience?]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1490</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I think it would be hard for anyone who spent even a few years probing deeply into research on stress to deny that it can really damage a person, both psychologically and physically. Reactions to stress are not just “in &#8230; <a href="/2013/09/25/recovery-and-adaptation/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think it would be hard for anyone who spent even a few years probing deeply into research on stress to deny that it can really damage a person, both psychologically and physically. Reactions to stress are not just “in your head”. They are palpable.</p>
<p>Stress is far more important to health than most people think. And the more stress there is in a person’s life, the more likely it is that she or he will become ill.</p>
<p>But the load of stress people can handle without getting sick varies a lot from one person to another. What are the differences between people who are stress resistant and those who are highly vulnerable to stress? And is there some way to guide the more vulnerable people to become more stress resistant?</p>
<p>Once you shift to these questions, you are moving from an emphasis on stress to an emphasis on resilience. We made that shift several decades ago. Our approach has been to identify how resilient people deal with stress, and then to ask how more vulnerable people might learn to use those patterns of resilience.</p>
<p><span id="more-1490"></span></p>
<p>It is important to realize that stress responses are <strong><em>adaptive. </em></strong>So it is not a good idea to just try to stamp out or run away from those responses.</p>
<p>Here is an example of the adaptiveness of the stress response. You have probably heard of the “fight or flight” response. When you have that pattern of responses, your heart pounds rapidly and the little blood vessels in the outer parts of your body constrict.</p>
<p>Since your blood pressure depends on the volume of blood being pumped and the amount of resistance coming from the downstream blood vessels, your blood pressure shoots up under stress. That increases the likelihood of cardiovascular diseases such as heart attack and stroke.</p>
<p>However, the fight or flight responses also help you if you have to fight or flee. Blood flow shifts away from your intestines to your muscles, so you are better equipped for fleeing or fighting. It also shifts away from your skin and coagulates more easily, so you will lose less blood if you are wounded.</p>
<p>So whether stress responses are good or bad depends on the circumstances.</p>
<p>Also, it may be good for you to deliberately stress yourself in order to become more resilient.</p>
<p>To illustrate, it is generally believed, on the basis of much research,  both by experts and by almost everybody else, that exercise is good for you. Yet exercise is stressful, and the physiological response to exercise is identical to the fight or flight response.</p>
<p>To be healthy, exercise has to stay within a range that allows us to recover fully and promptly.</p>
<p>With regular exercise we adapt to stress. We experience a “training effect” that changes our physiology in ways that enable us to exert ourselves more and more, and yet recover without harming ourselves. Basically, exercise increases our <strong><em>resilience</em></strong>.</p>
<p>A bonus is that, once we get that training effect from physical exercise, we can even handle psychological stress more comfortably.</p>
<p>Some people are just gifted with an ability to put out more work (or take more hits) than others, and still not be permanently or seriously damaged. But virtually all of us can build up resistance to stress by gradually increasing our stress level while holding back enough that we can still recover efficiently.</p>
<p>In the older research literature on the stress of work, it was pretty clear that people were working themselves to death. In the United States our idea of a full work-week has long been 40 hours. And at least part of the weekends are commonly time off or at least paid extra “overtime” salaries. (That appears to be changing as the rift between the well off and ordinary middle class and laboring people grows).</p>
<p>In many European countries, the work week is even shorter than that.  So now instead of hearing that work kills us, we often find studies concluding that <a href="http://www.medpagetoday.com/PrimaryCare/PreventiveCare/1980"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">retirement</span> kills us</a>.</p>
<p>It was Aaron Antonovky’s book “Health, Stress, and Coping” that helped clarify for us the importance of adaptation to and prompt recovery from stress. He spoke of “Stress resistance resources”; those resources underlie our ability to adapt to greater levels of stress. They are the primary source of resilience.</p>
<p>A great deal of research on resilience has centered on psychological patterns that make us more resilient. But Antonovsky saw that as only one category of factors that make us more resilient. For example, he included cultural or communal patterns that foster healthy, happy, successful, and resilient lives.</p>
<p>He did his research in Israel, a part of the world that included people who had been deprived of even the most basic resources that might help them adapt. These were survivors of Nazi concentration camps.  Of course they had a life before the camps, and had been able to develop inner resilience.</p>
<p>By tracking down the factors that differentiated people who came out of those camps and went on to do well, often exceptionally well, he concluded that some people have resources that lead them to be resilient even when those resources are taken from them.</p>
<p>He went on to say that researchers should turn their attention away from stress and toward resilience. He came to believe that we should be looking into what keeps us well (“Salutogenisis”) instead of what makes us ill (“Pathogenesis”).</p>
<p>He maintained that stress is so common that all of us are stressed enough to get sick from it.</p>
<p>That means we should focus on the science of resilience, which is what we have done.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F09%2F25%2F1490%2F&amp;linkname=Recovery%20and%20Adaptation" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Don’t Let Anger Give You a Heart Attack.</title>
		<link>/2013/05/29/dont-let-anger-give-you-a-heart-attack/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2013 03:55:42 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effective Communication]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Expressing Feelings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Focusing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience and Health]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1382</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[What should we do with anger bottled up inside of us? A recent article in the Washington Post discussed a serious effect of one option, that of letting out the raw anger, even to the point of throwing things and &#8230; <a href="/2013/05/29/dont-let-anger-give-you-a-heart-attack/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What should we do with anger bottled up inside of us? A <a href="http://articles.washingtonpost.com/2013-05-20/national/39387984_1_heart-attack-elizabeth-mostofsky-risk">recent article in the Washington Post</a> discussed a serious effect of one option, that of letting out the raw anger, even to the point of throwing things and threatening to hurt other people.</p>
<p>A common theme for some mental health professionals has been that we should get the anger out. For these therapists, sessions can consist of banging a pillow (usually representing  parents who were taken as having failed the client), with a bat that has many of the properties of a nasty club, but is in fact safely padded.</p>
<p>The Washington Post article describes a study in which about 4000 people who had heart attacks were asked about their experiences of anger. Heart attacks were twice as likely to occur after an episode of anger. There was a tendency for the heart attacks to occur within two hours of the anger episode.</p>
<p>Patients were also asked to rate how intense their anger episode had been, and the more intense the anger episode, the more likely patients were to have a heart attack.</p>
<p>So we have therapists trying to help us get the anger out versus research showing that expressing anger can lead to a heart attack.  So what are we to do? Should we bottled up our anger or express it?</p>
<p><span id="more-1382"></span></p>
<p>The Washington Post article says that “Bottling up of emotions is thought to harm both mind and body, but a new study suggests that doing the opposite may be no better.” What I want to do here is to be sure readers don’t take the options as limited to either “bottling up” or “doing the <span style="text-decoration: underline;">opposite</span>”, blowing your stack.</p>
<p>There is a lot of research indicating that, even though <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Anger-Misunderstood-Emotion-Carol-Tavris/dp/0671675230/ref=sr_1_3?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1369798270&amp;sr=1-3&amp;keywords=carol+tavris">letting out raw anger</a> harms you, striving to get clear about, articulate, and express your emotions has positive effects on the mind and body, not to mention on social relationships.</p>
<p>This is very different from blowing your stack or “<a href="/2011/04/18/articulation-of-feelings-is-not-the-same-as-venting/">venting</a>”, which has long been known to be an ineffective and typically damaging way to deal with distressing experiences.</p>
<p>It is important to learn how to <a href="/2011/05/03/focusing-a-highly-effective-way-to-resolve-distress/">understand your feelings when distressed</a>, and to articulate them without unnecessarily alienating others, especially others who might be able to help you minimize any potential damage coming from your stress. “Blowing your stack” is almost certain to amplify the impact of stress.</p>
<p>With stress amplification, your response to stress increases the physiological responses that make heart attacks more likely. That kind of response also may alienate your potential support systems and thus make   you less resilient and more vulnerable. It’s amazing how many people follow this totally ineffective pattern of stress management.</p>
<p>Your anger is there to protect you. It helps you to push against obstacles that can block you from reaching your goals, including people who are trying to dominate you in order to reach their own goals.</p>
<p>If you use anger well, it will be a powerful source of energy to help you reach your goals.</p>
<p>If, instead, you amplify the impact of your stress, you become your own enemy, often your own worst enemy.</p>
<p>To deal with anger you should not act on it. Don’t let your brain’s motor system rule you. You should attend to the anger and find out what it means.</p>
<p>To do this, you have to <a title="open a mental space in which you can gain a deep understanding of why you are angry" href="/2011/05/03/focusing-a-highly-effective-way-to-resolve-distress/">open a mental space in which you can gain a deep understanding of why you are angry</a>.</p>
<p>That way you are more likely to move toward your sensible goals instead of undermining yourself.</p>
<p>You should take time to attend to your angry reactions, focusing first on what you feel in your body.  Visit with those bodily reactions until they can be expressed in words.</p>
<p>When you do that, you shift from unwise, primitive commands from the parts of your brain that lead to mindless action. Instead you pull together and synthesize thoughts with emotions and then take action.</p>
<p>That synthesis is most likely to be the creative source of actions that are both wise and effective.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F05%2F29%2Fdont-let-anger-give-you-a-heart-attack%2F&amp;linkname=Don%E2%80%99t%20Let%20Anger%20Give%20You%20a%20Heart%20Attack." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
