<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Positivity/Negativity &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/positivitynegativity/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The Path to Greater Resilience: From Attitudes to Skills and to Habits.</title>
		<link>/2015/09/09/the-path-to-greater-resilience-from-attitudes-to-skills-and-to-habits/</link>
		<comments>/2015/09/09/the-path-to-greater-resilience-from-attitudes-to-skills-and-to-habits/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2015 20:41:26 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Attitudes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Habits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1982</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[When we discussed the Sense of Coherence in our previous post, we said that it was a match for the first factor in our three factor model of resilience. In both popular culture (e.g. Rev. Normal Vincent Peale’s “The Power &#8230; <a href="/2015/09/09/the-path-to-greater-resilience-from-attitudes-to-skills-and-to-habits/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When we discussed the Sense of Coherence in our previous post, we said that it was a match for the first factor in our three factor model of resilience.</p>
<p>In both popular culture (e.g. Rev. Normal Vincent Peale’s “The Power of Positive Thinking” which had a huge impact in the United States and elsewhere) and scientifically developed theory (e.g. Barbara Frederickson’s book, “Positivity”), the value of positivity has been recognized as playing a major role in lives well-lived.</p>
<p>But we see a distinction between attitudes of positivity and positive skills that are closely connected to those attitudes.</p>
<p>Probably most people would predict that positive attitudes and thoughts are related to resilience. But having skills such as knowing ways to calm and soothe yourself when distressed have been given less attention. In addition, many of us possess the needed skills, but do not implement them.</p>
<p>Once we take the skills to the point where we actually implement them when they are needed, we have reached the third level of using resilience tools, the level of habit.</p>
<p>In sum, we have to go from attitudes to skills and on to habits.</p>
<p>Isn’t this a lot of work? It can be, but for the most part the process is very enjoyable, even exhilarating at times.</p>
<p>Do we need to say that we think you should give it a try?</p>
<p>If you decide to do that, <a href="/2014/12/22/prepare-for-your-later-life-by-accumulating-skills-and-habits-of-resilience/">this</a> and <a href="/2014/10/08/build-your-toughness-and-become-more-resilient/">this</a> will help get you started.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2015%2F09%2F09%2Fthe-path-to-greater-resilience-from-attitudes-to-skills-and-to-habits%2F&amp;linkname=The%20Path%20to%20Greater%20Resilience%3A%20From%20Attitudes%20to%20Skills%20and%20to%20Habits." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2015/09/09/the-path-to-greater-resilience-from-attitudes-to-skills-and-to-habits/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Role of Resilience in Making Failure a Stepping Stone to Success</title>
		<link>/2015/02/04/the-role-of-resilience-in-making-failure-a-stepping-stone-to-success/</link>
		<comments>/2015/02/04/the-role-of-resilience-in-making-failure-a-stepping-stone-to-success/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2015 17:02:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[mental contrasting]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1832</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[They say that “dog bites man” is not worth reporting, but “man bites dog” is newsworthy. Some of our blog posts started as cases of “man bites dog”.   After decades in which “positive thinking” was generally accepted, those posts took &#8230; <a href="/2015/02/04/the-role-of-resilience-in-making-failure-a-stepping-stone-to-success/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>They say that “dog bites man” is not worth reporting, but “man bites dog” is newsworthy.</p>
<p>Some of our blog posts started as cases of “man bites dog”.   After decades in which “positive thinking” was generally accepted, those posts took a close look at a growing view that “negativity may be good for you”.  But we ended up concluding that arguments for negativity commonly turn out to be based on mere matters of how you <strong><em>define</em></strong> negativity.</p>
<p>Upon close examination, at least some claims for negativity appear to be simple matters of treating <strong><em>realism</em></strong> as negative thinking. For example, thinking through obstacles that might get in the way of reaching a desired goal is <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/10/26/opinion/sunday/the-problem-with-positive-thinking.html">considered negativity</a>.</p>
<p><span id="more-1832"></span></p>
<p>That realism helps us to reach our goals is clearly not a “man bites dog” story. Who would be intrigued by a story like that?</p>
<p>So must we conclude that positivity is simply good and negativity is simply bad? What about the many writings that affirm the value of failure?</p>
<p>It isn’t easy to dismiss the <a href="http://www.calebwojcik.com/blog/2012/01/30/quotes-overcome-fear-of-failure">statements of the highly successful</a> that <a href="http://www.goodreads.com/quotes/tag/failure">failure has been a central contributor</a> to their success.</p>
<p>But didn’t it require a lot of positivity to confront their mistakes, learn from them, and then take the chances that ultimately resulted in success? Surely hope, optimism, problem-solving, and other aspects of positivity were needed to enable persistence through failure on to the point of success.</p>
<p>Hope, optimism, and a problem-solving attitude are all important aspects of resilience. And there is research confirming that resilience makes success more likely.</p>
<p>Martin Seligman in his classic book, “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Learned-Optimism-Change-Your-Mind/dp/1400078393/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1423027034&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=learned+optimism">Learned Optimism</a>” has whole chapters describing how what he calls an “optimistic explanatory style” is linked to success in difficult sales jobs (Chapter 6) and in various aspects of athletic competition (Chapter 9).</p>
<p>The work on athletics is particularly relevant to our present discussion of the role of failure. Seligman found that athletes and teams with optimistic styles were more likely than others to come back and win after being behind in the game. They were able to snatch victory from what appeared to be a coming defeat.</p>
<p>One thing for sure is that a failure need not be a reason to give up on anything; not on reaching your goals and, most importantly, not on yourself.</p>
<p>Failures, painful as they may be, are opportunities to learn what doesn’t work and plan the next steps better informed than you were when you first planned how to reach your goals.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=&amp;linkname=" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2015/02/04/the-role-of-resilience-in-making-failure-a-stepping-stone-to-success/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Anticipating Barriers as an Aspect of Positivity.</title>
		<link>/2015/01/07/anticipating-barriers-as-an-aspect-of-positivity/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2015 22:50:33 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Expressing Feelings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Harvard Grant Study]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1815</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Should you do all in your power to block every negative thought from coming into your mind? Some people have argued that you cannot afford the luxury of a negative thought. A common refrain in our society is “Be positive!” &#8230; <a href="/2015/01/07/anticipating-barriers-as-an-aspect-of-positivity/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Should you do all in your power to block every negative thought from coming into your mind? Some people have argued that <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Cant-Afford-Luxury-Negative-Thought/dp/0931580242/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1420479276&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=you+can%27t+afford+the+luxury+of+a+negative+thought">you cannot afford the luxury of a negative thought</a>.</p>
<p>A common refrain in our society is “Be positive!” And there is a great deal of research supporting the idea that <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Positivity-Top-Notch-Research-Reveals-Change/dp/0307393747/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1420479383&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=positivity+barbara+fredrickson">positivity is good for you</a>. But can you really turn your mind from negative to positive on demand? Does that really help?</p>
<p><a href="http://www.abebooks.com/servlet/BookDetailsPL?bi=14729916967&amp;searchurl=x%3D64%26y%3D4%26bi%3D0%26ds%3D30%26sts%3Dt%26bx%3Doff%26sortby%3D17%26tn%3Dthe+nature+of+emotion%26an%3Dpaul+ekman%26recentlyadded%3Dall">Convincing research</a> indicates that pretending we are not distressed when we really are results in physiological responses that are known to be unhealthy, e.g. high blood pressure. This doesn’t happen if we <a href="http://www.utexas.edu/features/archive/2005/writing.html">get to think and talk about our feelings of distress</a>, which inevitably involves letting negative thoughts and feelings enter your mind.</p>
<p>More than a few highly competent researchers have argued that there are actually benefits to negativity.</p>
<p><span id="more-1815"></span></p>
<p>One of them, <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2014/09/dont-think-positively/379993/">Dr. Julie Norem</a>, maintains that many of us do well by using a strategy of “defensive pessimism”. This means that, when we set a goal, we go on to review all the things that might go wrong, then develop ways of preventing the anticipated problems from blocking our success.</p>
<p>To us, that strategy is just common sense, but we would not have thought of it as pessimism.</p>
<p>In the famous <a href="http://www.abebooks.com/servlet/SearchResults?an=george+vaillant&amp;sts=t&amp;tn=adaptation+to+life">Harvard Grant Study</a>, participants were tested and interviewed regularly over their lifetime.  <em>Anticipation</em>, a tendency to look ahead for problems and avoid being blind-sided by them was identified as a healthy way to live. Anticipation is one of the “healthy defense mechanisms” identified in that study. And it seems to be “defensive pessimism” by another name.</p>
<p>It’s not clear to us why that kind of behavior should be categorized as negative and labeled “defensive pessimism”. It could as well be deemed a way to deal with reality and prepare for problems we are likely to confront. It is more like “realism” than “pessimism”.</p>
<p>It also seems to us that defensive pessimism implies that you are hopeful enough to look for solutions that can get you to your goal. That’s a pretty positive attitude, very different from something like “It’s no use. There is nothing I can do to succeed in this situation”, which is clearly negative. See this <a href="/2011/08/09/handling-distress-the-power-of-optimism-hope-and-a-problem-solving-attitude/">earlier post</a> for an interesting case of shifting a person from hopeless pessimism to problem solving.</p>
<p>In our research on resilience, we found that optimism is linked to a “problem solving attitude”, which seems to be exactly what defensive pessimists have.</p>
<p>However, it doesn’t matter what you call it; anticipating problems and finding solutions to them is a good way to deal effectivly with life’s challenges.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2015%2F01%2F07%2Fanticipating-barriers-as-an-aspect-of-positivity%2F&amp;linkname=Anticipating%20Barriers%20as%20an%20Aspect%20of%20Positivity." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Resilience and Grit</title>
		<link>/2014/09/08/resilience-and-grit/</link>
		<comments>/2014/09/08/resilience-and-grit/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2014 06:17:14 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Research]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1722</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This post was based on our reactions to a YouTube Ted Talk by Angela Duckworth on the topic of grit. It is best to take a look at it and then come back to our discussion. The key idea in &#8230; <a href="/2014/09/08/resilience-and-grit/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This post was based on our reactions to a YouTube <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H14bBuluwB8">Ted Talk by Angela Duckworth on the topic of grit</a>. It is best to take a look at it and then come back to our discussion.</p>
<p><iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/H14bBuluwB8" frameborder="0" width="560" height="315"></iframe></p>
<p>The key idea in Dr. Duckworth’s talk is that grit is more important than IQ in predicting academic success. It is also linked to other benefits such as being happier and more satisfied with your life. Anything that can make people more successful, happier, and more satisfied with their lives deserves attention.</p>
<p>Given the apparent benefits of grit, you may well want to know how much of it you have. You can find out your own level of grit by taking the grit test Dr. Duckworth developed. It is <a href="http://www.sas.upenn.edu/~duckwort/images/12-item%20Grit%20Scale.05312011.pdf">here</a>.</p>
<p>You might also want to <strong><em>increase</em></strong> your grit. So far, there does not seem to be a clear path to developing more grit. We suspect that a major part of the path lies in increasing your resilience.</p>
<p><span id="more-1722"></span></p>
<p>A core, maybe even <strong><em>the</em></strong> core of grit is perseverance. Dr. Duckworth uses a racing metaphor. People with grit lead life as a marathon, not as a sprint.</p>
<p>One of the most notable characteristics of resilient people is that they are optimistic. And one of the characteristics of optimists is their perseverance. In fact, the perseverance of optimists is a characteristic that can be a problem for them because they may not know when it is time to stop and change direction.</p>
<p>People doing research and developing theories on topics like grit and resilience seem to be inclined to view some characteristics as simply “good for you” and others as simply “bad for you”.</p>
<p>But most things are good or bad, depending on how far you push them.</p>
<p>If you are too much of a butterfly that flits from flower to flower, you are not being gritty. On the other hand, if you push grittiness too far, you are may well harm yourself.</p>
<p>A good example of carrying persistence too far is working <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-04-04/work-days-of-11-hours-boost-risk-for-heart-disease-study-says.html">too many hours</a>. Many people today think that pushing their bodies to greater and greater limits is healthy but they are wrong to see no limits to the amount of exertion that is healthy.  Older research consistently showed that extending physical work too long kills people and contemporary research is showing the same thing.</p>
<p>Can too much grit damage your health? It would seem to be likely, in light of what we pointed out above. Duckworth and Eskreis-Winkler have  pointed out that <a href="http://www.psychologicalscience.org/index.php/publications/observer/2013/april-13/true-grit.html?utm_source=socialmedia&amp;utm_medium=sociallinks&amp;utm_campaign=twitter">we need research on that topic</a>.</p>
<p>Grit is a pretty new focus of attention, and we see an increase of research on the topic. We need to keep an eye on that research. We are likely to learn more about how to build grit. Hopefully there will be research on the relationship between grit and optimism.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F09%2F08%2Fresilience-and-grit%2F&amp;linkname=Resilience%20and%20Grit" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2014/09/08/resilience-and-grit/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Optimism and Vigilance</title>
		<link>/2014/05/28/optimism-and-vigilance/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2014 03:09:52 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Harvard Grant Study]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1652</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Our experience has been that people who are optimistic, even those who strike us as unduly optimistic, lead more satisfying and fulfilling lives than those who are not optimistic. Provided they do not push too hard on reasonable limits of &#8230; <a href="/2014/05/28/optimism-and-vigilance/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Our experience has been that people who are optimistic, even those who strike us as unduly optimistic, lead more satisfying and fulfilling lives than those who are not optimistic. Provided they do not push too hard on reasonable limits of optimistic prediction, optimsts seem to do better than most people.</p>
<p>Furthermore, there is a lot of scientific evidence that optimism results in improvements in many aspects of life. (for example in <a href="http://www.forbes.com/2011/02/18/optimism-job-success-pay-leadership-careers-promotion.html">work performance</a> and <a href="http://www.eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2002-08/mc-mcs081202.php">physical health</a>).</p>
<p>On the other hand, a major study of what leads to a life well-lived, the Harvard Grant Study, indicates that “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Adaptation-Life-George-E-Vaillant/dp/0674004140">Anticipation</a>”(pages 114-116) is a factor that leads to a better life. Anticipation is looking at a wide range of risks and benefits to prepare for most problems that might come up and planning ahead to minimize the impact of those risks.</p>
<p>Yet, anticipation can go too far. One form of that is called “hyper-vigilance”, and it can be very damaging. It is a known aspect of post-traumatic stress disorder.</p>
<p>A major aspect of hyper-vigilance is an extreme form of anticipation. People who have experienced intense trauma, such as multiple military deployments, are often so vigilant that even a few hours of sleep can terrify them because they cannot be vigilant when they are asleep.</p>
<p>So, pushing anticipation too far is a serious problem but is extra optimism also a problem?</p>
<p>A major barrier to thinking about such issues is the tendency for psychologists and self-help gurus to break things down into “black or white” categories.  For example, “optimism and positivity are good”, but “wariness and pessimism are bad”.</p>
<p><a href="/2014/04/30/stop-doing-things-that-make-you-more-vulnerable-and-less-resilient/?#comment-18752">Christine Olmstead’s comments</a> on yin and yang drew our attention to a Buddhist view that too much Yin can become Yang. If you are not familiar with the contrast between Yin and Yang, click <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ezmR9Attpyc">here</a> for a quick explanation.</p>
<p>This Buddhist view is consistent with that of Aristotle, who argued that vice results when a virtue is overdone or underdone.</p>
<p>Optimism, when taken too far, may take the form of having unrealistic expectations or even of delusional grandiosity or mania.</p>
<p>What we think works is optimism <strong><em>tempered by</em></strong> anticipation. That means looking on the bright side of things while also adjusting your expectations by carefully monitoring the situation you are in, and, in particular, balancing the payoffs you can get from your choices against the losses that may be entailed when you act on them.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F05%2F27%2Flooking-at-the-bright-side-of-situations-versus-endless-looking-for-threats%2F&amp;linkname=Looking%20at%20the%20bright%20side%20of%20situations%20versus%20endless%20looking%20for%20threats.%20%20%20" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Some Common Ways People Make Stress Worse</title>
		<link>/2014/01/08/some-common-ways-people-make-stress-worse/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2014 18:52:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Self-Criticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1568</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Rather than soothing themselves, it is very common for people to react to stress in ways that make things worse. Here are two key reactions that amplify instead minimizing reactions to stress: To treat yourself in ways that increase the &#8230; <a href="/2014/01/08/some-common-ways-people-make-stress-worse/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rather than soothing themselves, it is very common for people to react to stress in ways that make things worse. Here are two key reactions that amplify instead minimizing reactions to stress:</p>
<ol start="1">
<li>To treat yourself in ways that increase the stress or undermine your ability to cope with it. Usually this involves exaggerating the power of the stressful event or blaming and attacking yourself, thus turning your capacity for aggression against yourself at the very time when you need to hear a supportive, helpful voice, even if it is your own voice.</li>
<li>To treat people who are likely sources of help in ways that lead them to withdraw their support, or even to strike back at you and pile on another source of stress.</li>
</ol>
<p>There are two main ways you can treat yourself that make things worse.  You can:</p>
<p>1.            Catastrophize</p>
<p>2.            Attack yourself with criticism</p>
<p>In this post we will discuss the first of these ways, those involved in how you treat yourself. We will also explain what you can do to avoid undermining of yourself.</p>
<p>In later posts we will cover the issues about 1. overcoming any tendency you may have to criticize yourself, and 2. Learning how to help your supporters support you.</p>
<p><span id="more-1568"></span></p>
<p>Catastrophizing has to do with the ways you talk to yourself when trouble comes your way.</p>
<p>A person who amplifies stress might say that what has happened is not just bad. It is “awful” “outrageous” “unbearable”, “catastrophic”. You can probably extend this list yourself. It is basically a matter of over-estimating the power of the distressing event.</p>
<p>The antidote is to learn to tell yourself, more realistically, that you “really don’t like this, but can manage it”, “hate it, but have enough grit to deal with it” or that it is “inconvenient”,“annoying”, or “hurtful” but not catastrophic.</p>
<p>Basically, to escape the pattern of catastrophizing is a matter of examining and disputing the evidence you have in favor of the idea that “This is catastrophic”. If you are catastrophizing, that evidence will be slim or even missing. If so, you have to develop a more realistic interpretation of what happened, and then find more useful self-statements.</p>
<p>Then you must resolutely guide your mind to the interpretations that are more realistic and more helpful.</p>
<p>If you have a habit of catastrophizing, you may have to “drill the new interpretations into your head”, repeatedly drawing your mind back to them whenever it drifts to the more familiar, catastrophizing mode.</p>
<p>Whenever you find yourself catastrophizing, you can say “This is my cue to start talking to myself in more realistic and more helpful ways”.</p>
<p>No one learns in primary school that how you talk to yourself has a major effect on how you react to the events of your life. That is too bad. The reality of this has been understood since ancient times, and repeatedly rediscovered. Currently it is an approach that psychotherapists have found helpful over many years, supported with a substantial body of scientific research. It goes under various names, such as “cognitive therapy” or “cognitive behavioral therapy”.</p>
<p>You may need help from a therapist to change your habitual way of dealing with yourself, but often you can improve substantially on your own.  If self-help doesn’t work, consider getting help from a therapist. If you think that implies that you are “crazy”, you are amazingly out of date.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why Do So Many Successful People Praise Failure?</title>
		<link>/2013/09/11/why-do-so-many-successful-people-praise-failure/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2013 03:23:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Self-Criticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Compassion]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1479</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Nobody wants to fail, or, worse, BE a failure. Failure is associated with shame, financial ruin, living a harder life, diminished status, not being able to contribute to your family’s resources.… Yet, we often see and hear what appears to &#8230; <a href="/2013/09/11/why-do-so-many-successful-people-praise-failure/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Nobody wants to fail, or, worse, BE a failure. Failure is associated with shame, financial ruin, living a harder life, diminished status, not being able to contribute to your family’s resources.…</p>
<p>Yet, we often see and hear what appears to be praise for failure. What could this be about?</p>
<p><span id="more-1479"></span></p>
<p>People who praise failure are not really talking about a lust for failure; they are talking about an important role of failure in teaching paths to success.</p>
<p>They are also talking about how avoidance of failure, or refusal to acknowledge failure can keep you from understanding what went wrong with your ineffective tries, and thus from seeing how to do better.</p>
<p>Here is an example: Debbie and I often watch Fareed Zakaria’s weekly TV show, “<a href="http://globalpublicsquare.blogs.cnn.com/category/gps-episodes/">GPS</a>” (Global Public Square).  A week or so ago, he interviewed Sara Blakely, an attractive young woman who went from cold call sales of copy machines to creating a business that made her a billionaire. She invented Spanx, an undergarment  she says makes women look better. Obviously many women agree with her.</p>
<p>In that interview, Ms. Blakely talked about the important role of her father in teaching her what it takes to succeed. He taught his children to boldly try new things, and, when they failed praised them for the try and gave them a “high five”.  He taught them not to avoid risk, and to see failure as a positive aspect of life, a key aspect of adaptation to the world as it is.</p>
<p>When Charlie Rose interviewed renowned golf champion, Ben Hogan, he asked Hogan about how he reacted to one of his greatest tournament failures. Hogan said it was the best thing that ever happened to him.  He embraced his mistakes, and learned from them. Many other golf masters have made similar comments.</p>
<p>Placed in the context of the resilience factors we have been discussing in the recent blog posts, these highly accomplished people are expressing  attitudes that are resilient with respect to Factor One (Resilient Attitudes and Skills).  They respond to failures with resilient attitudes  of <span style="text-decoration: underline;">positivity</span> and <span style="text-decoration: underline;">a problem-solving perspective</span>.</p>
<p>In addition, they do not cut their legs out from under themselves with unreasonable self-criticism. So they have resilient qualities reflected in Factor Two (Self-Compassion versus Self-Criticism).</p>
<p>So what the “pro-failure” people are really saying is that we need to grant ourselves the space to learn from our mistakes. If we pass up opportunities in order to avoid risk, or deny our role in failure, we will not learn to adapt to the world we live in.</p>
<p>Making mistakes does not make us “losers”, but we have the option of interpreting our mistakes either in ways that make us lose or in ways that help us win.</p>
<p>Once again, we see the power of “<a href="/2013/04/25/how-to-teach-your-worrier-brain-to-function-like-a-warrior-brain/">Reappraisal</a>”. If we see failure as an opportunity to learn, failure can be a positive influence. If we see it as humiliating, even unspeakable, or give ourselves no option other than to deny that it was our mistake, our adaptation to life will be thwarted.</p>
<p>We do not have to be afraid of making mistakes. Dealing with them is a known path to doing better in life.</p>
<p>Zorba the Greek said “Life is trouble. Only death is not. To be alive is to undo your belt and *look* for trouble.”</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F09%2F11%2Fwhy-do-so-many-successful-people-praise-failure%2F&amp;linkname=Why%20Do%20So%20Many%20Successful%20People%20Praise%20Failure%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Magic of Small Changes</title>
		<link>/2013/08/27/the-magic-of-small-changes/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2013 03:06:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[How Hard Is It To Change Resilience?]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1470</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[There is an unusual poem by award-winning poet, Mona van Duyn, which illustrates some key aspects of resilience. Please read the poem. I know that many people do not like poetry, and see the core of it as rhyming. This &#8230; <a href="/2013/08/27/the-magic-of-small-changes/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There is an unusual poem by award-winning poet, Mona van Duyn, which illustrates some key aspects of resilience. Please read <a href="http://www.poets.org/viewmedia.php/prmMID/15674">the poem</a>. I know that many people do not like poetry, and see the core of it as rhyming.</p>
<p>This poem could be called a “prose poem”, and it is quite readable and lacks rhyme. And it’s over the top gloominess is even funny in spots.</p>
<p>The poem is called “Letters from a Father”. The letters come from an elderly father and are written to his daughter.</p>
<p>So please give it a chance so you can make sense of our comments on it.</p>
<p>Here is a synopsis that will allow you to understand how our linking it to resilience makes sense.</p>
<p>An elderly father speaks for both himself and his elderly wife. They seem both to have given up on life, and see themselves as on the threshold of death.</p>
<p>The daughter has sent them a bird feeder and feed, and the letters focus on how she is wasting her money on parents who won’t live long enough to enjoy the results.</p>
<p>Slowly the letters begin to reflect the parent’s re-engagement with life, as seen by the father’s diminished focus on death and increasing enjoyment of the birds, as well as pride in how well they are doing in getting interesting birds to visit.</p>
<p>Basically, that’s it.</p>
<p>Here are our comments on how this poem relates to resilience, and, in particular, how simple, small changes can move us from negativity and despair to positivity. Such changes can help us to shift from a morbid view of life to engrossment in the beauty of even a simple part of our lives.</p>
<p><span id="more-1470"></span></p>
<p>Small changes can result in major shifts in how resilient we are and in how we appreciate and enjoy our lives. Here is a valuable quotation from a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Small-Change-Little-Things-Difference/dp/1585423599/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1377485594&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=Terkel+%22small+change%22">book by Susan and Larry Terkel entitled “Small Change”</a>.</p>
<p>“Small change adds up. This is worth repeating: small change adds up. Empty your small change in a jar every day, and watch the total add up over time. Make small changes in your daily habits – such as your meals or snacks, your relationships, your work, or your leisure- and watch those changes gradually accumulate into a much healthier, happier, and more satisfying life.”</p>
<p>“An angle of only one degree is difficult to draw on a piece of paper. It is too small. If a flight from New York to Los Angeles is off course by just one degree, the plane will arrive closer to Tijuana, Mexico, than Los Angeles.”</p>
<p>“Small changes can get us back on course as easily as the can lead us off course”</p>
<p>For more about “small change”, click <a href="/2011/01/20/small-changes-can-result-in-big-improvements-in-resilience/">here.</a></p>
<p>We know very well how easy it is to give up on learning how to live a fulsome life. Life can be so densely hard that we may come to believe that nothing short of a miracle could make things better.</p>
<p>The pain of life can make us oblivious to the value of gifts (maybe we should say “blessings”) that fall in our laps. And this devaluation of the good things that come our way can lead us to pass up the opportunities for happiness that are offered to us for free.</p>
<p>In this poem, two elderly people who are in despair are drawn back to the joy that remains for them. And, in this case, all it took was a bird feeder and some seeds.</p>
<p>The Poem illustrates not only the value of small changes, but also the importance of other people in our resilience. The daughter played an essential role.</p>
<p>Resilience is not just inside us. There is a great deal of research that shows that we live better and healthier lives if we get support from others.</p>
<p>So the pathway from vulnerability to resilience includes not only shifts within us, but also shifts in our selection of the people who provide our life’s context. Our family and friends are more than the people we care about; they are also important sources of the support we need to get successfully to a healthy, satisfying life.”</p>
<p>Take an appreciative look at those people, and maybe even let them know how important they are to you.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F08%2F27%2Fthe-magic-of-small-changes%2F&amp;linkname=The%20magic%20of%20small%20changes" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Suppression of Emotions, Positive or Negative, Increases Your Body’s Stress Burden</title>
		<link>/2013/08/05/suppression-of-emotions-positive-or-negative-increases-your-bodys-stress-burden/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2013 04:22:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Expressing Feelings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1456</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Up until now we have discussed the value of expressing emotions when you are distressed. When you become clear about your feelings and safely express them, it has a calming effect. Expressiveness is a wonderful tool for self-soothing. Do the &#8230; <a href="/2013/08/05/suppression-of-emotions-positive-or-negative-increases-your-bodys-stress-burden/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Up until now we have discussed the value of expressing emotions when you are distressed. When you become clear about your feelings and safely express them, it has a calming effect. Expressiveness is a wonderful tool for self-soothing.</p>
<p>Do the opposite effects occur when suppressing positive emotions?</p>
<p>You may think, “Why would anyone suppress positive emotions?”</p>
<p>It’s actually not unusual. Think of a saying like “Pride goeth before a fall”. There is a tendency to believe that you will be punished if you are too joyful.</p>
<p>Many people learn as they grow up to keep a stony look on their face. It’s just what serious, hardworking people do.</p>
<p>Also, when learning to suppress negative feelings, the suppression can easily spread to all feelings.</p>
<p>I just googled the phrase “keep a straight face”, and there were many entries, most of them on <em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">learning how</span></em> to keep a straight face. So it seems that people are looking for ways to suppress their feelings.</p>
<p>I could give many more examples showing how deep our fear of expressing joy is. But this is enough to show that studying the effects of suppressing positive feelings is a worthwhile enterprise.</p>
<p>In this post I want to describe some exceptionally well-designed research that revealed the physiological impact of suppressing positive and negative emotions.</p>
<p><span id="more-1456"></span></p>
<p>What I have to say here is based on elegant research done by James Gross and Robert Levenson, and published in two papers.</p>
<p><a title="The first of the papers" href="http://ist-socrates.berkeley.edu/~ucbpl/docs/48-Emotion%20Elicitation95.pdf">The first of the papers</a> described how they developed effective methods of producing authentic emotions in the laboratory. They edited sections of videos that seemed capable of producing emotions. And then they went on to test whether their selections actually worked. Two good examples are the “faking orgasm” scene in “When Harry Met Sally” (to produce amusement) and actual footage of the surgical removal of a human arm (to produce disgust).</p>
<p>They spent years developing and testing these videos, and the videos worked well and better than previous methods.</p>
<p>In <a title="the second paper" href="http://ist-socrates.berkeley.edu/~ucbpl/docs/51-Hiding%20Feelings97.pdf">the second paper</a>, they tested, among many other things, whether suppression of both positive and negative emotions elicited increases in physiological activity that correspond to the well known stress response of fight or flight.</p>
<p>That kind of reaction includes faster heart rate, sweaty hands, faster breathing and a wide range of other bodily responses that are useful for surviving when confronted with a lethal threat, but damaging when you experience them regularly at work, at home, or in any place that is part of your everyday life.</p>
<p>Their conclusion was clear: suppression of either kind of emotion elicits a fight or flight response.</p>
<p>So it would seem to be wise to avoid a life in which you are regularly or even constantly needing to suppress your feelings.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F08%2F05%2Fsuppression-of-emotions-positive-or-negative-increases-your-bodys-stress-burden%2F&amp;linkname=Suppression%20of%20Emotions%2C%20Positive%20or%20Negative%2C%20Increases%20Your%20Body%E2%80%99s%20Stress%20Burden" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Can Foreseeing a Dark Future Result in Less Disability and Lower Likelihood of Death?</title>
		<link>/2013/03/07/can-foreseeing-a-dark-future-result-in-less-disability-and-lower-likelihood-of-death/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2013 18:16:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Harvard Grant Study]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1334</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[About a week ago, Debbie came back from her morning run and said she heard on the radio that a study had been published supporting the idea that pessimism is more conducive to physical health than optimism. She went on &#8230; <a href="/2013/03/07/can-foreseeing-a-dark-future-result-in-less-disability-and-lower-likelihood-of-death/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>About a week ago, Debbie came back from her morning run and said she heard on the radio that a study had been published supporting the idea that pessimism is more conducive to physical health than optimism.</p>
<p>She went on to say that, based on the description of what was being called “pessimism”, it struck her as “anticipation”, which is a well-known successful way of coping with life. Anticipation means looking ahead to the future so that you can avoid being blind-sided by events.</p>
<p>There is abundant research showing that optimism is much more helpful than pessimism, e.g. this article. If there are circumstances in which pessimism beats optimism, we need to know about them.</p>
<p>In this post we will tell you about the results of our search for the details of this study and our interpretation of the results.</p>
<p><span id="more-1334"></span></p>
<p>Please be patient; it will take a few paragraphs to explain how the study was done.</p>
<p>It was done on a representative sample of 10,000 Germans. This means that they had an unusually large sample and respondents were selected in a pattern that matched the population of their country. Participants were tested and retested for eleven years. Most studies are one-shot deals, so duration of the study is a plus.</p>
<p>They were asked at the beginning of the study and in each subsequent year to rate their current quality of life, and to predict the quality of life they expected five years in the future.</p>
<p>If they predicted less life satisfaction than actually occurred, they were categorized as pessimistic (a pretty good common sense measure of optimism versus pessimism).</p>
<p>If their actual life satisfaction was worse than they had predicted, they were deemed optimistic; their expectations were more positive than what really happened. If they accurately predicted their future life satisfaction, they were deemed realistic.</p>
<p>The study divided participants in age categories ranging from Young adults (18-39 years), Middle-aged adults (40-64 years), and Older adults (65+ years).</p>
<p>Their outcome measures, i.e. what the study sought to predict, was disability or death.</p>
<p>They found that “Older adults” who underestimated how satisfying their future lives would be had less disability or death than those who were optimistic or realistic in their predictions. However, this worked only for the older adults, and the people rated as pessimistic were only 2 to 3 percent less likely to be disabled or dead than realists or optimists. In addition, the older adult sample included 856 people, whereas the other age groups each included 3 to 4 thousand.</p>
<p>Conclusion</p>
<p>This study had an unusual measure of optimism versus pessimism. A much more tested one, which is a very good predictor of future health can be found here. It is free, and you can take it and score it yourself.</p>
<p>The years from 65 up are a period of rapid change, much like the years from birth to young adulthood. Older people routinely have parents, friends, relatives, etc. they have seen develop various illnesses and losing a range of capacities they once had, and also dying. A common lament of older people is that so many, or even all, of their friends have died. And many worry about observed loss of various cognitive function, e.g. “a senior moment”.</p>
<p>An older adult who is alert is likely to realize what is in their future, and prepare for it. That is anticipation. I think Debbie had it right.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F03%2F07%2Fcan-foreseeing-a-dark-future-result-in-less-disability-and-lower-likelihood-of-death%2F&amp;linkname=Can%20Foreseeing%20a%20Dark%20Future%20Result%20in%20Less%20Disability%20and%20Lower%20Likelihood%20of%20Death%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
