<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Harvard Grant Study &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/harvard-grant-study/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Tips on Resilient Aging 3</title>
		<link>/2016/03/17/tips-on-resilient-aging-3/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2016 18:05:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Harvard Grant Study]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2041</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[&#160; (Note: we are dealing with a long chain of  technological failures, so this post was prepared on our iPad. Please forgive errors.) &#160; This is the third of a series of groundbreaking studies dealing with aging that we are &#8230; <a href="/2016/03/17/tips-on-resilient-aging-3/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>(Note: we are dealing with a long chain of  technological failures, so this post was prepared on our iPad. Please forgive errors.)</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>This is the third of a series of groundbreaking studies dealing with aging that we are covering in this blog-the Harvard Grant Study.</p>
<p>I For many decades there has been a study going on of characteristics leading to overall life success of Harvard students. To give you a sense of how long the study has been taking place, President John Kennedy was one of the undergraduates studied, and it is still going on.</p>
<p>The meaning of &#8220;overall life success&#8221; was borrowed from Freud, who defined it as the ability to love and to work, i.e. to develop stable loving relationships and a productive, satisfying career.</p>
<p>For many years, the head of the Grant Study was George Vaillant and he published &#8220;Adaptation to Life&#8221;, a very useful book for anyone interested in details on how others have lived happy, fruitful lives.</p>
<p>Vaillant described several adaptive styles that led to success. Here is a list of them:</p>
<p>1. Anticipation: being aware of future challenges and planning how you will avoid being blinded by them.<br />
2. Suppression: After doing what can be done about difficult circumstances, being able to put them aside and direct your attention to things that are in your control.<br />
3. Humor: People who used humor to help deal with stress did better than the humorless.<br />
4. Altruism: Taking the needs of others seriously, and letting them be important to you in the ways your own needs are important.<br />
5. Sublimation: Fulfilling unconscious yet unacceptable urges by putting your energy into doing something that is socially useful and acceptable that fulfills those urges. Two participants in the study illustrated this contrast. Both went hungry in their youth. One of them became determined to never be deprived again. The other sublimated his feelings by working<br />
for the US Department of Agriculture in the area of food aid.</p>
<p>How can you make use of this information?</p>
<p>Vaillant interpreted the studies within a Freudian framework. He saw these adaptive styles as &#8220;defense mechanisms&#8221;, which are ways we control our anxieties and keep undesirable desires out of our conscious awareness. Normally defense mechanisms are not seen as controllable by the conscious mind. Our purpose in this blog has never been to do psychotherapy,especially not depth therapy,like psychoanalysis,that attempts to uncover thoughts and feelings from the unconscious. Instead,we teach people to change their thoughts and habits,and even environments,to ones that help them do well in life. Looking at the five items in our list above, here are some ways to put some of them to use without venturing into depth psychology.</p>
<p>Anticipation</p>
<p>Anticipation is looking ahead, and planning for ways we might be able to get control of predictable stressors,then using the results of our planning to maximize good outcomes and minimize bad ones.</p>
<p>Try this: Imagine how you would like to be in the future(for example, six months or a year from now). Imagine the obstacles that might get in the way of your reaching your goals.Pick one of the barriers and plan ways to get past it. When opportunities arise to do this again, repeat with another barrier. Continue this until you can clearly imagine a reasonably smooth path to success.</p>
<p>Suppression:</p>
<p>Suppression is allowing yourself to be aware of your feelings without acting on them. An example of useful suppression: The idea that &#8220;I&#8217;ll cry tomorrow&#8221; allows you to be aware of your sadness, but also allows you to do what you need to do until the time is right for expressing the feeling.</p>
<p>Humor</p>
<p>A few decades ago, Norman Cousins, had a disease that his doctors could not cure. He decided to cure himself by watching films that made him laugh. He wrote a book about how this worked out, and felt it was quite successful.</p>
<p>The research literature on the healing effects of laughter, or of humor in general, despite having some evidence of such healing effects, does not lead to sound conclusions. However the use of laughter in common experiences lends support to the idea that laughter is beneficial. Laughter can engage us in ways that enable us to put aside painful thoughts, for a time even painful realities. In the meanwhile our resilience resources can replenish us and give us the stamina to settle the situation.</p>
<p>We need more and better research on various aspects of humor before reaching solid conclusions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Anticipating Barriers as an Aspect of Positivity.</title>
		<link>/2015/01/07/anticipating-barriers-as-an-aspect-of-positivity/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2015 22:50:33 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Expressing Feelings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Harvard Grant Study]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1815</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Should you do all in your power to block every negative thought from coming into your mind? Some people have argued that you cannot afford the luxury of a negative thought. A common refrain in our society is “Be positive!” &#8230; <a href="/2015/01/07/anticipating-barriers-as-an-aspect-of-positivity/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Should you do all in your power to block every negative thought from coming into your mind? Some people have argued that <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Cant-Afford-Luxury-Negative-Thought/dp/0931580242/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1420479276&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=you+can%27t+afford+the+luxury+of+a+negative+thought">you cannot afford the luxury of a negative thought</a>.</p>
<p>A common refrain in our society is “Be positive!” And there is a great deal of research supporting the idea that <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Positivity-Top-Notch-Research-Reveals-Change/dp/0307393747/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1420479383&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=positivity+barbara+fredrickson">positivity is good for you</a>. But can you really turn your mind from negative to positive on demand? Does that really help?</p>
<p><a href="http://www.abebooks.com/servlet/BookDetailsPL?bi=14729916967&amp;searchurl=x%3D64%26y%3D4%26bi%3D0%26ds%3D30%26sts%3Dt%26bx%3Doff%26sortby%3D17%26tn%3Dthe+nature+of+emotion%26an%3Dpaul+ekman%26recentlyadded%3Dall">Convincing research</a> indicates that pretending we are not distressed when we really are results in physiological responses that are known to be unhealthy, e.g. high blood pressure. This doesn’t happen if we <a href="http://www.utexas.edu/features/archive/2005/writing.html">get to think and talk about our feelings of distress</a>, which inevitably involves letting negative thoughts and feelings enter your mind.</p>
<p>More than a few highly competent researchers have argued that there are actually benefits to negativity.</p>
<p><span id="more-1815"></span></p>
<p>One of them, <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2014/09/dont-think-positively/379993/">Dr. Julie Norem</a>, maintains that many of us do well by using a strategy of “defensive pessimism”. This means that, when we set a goal, we go on to review all the things that might go wrong, then develop ways of preventing the anticipated problems from blocking our success.</p>
<p>To us, that strategy is just common sense, but we would not have thought of it as pessimism.</p>
<p>In the famous <a href="http://www.abebooks.com/servlet/SearchResults?an=george+vaillant&amp;sts=t&amp;tn=adaptation+to+life">Harvard Grant Study</a>, participants were tested and interviewed regularly over their lifetime.  <em>Anticipation</em>, a tendency to look ahead for problems and avoid being blind-sided by them was identified as a healthy way to live. Anticipation is one of the “healthy defense mechanisms” identified in that study. And it seems to be “defensive pessimism” by another name.</p>
<p>It’s not clear to us why that kind of behavior should be categorized as negative and labeled “defensive pessimism”. It could as well be deemed a way to deal with reality and prepare for problems we are likely to confront. It is more like “realism” than “pessimism”.</p>
<p>It also seems to us that defensive pessimism implies that you are hopeful enough to look for solutions that can get you to your goal. That’s a pretty positive attitude, very different from something like “It’s no use. There is nothing I can do to succeed in this situation”, which is clearly negative. See this <a href="/2011/08/09/handling-distress-the-power-of-optimism-hope-and-a-problem-solving-attitude/">earlier post</a> for an interesting case of shifting a person from hopeless pessimism to problem solving.</p>
<p>In our research on resilience, we found that optimism is linked to a “problem solving attitude”, which seems to be exactly what defensive pessimists have.</p>
<p>However, it doesn’t matter what you call it; anticipating problems and finding solutions to them is a good way to deal effectivly with life’s challenges.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2015%2F01%2F07%2Fanticipating-barriers-as-an-aspect-of-positivity%2F&amp;linkname=Anticipating%20Barriers%20as%20an%20Aspect%20of%20Positivity." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Optimism and Vigilance</title>
		<link>/2014/05/28/optimism-and-vigilance/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2014 03:09:52 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Harvard Grant Study]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1652</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Our experience has been that people who are optimistic, even those who strike us as unduly optimistic, lead more satisfying and fulfilling lives than those who are not optimistic. Provided they do not push too hard on reasonable limits of &#8230; <a href="/2014/05/28/optimism-and-vigilance/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Our experience has been that people who are optimistic, even those who strike us as unduly optimistic, lead more satisfying and fulfilling lives than those who are not optimistic. Provided they do not push too hard on reasonable limits of optimistic prediction, optimsts seem to do better than most people.</p>
<p>Furthermore, there is a lot of scientific evidence that optimism results in improvements in many aspects of life. (for example in <a href="http://www.forbes.com/2011/02/18/optimism-job-success-pay-leadership-careers-promotion.html">work performance</a> and <a href="http://www.eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2002-08/mc-mcs081202.php">physical health</a>).</p>
<p>On the other hand, a major study of what leads to a life well-lived, the Harvard Grant Study, indicates that “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Adaptation-Life-George-E-Vaillant/dp/0674004140">Anticipation</a>”(pages 114-116) is a factor that leads to a better life. Anticipation is looking at a wide range of risks and benefits to prepare for most problems that might come up and planning ahead to minimize the impact of those risks.</p>
<p>Yet, anticipation can go too far. One form of that is called “hyper-vigilance”, and it can be very damaging. It is a known aspect of post-traumatic stress disorder.</p>
<p>A major aspect of hyper-vigilance is an extreme form of anticipation. People who have experienced intense trauma, such as multiple military deployments, are often so vigilant that even a few hours of sleep can terrify them because they cannot be vigilant when they are asleep.</p>
<p>So, pushing anticipation too far is a serious problem but is extra optimism also a problem?</p>
<p>A major barrier to thinking about such issues is the tendency for psychologists and self-help gurus to break things down into “black or white” categories.  For example, “optimism and positivity are good”, but “wariness and pessimism are bad”.</p>
<p><a href="/2014/04/30/stop-doing-things-that-make-you-more-vulnerable-and-less-resilient/?#comment-18752">Christine Olmstead’s comments</a> on yin and yang drew our attention to a Buddhist view that too much Yin can become Yang. If you are not familiar with the contrast between Yin and Yang, click <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ezmR9Attpyc">here</a> for a quick explanation.</p>
<p>This Buddhist view is consistent with that of Aristotle, who argued that vice results when a virtue is overdone or underdone.</p>
<p>Optimism, when taken too far, may take the form of having unrealistic expectations or even of delusional grandiosity or mania.</p>
<p>What we think works is optimism <strong><em>tempered by</em></strong> anticipation. That means looking on the bright side of things while also adjusting your expectations by carefully monitoring the situation you are in, and, in particular, balancing the payoffs you can get from your choices against the losses that may be entailed when you act on them.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F05%2F27%2Flooking-at-the-bright-side-of-situations-versus-endless-looking-for-threats%2F&amp;linkname=Looking%20at%20the%20bright%20side%20of%20situations%20versus%20endless%20looking%20for%20threats.%20%20%20" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Can Foreseeing a Dark Future Result in Less Disability and Lower Likelihood of Death?</title>
		<link>/2013/03/07/can-foreseeing-a-dark-future-result-in-less-disability-and-lower-likelihood-of-death/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2013 18:16:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Harvard Grant Study]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1334</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[About a week ago, Debbie came back from her morning run and said she heard on the radio that a study had been published supporting the idea that pessimism is more conducive to physical health than optimism. She went on &#8230; <a href="/2013/03/07/can-foreseeing-a-dark-future-result-in-less-disability-and-lower-likelihood-of-death/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>About a week ago, Debbie came back from her morning run and said she heard on the radio that a study had been published supporting the idea that pessimism is more conducive to physical health than optimism.</p>
<p>She went on to say that, based on the description of what was being called “pessimism”, it struck her as “anticipation”, which is a well-known successful way of coping with life. Anticipation means looking ahead to the future so that you can avoid being blind-sided by events.</p>
<p>There is abundant research showing that optimism is much more helpful than pessimism, e.g. this article. If there are circumstances in which pessimism beats optimism, we need to know about them.</p>
<p>In this post we will tell you about the results of our search for the details of this study and our interpretation of the results.</p>
<p><span id="more-1334"></span></p>
<p>Please be patient; it will take a few paragraphs to explain how the study was done.</p>
<p>It was done on a representative sample of 10,000 Germans. This means that they had an unusually large sample and respondents were selected in a pattern that matched the population of their country. Participants were tested and retested for eleven years. Most studies are one-shot deals, so duration of the study is a plus.</p>
<p>They were asked at the beginning of the study and in each subsequent year to rate their current quality of life, and to predict the quality of life they expected five years in the future.</p>
<p>If they predicted less life satisfaction than actually occurred, they were categorized as pessimistic (a pretty good common sense measure of optimism versus pessimism).</p>
<p>If their actual life satisfaction was worse than they had predicted, they were deemed optimistic; their expectations were more positive than what really happened. If they accurately predicted their future life satisfaction, they were deemed realistic.</p>
<p>The study divided participants in age categories ranging from Young adults (18-39 years), Middle-aged adults (40-64 years), and Older adults (65+ years).</p>
<p>Their outcome measures, i.e. what the study sought to predict, was disability or death.</p>
<p>They found that “Older adults” who underestimated how satisfying their future lives would be had less disability or death than those who were optimistic or realistic in their predictions. However, this worked only for the older adults, and the people rated as pessimistic were only 2 to 3 percent less likely to be disabled or dead than realists or optimists. In addition, the older adult sample included 856 people, whereas the other age groups each included 3 to 4 thousand.</p>
<p>Conclusion</p>
<p>This study had an unusual measure of optimism versus pessimism. A much more tested one, which is a very good predictor of future health can be found here. It is free, and you can take it and score it yourself.</p>
<p>The years from 65 up are a period of rapid change, much like the years from birth to young adulthood. Older people routinely have parents, friends, relatives, etc. they have seen develop various illnesses and losing a range of capacities they once had, and also dying. A common lament of older people is that so many, or even all, of their friends have died. And many worry about observed loss of various cognitive function, e.g. “a senior moment”.</p>
<p>An older adult who is alert is likely to realize what is in their future, and prepare for it. That is anticipation. I think Debbie had it right.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F03%2F07%2Fcan-foreseeing-a-dark-future-result-in-less-disability-and-lower-likelihood-of-death%2F&amp;linkname=Can%20Foreseeing%20a%20Dark%20Future%20Result%20in%20Less%20Disability%20and%20Lower%20Likelihood%20of%20Death%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Some Keys to a Long and Happy Life: Intimacy with Others, a Positive Focus and Goal-Directed Persistence.</title>
		<link>/2012/12/11/some-keys-to-a-long-and-happy-life-intimacy-with-others-a-positive-focus-and-goal-directed-persistence/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 11 Dec 2012 22:31:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Harvard Grant Study]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1291</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[David Brooks of the New York Times recently wrote a column triggered by the publication of George Vaillant’s book, “Triumphs of Experience”. The book discusses the most recent information gleaned from the Harvard Grant Study, a study of what leads &#8230; <a href="/2012/12/11/some-keys-to-a-long-and-happy-life-intimacy-with-others-a-positive-focus-and-goal-directed-persistence/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>David Brooks of the New York Times recently wrote a <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/11/06/opinion/brooks-the-heart-grows-smarter.html">column</a> triggered by the publication of George Vaillant’s book, “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Triumphs-Experience-Harvard-Grant-Study/dp/0674059824/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1355246530&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=vaillant+george">Triumphs of Experience</a>”. The book discusses the most recent information gleaned from the Harvard Grant Study, a study of what leads to a happy, productive, successful life. The investigators have closely followed Harvard undergraduates for 75 years.</p>
<p>The study could not possibly meet the ideal standards of controlled research, but it is about as good as we are likely to get. Each person was studied in much greater detail and over many more years than in most studies.</p>
<p>We discussed aspects of the study in several previous posts. <a href="/2011/01/27/through-adversity-to-the-stars/?#more-555">This one</a> includes a brief outline of characteristics that led to success in love and work, as summarized in Vailiant’s 1977 book “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/s/ref=nb_sb_ss_i_1_14?url=search-alias%3Dstripbooks&amp;field-keywords=adaptation+to+life+vaillant&amp;sprefix=adaptation+to+%2Cstripbooks%2C349">Adaptation to Life</a>”. This information remains very useful.</p>
<p>So here we are, clearly at the end game of the participants’ lives. The findings will probably be the last clues we get from the Harvard study on how to live our lives well.</p>
<p><span id="more-1291"></span></p>
<h2>Relationships Come First</h2>
<p>According to Brooks, the results show that <strong><em>we should give significant priority to fostering our relationships to others</em></strong>.</p>
<p>At the beginning of the study, the investigators expected that individual and even physical characteristics of the participants would determine how they did in life, but that is not the way it looks after collecting 75 years of data.</p>
<p>This is not a finding that surprises those of us who have been studying ways for people to live better, healthier, and longer lives.</p>
<p>I remember, decades ago, reading papers on the great importance of “social support” to living the good life. It surprised and struck me to learn that my friends were more than people I liked, enjoyed, trusted, etc. They were also my lifelines to a better, healthier, and longer life. Keep in mind that yours probably are too.</p>
<h2>Should We Focus on What Goes Right or What Goes Wrong?</h2>
<p>Another principle Brooks gleaned from the book is that <strong><em>“What goes right is more important than what goes wrong.”</em></strong></p>
<p>Most of us have been taught to work hard to overcome our weaknesses, but it may well be that it is better to concentrate more on building our strengths. There is a very useful book, “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/s/ref=nb_sb_ss_i_0_6?url=search-alias%3Dstripbooks&amp;field-keywords=soar+with+your+strengths&amp;sprefix=soar+w%2Cstripbooks%2C358">Soar with Your Strengths</a>”, that makes this point in detail.</p>
<p>Sure, we have to keep our weaknesses from undermining what is best about us. But we can just keep our weaknesses under control and then concentrate on giving our talents the concentrated attention they deserve.</p>
<p>Actually, “What goes right is more important than what goes wrong” is a core principle for those of us who focus on building resilience.</p>
<h2>What is Most Important? I.Q.? Physique?</h2>
<p>As Brooks says <strong><em>“In case after case the magic formula is capacity for intimacy combined with persistence, discipline, order and dependability.”</em></strong>  The terms “persistence, discipline, order and dependability” are a very good approximation to how we might describe a major aspect of the most powerful factor in our analysis of resilience. It is very closely linked to optimism, hope and positivity.</p>
<h2>Do We Have Time Left to Change?</h2>
<p>A final observation is that <strong><em>“You can teach an old dog new tricks.”</em></strong> The men kept changing throughout their lives.</p>
<p>This observation adds an important acknowledgement that, no matter how much you may have failed to live the good life in the past, it is not too late to do better in the remaining time.</p>
<p>There is an ancient Greek saying that no one’s life can be deemed happy until they are dead. That is an unnecessarily negative way to frame it, and we could just as well say that as long as we are alive, there is time for us to shift in ways that make our lives worthwhile, happy and meaningful</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=&amp;linkname=Some%20Keys%20to%20a%20Long%20and%20Happy%20Life%3A%20Intimacy%20with%20Others%2C%20a%20Positive%20Focus%20and%20Goal-Directed%20Persistence." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Here we go again! Is positivity really bad for you?</title>
		<link>/2012/08/23/here-we-go-again-is-positivity-really-bad-for-you/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 23 Aug 2012 03:08:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Harvard Grant Study]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1120</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In today’s post we will discuss a recent article, , “The Power of Negative Thinking”, published in the New York Times on August 4th. It would be reasonable to expect that anything that appears in the NYT is well-vetted, but &#8230; <a href="/2012/08/23/here-we-go-again-is-positivity-really-bad-for-you/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In today’s post we will discuss a recent article, , “The Power of Negative Thinking”, published in the New York Times on August 4th.</p>
<p>It would be reasonable to expect that anything that appears in the NYT is well-vetted, but you shouldn’t count on that. We read it regularly, and it often publishes articles that help us to think of timely new posts. Sometimes, though, they publish articles that just are not up to snuff.</p>
<p>The article, by Oliver Burkeman, begins by describing an event in which several people, apparently guided by the motivational speaker, Tony Robbins, attempted to walk barefoot over hot, burning coals. Twenty one of them had to be treated for burns. No big surprise for us.</p>
<p>Burkeman points out that physics tells us that “with quick, light steps, you’ll usually be fine”.  He goes on from that “lesson in physics” to turn the event into evidence against positivity.<span id="more-1120"></span></p>
<p>Well, there is overwhelming evidence that positivity helps us to flourish in life. With positivity we recover more quickly from surgery, perform better at work and in sports, are more successful in relationships, live longer, etc.</p>
<p>One would think that the “flagship” of newspapers in this country would require of its authors an awareness of at least a lot of this evidence, but apparently it does not. If you want to challenge the idea that positivity is good for people, why not include the body of serious research that supports this idea?</p>
<p>So, our first point is that this article shows no evidence of the author’s having reviewed the vetted, published literature on positivity and its outcomes.</p>
<p>Mr. Burkeman cites an article by Gabriele Oettingen, who is a real scientist, showing that people who were experimentally water-deprived and asked to picture a refreshing glass of water experienced a marked decline of energy levels compared to those who engaged in negative or neutral fantasies.</p>
<p>Anyone who has kept up with Dr. Oettingen’s research will understand that most of her work shows how effective positive imagining is when we contrast our future selves with and without taking constructive action designed for improvement. We routinely suggest this method to people who attend our workshops.</p>
<p>The body of Oettingen’s work demonstrates the effectiveness of positivity, not its ineffectiveness. It also points out important <span style="text-decoration: underline;">nuances</span> about how we can gain from positivity. So a second point is that the article has taken work out of context in a way that conceals the work&#8217;s overall significance. The nuances of positivity are missing.</p>
<p>Also the article lacks clarity about the definition of positivity. Living in a fantasy world is not the same as cultivating a life of positivity. It has long been known that mere fantasy is not likely to lead to success. George Vaillant in his <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Adaptation-Life-George-E-Vaillant/dp/0674004140">book on the Harvard Grant Study</a>, provides compelling evidence of that. Things like substituting fantasy for taking action to improve our lives and living in denial of the downside of our choices are not what research on positivity represents. Denial and fantasy have long been viewed as <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Defence_mechanism#Level_1_-_Pathological">immature or even pathological defense mechanism</a>, i.e. ways of fending off urges that are in conflict with our sense of self. Vaillant’s work shows that fantasy and denial are maladaptive.</p>
<p>Space limitations do not permit a more thorough analysis of the misconceptions in Burkeman’s article, but one, last point is that the author seems to assume that the cultivation of positivity entails the absence of negativity. Anyone who has read our last few posts will know that current evidence indicates that the needed ratio of positivity to negativity is around 3 positives to 1 negative, not 3 versus zero negatives.</p>
<p>Burkeman also cites Barbara Enrenreich’s grand rejection of positivity as authoritative. We have dealt with that in a <a href="/2010/12/18/is-optimism-really-toxic-5/">previous post</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Through Adversity to the Stars</title>
		<link>/2011/01/27/through-adversity-to-the-stars/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 27 Jan 2011 16:10:33 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Harvard Grant Study]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sense of Coherence]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=555</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The title of this post (in Latin) is cut in stone on the entryway to the gym at the University where I spent the great bulk of my working life. Nietzsche said something very similar, “Whatever does not kill me &#8230; <a href="/2011/01/27/through-adversity-to-the-stars/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The title of this post (in Latin) is cut in stone on the entryway to the gym at the University where I spent the great bulk of my working life. Nietzsche said something very similar, “Whatever does not kill me makes me stronger”. Statements like these are much contested on the Internet; taken too literally they are dubious at best.  However, I think we should lighten up and understand they are part poetry and part wisdom.</p>
<p>The quotations point toward an important question. <em>Can going through adversity actually improve your ability to pull through distressing experiences?</em> The New York Times recently published an <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/01/04/health/04mind.html">article</a> describing research on close to 2000 people who were asked to indicate all of the upsetting life events they had experienced before entering the study and any new ones that occurred along the way. Examples of such events included divorce, the death of a friend or parent, a serious illness, and being in a natural disaster.</p>
<p>The mental well-being of the participants was monitored over several years. The mental well-being measures were compared for those who reported no such life events, those who reported 2 to 6 such events, and those who presented 7 or more.</p>
<p>Those who reported no events were not highest in mental well-being. In fact, their well-being was like that of participants who reported 12 or more adverse events. Intermediate levels of adversity were associated with the greatest well-being.</p>
<p>The NYT article goes on to make two points: 1. We cannot accurately predict who will emerge from adversity well or even stronger and 2. It may be that dealing with adversity is important because it provides opportunities to hone skills for dealing with challenging situations.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, the first point is not quite accurate and the second, though sensible, is mere speculation. The main thrust of this post is to object to the first point.</p>
<p>For a long time we could only speculate about which qualities enabled some people to go through hellish challenges and come out of them healthy, happy, and successful. But there is now a well-developed science of resilience.</p>
<p>I will briefly discuss two examples, but there are many:</p>
<p><span id="more-555"></span></p>
<ol>
<li>George Vaillant summarized      the results of a  <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2009/06/what-makes-us-happy/7439/">major      study over the lifespan of Harvard Students</a>. The students were studied      from their undergraduate years into old age, and copious information      collected on how they coped with life and on how successful their lives      had been. Success in life was defined as the ability to love and to work.      In other words, could they form good, solid relationships and were they      successful in their work? Good outcomes depended on the following:</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Using humor to deal with adversity.</li>
<li>Facing reality, but also having the ability to put challenges aside when nothing more can be done about them.</li>
<li>Being able to look ahead and notice what might cause you trouble later, and to take action to minimize the distress that might result.</li>
<li>Taking the needs of others seriously and including them in the orb of people whose needs are important to you.</li>
<li>Finding socially constructive ways to give expression to your deep needs, e.g. putting aggression into sport.</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salutogenesis">Aaron Antonosky</a> observed      that holocaust survivors commonly have a very hard time dealing with      challenges later in life, e.g. menopause. However, many survivors emerged      as outstandingly resilient people. He studied women who were survivors and      found that an orientation to life he called “Sense of Coherence”      characterized these remarkably resilient survivors.</li>
</ol>
<p>It’s true that we cannot predict how an individual will react at a given time. Even predictions in the “hard” sciences are generally about averages, not about individuals. Researchers have discovered many characteristics that make it more likely, on average, that someone will emerge from a difficult situation intact and maybe even stronger.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2011%2F01%2F27%2Fthrough-adversity-to-the-stars%2F&amp;linkname=Through%20Adversity%20to%20the%20Stars" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
