<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Meditation &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/meditation/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The Powers of the Mind 1</title>
		<link>/2016/06/01/the-powers-of-the-mind-1/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2016 18:53:11 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2082</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[There is a graph that has stayed alive in Jerry&#8217;s mind for decades. It was in a study designed to see what happens if a person is given gradual increases in the dosage of isoproterenol, a drug that imitates adrenaline, &#8230; <a href="/2016/06/01/the-powers-of-the-mind-1/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There is a graph that has stayed alive in Jerry&#8217;s mind for decades. It was in a study designed to see what happens if a person is given gradual increases in the dosage of isoproterenol, a drug that imitates adrenaline, the familiar &#8220;fight or flight&#8221; hormone. It is used primarily to deal with abnormally  slow and weak heartbeat  ( bradycardia), and heart block.</p>
<p>(Heart Block is an abnormal heart rhythm in which the heart beats too slowly. In this condition, the electrical signals that tell the heart to contract are blocked between the heart&#8217;s upper and lower chambers.)</p>
<p>The study appears to have been a routine one of the &#8220;dose-response curve&#8221;, to observe changes in heart rate as the dosage of the drug was gradually increased. Isoproterenol works by making changes in the junctions between the nervous system  and the heart muscle.</p>
<p>Not surprisingly, heart rate increased with each increment of the drug dosage, but there was one person whose heart followed the expected pattern as the dose was increased from zero to .1 on to .5 micrograms, but then began slowing down as the dose continued to be increased to 1.0, 2.0, and on to 4.0 micrograms.</p>
<p>The heart rate of the unusual person went from around 68 beats per minute (bpm) before any drug was given, to above 80 bpm at a dosage but then went down steadily to end up at around 53 bpm when the drug was at its top level. At this top dosage the other participants had a heart rate around 90 bpm.</p>
<p>What was going on? When the researchers asked the outlier that question, she said she had become bored and started meditating just before bher heart rate slowed down.</p>
<p>On occasion, there are reports of remarkable bodily control on the part of people who have devoted a great deal of their lives engaged in training that results in unusual control of mind over body. For example a Yogi, the Swami Rama was studied at the Menninger Clinic, and was able to make one part of his hand warm up while cooling a nearby part. He also showed that he could stop his heart from pumping while connected to an electronic device that measured his physiological reactions. This device would make it impossible to do any tricks to give an unreal impression of  bodily control.</p>
<p>If you want more detail on Swami Rama, the person who acted as his personal assistant in the  United States wrote a book, &#8220;Swami&#8221;, about him. It appears to be out of print, but inexpensive copies are available at Abebooks.com.</p>
<p>A lesson that we can take from such accomplishments is that regular practice of effective procedures such as meditation  can lead to our developing skills that enable us to gain remarkable control over our minds and bodies.</p>
<p>The woman who lowered her heart rate was able to challenge and defeat the biological system that underlies fight or flight. It is a system that also underlies &#8220;losing one&#8217;s temper&#8221; and even violent acts under some circumstances. It also underlies such things as stage fright, and a score of other things that we might want to bring under our control.</p>
<p>It is interesting to know that the woman who controlled her heart was self- trained. It is usually best to have a trainer, but some people can do well even on their own. The take-home message is that self-control is probably within your reach. The key is &#8220;practice, practice, practice&#8221;.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Loving Kindness Meditation: A Practice That May Increase Your Altruism</title>
		<link>/2016/05/08/loving-kindness-meditation-a-practice-that-may-increase-your-altruism/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2016 18:50:05 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Meditation]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2069</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In our previous post, which was about the Harvard Grant Study, we mentioned that altruism was one of a handful of characteristics associated with good a successful life. We didn&#8217;t do much with the topic until Debbie wrote a post &#8230; <a href="/2016/05/08/loving-kindness-meditation-a-practice-that-may-increase-your-altruism/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In our previous post, which was about the Harvard Grant Study, we mentioned that altruism was one of a handful of characteristics associated with good a successful life. We didn&#8217;t do much with the topic until Debbie wrote a post on her own experience with altruism, which came to the front and grew while taking care of her mother, who  has Alzheimer&#8217;s disease.</p>
<p>Looking back at the book written by George Vaillant on the Harvard Grant Study, we saw that he also had elaborated very little on altruism. He had a few comments on it, but nothing like the space given to other resilience-promoting characteristics.</p>
<p>Both of us thought of giving an account of &#8220;Loving Kindness&#8221; practice, since a major goal of that kind of meditation is to induce people to love themselves and also to love others.  There is reason to see Loving Kindness Meditation as a way to increase your altruism. This suggests that it might be a manifestation of altruism that has been evaluated with fairly well-controlled research.</p>
<p>What You Can Gain by Practicing Loving Kindness</p>
<p>Here is a short list of examples of benefits of training in Loving Kindness:</p>
<p>1. Reduction of chronic low <a href="http://yogaforseniors.com/we-content/uploads/2013/11/lovingkindnessforchronicpain.pdf" target="_blank">back pain </a>and accompanying irritability.<br />
2. Lengthening of telomeres, which indicates less biological aging.<br />
3. Reduction of self-criticism.<br />
4. More positive feelings and fewer negative ones<br />
5. Greater improvements than training to be more compassionate.<br />
6. Increases in social connectedness.<br />
7. Relief from symptoms of Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD).</p>
<p>How To Do Loving Kindness Meditation</p>
<p>We did a search on Google Scholar and found that there have been many studies on loving kindness, and there was a consistent pattern of Loving Kindness Meditation leading to good results, often better than alternatives.</p>
<p>Our search showed that there are many variations on how to practice this kind of meditation. This suggests that you can be somewhat flexible in the small details of how you choose to do it.</p>
<p>Begin by scanning your body and letting go of any tension you experience. Continuing to breathe in and out and use either one of these traditional phrases or ones you choose yourself. Say or think them several times.</p>
<p>May I be free from inner and outer harm and danger. May I be safe and protected.</p>
<p>May I be free of mental suffering.</p>
<p>May I be happy.</p>
<p>May I be healthy and strong.</p>
<p>May I be able to live in this world happily, peacefully, joyfully, with ease.</p>
<p>Now pick someone who you find easy to apply these phrases to and repeat the exercise.</p>
<p>Next apply them to a neutral person, someone you neither like nor dislike, and then move on to someone you don&#8217;t particularly like and have hostile feelings toward.</p>
<p>Take your time do not try to rush your mind and heart.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Distractions Play a Central Role in Producing the Benefits of Meditation</title>
		<link>/2015/05/07/distractions-play-a-central-role-in-producing-the-benefits-of-meditation/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2015 15:30:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1884</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[When you meditate, your experiences fall into two categories : 1. The object on which you intend to focus, and 2. Distractions. Here we want to focus on distractions, particularly on where they come from and what you should do &#8230; <a href="/2015/05/07/distractions-play-a-central-role-in-producing-the-benefits-of-meditation/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When you meditate, your experiences fall into two categories : 1. The object on which you intend to focus, and 2. Distractions.<br />
Here we want to focus on distractions, particularly on where they come from and what you should do with them. </p>
<p>At first we may be inclined to say that distractions are mere chaos of the mind. When we call them “chatter” we come close to implying that view of them.If you take a step back and observe distractions, you can see that they are meaningful. In our ordinary, non-meditative life, they are calls to needed actions, attempts to solve problems that we face, strategies for fending off painful thoughts, etc.</p>
<p>During meditation, they are not allowed to take center stage.We keep our attention on the object of our meditation by gently turning away from the distractions. We do not wage an internal war against them. Instead we take a calm, passive attitude toward them, and let the distractions pass through, neither grasping them nor fighting them off.</p>
<p>What happens as you get better and better at letting thoughts that have usually driven you to action go unappeased is that the distraction loses its power over you, and you start remaining calm and centered instead of jumping to action.<br />
You can see why meditation can make you calm, relaxed, and in control of your own actions.</p>
<h2>Autogenic Discharge</h2>
<p>One particular type of distraction calls for special attention. We call it “discharge”, a term taken from Autogenic Training, which can be observed over a wide range of techniques that involve calming the mind and body. For example, in Zen meditation it is called “<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Makyo">Makyo</a>”, and Zen masters inquire about it regularly with their students.</p>
<p>These discharges may include a wide range of symptoms such as dizziness, anxiety, headache, nausea, twitching, disturbing images, crying etc. In some ways their texture is similar to that of experiences people may have just before they go to sleep.</p>
<p>The best thing to do when you have these experiences is to gently turn your attention back to the object of your meditation. Generally, such experiences are self-limiting. If you stay with your meditative focus, they will fade away.</p>
<p>However, if they feel unbearably disturbing, stop meditating. It’s best not to try toughing out the experience.</p>
<p>A number of adjustments can be made in your meditation routine in order to minimize the occurrence of such highly disturbing experiences.<span id="more-1884"></span></p>
<p>1. Reduce the length and/or the frequency of your sessions. Shorter methods tend to produce fewer discharges, as does reducing the frequency of sessions.</p>
<p>2. Shift from a highly passive method to one that is more active. For example, a relaxation procedure that has you tense and relax body parts, attending to the feelings of tension and relaxation is less passive than simply observing your breath.</p>
<p>3. Be sure that the context in which you are doing the work makes you feel safe. Your view of your setting has a powerful effect on how you interpret your experiences. To illustrate, there are a number of psychological studies showing that people given a drug that speeds the heart can produce reactions as diverse as increasing anger and increasing laughter. The situation determines the meaning of the state of arousal.</p>
<p>Finally, we pointed out earlier that each time meditators minimize their reactions to distractions, gently turning their attention back to the object of their meditation, the distractions lose more and more of their power to control you. For that reason the distractions are actually a very important part of the meditation.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2015%2F05%2F07%2Fdistractions-play-a-central-role-in-producing-the-benefits-of-meditation%2F&amp;linkname=Distractions%20Play%20a%20Central%20Role%20in%20Producing%20the%20Benefits%20of%20Meditation" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Clearing the Mind through Meditation</title>
		<link>/2015/04/14/clearing-the-mind-through-meditation/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 Apr 2015 16:22:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Understanding]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1874</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In this post we want to discuss mental changes that occur while and after meditation. The type of meditation you do is a factor in determining what happens, but there are many commonalities shared by various types of meditation. Relaxation &#8230; <a href="/2015/04/14/clearing-the-mind-through-meditation/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this post we want to discuss mental changes that occur while and after meditation.</p>
<p>The type of meditation you do is a factor in determining what happens, but there are many commonalities shared by various types of meditation. Relaxation of mind and body are very basic ones. We discussed this relaxation of mind and body in our previous post, and we followed Herbert Benson’s lead in dubbing it “the relaxation response”.</p>
<p>Since Benson is a cardiologist, it should not be a surprise that he focused on physiological reactions relevant to how the heart and blood vessels react. Obviously these changes are important for all of us. But there are also important changes in the way our <strong><em>minds</em></strong> function when we meditate. And these changes impact how we view the world and how we feel and behave.</p>
<p>A very valuable change has to do with getting control of the constant chattering that goes on in our minds.</p>
<p>Limiting the chatter/background noise is essential to developing a mind clear enough to be able to make our perception of reality clear. In Yoga it is seen as a form of enlightenment and in the more scientific framework of Information Theory it is a matter of reducing our mental “noise” level enough to tell whether an input contains something meaningful, a “signal”, or is merely noise.</p>
<p>We see the ancient views from Yoga and the modern views from information theory as expressing basically the same concepts, though within different frameworks.</p>
<p>One of the classic accounts of meditation and its consequences is in the Yoga Sutras of Patanjali. The first line of the Yoga Sutras says that “Even-mindedness is Yoga”.  In this view, the mind can be likened to a pond that responds with waves when something is dropped into it. If the pond is calm, without waves, even dropping a small pebble into it will result in easily noted waves.</p>
<p>In the middle of a storm, the impact of that same pebble may be impossible to detect.</p>
<p>With meditation, our minds have increased clarity and a wider awareness than they had prior to meditating. This clarity and extensiveness of awareness goes beyond mere facts. After meditation, things you have passed by many times with little reaction may suddenly reveal their beauty and trigger a sense of awe in you.  So meditation also clarifies a more emotional aspect of what we experience.</p>
<p>Until the 1960s, Western science paid little attention to claims that healthy changes could result from meditation. Such claims were generally ignored or seen as hokum. In the early 1960s this easy dismissal was called into question, and research began to be published that confirmed some of the claims.</p>
<p>Interesting early work by a psychiatrist, <a href="http://www.cuke.com/Cucumber%20Project/interviews/deikman.html">Arthur Deikman</a>, made a start in recognizing that our perceptions of many aspects of reality and our reactions to that reality are intensified and improved by meditation. He did a small study in which he got various colleagues to meditate on an ordinary blue vase. He simply asked the colleagues to sit in a room and keep their attention on the vase, putting aside distractions that came to mind.</p>
<p>Participants reported a wide range of reactions. Here is an illustration from an <a href="http://www.deikman.com/experimental.html">article written by Deikman</a> describing a shift in perception of the vase that occurred quite generally:</p>
<p><em>   Sooner or later they experienced a shift to a deeper and more intense blue. &#8220;More vivid&#8221;   was a phrase they used frequently. Ss experienced the vase as becoming brighter while everything in their visual field became quite dark and indistinct. The adjective &#8220;luminous&#8221; was often applied to the vase, as if it were a source of light. For example, subject B, Session #6, &#8220;The vase was a hell of a lot bluer this time than it has been before . . . it was darker and more luminous at the same time.&#8221;</em></p>
<p>(When Deikman wrote this article, the term “Subject” or “S” was in general use when referring to volunteer participants in psychological experiments.)</p>
<p>If you do a search in Google Scholar for research on meditation today, you will find many confirmations of beneficial effects of meditation.</p>
<p>We will continue discussing changes due to meditation in our next post.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2015%2F04%2F14%2Fclearing-the-mind-through-meditation%2F&amp;linkname=Clearing%20the%20Mind%20through%20Meditation" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why Not Put Meditation Through the Ultimate Test? Try It Out!</title>
		<link>/2015/03/23/why-not-put-meditation-through-the-ultimate-test-try-it-out/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 18:23:36 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Mantra Meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mindfulness]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1859</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Prior to the 1960s claims about psychological and, especially physical improvements from mind training practices, got about as much serious attention as claims that the earth is actually flat. A variety of influences encouraged those who are scientifically oriented to &#8230; <a href="/2015/03/23/why-not-put-meditation-through-the-ultimate-test-try-it-out/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Prior to the 1960s claims about psychological and, especially physical improvements from mind training practices, got about as much serious attention as claims that the earth is actually flat.</p>
<p>A variety of influences encouraged those who are scientifically oriented to take a second look at these techniques. A very significant shift in readiness to take them seriously resulted from the work of Herbert Benson, a senior cardiologist at Harvard’s Medical School.</p>
<p>His work was presumably stimulated by popular demand, stemming from such things as the wildly popular Beatles’ taking up “Transcendental Meditation”, a very well packaged program centered on an ancient method of “Mantra Meditation”.</p>
<p>In a nutshell, Benson confirmed that mantra meditation induced something he called the “relaxation response”. This was a clear and simple label for a complex pattern of physiological replenishment responses along with corollary psychological feelings of calm and relaxation.</p>
<p>The mind-body pattern was familiar to the few people who understood how our nervous systems respond when we are distressed versus when we are comfortable and calm. The pattern was based on activity in a number of neural systems that can only be understood after much study of neurophysiology.</p>
<p>So his simply calling their effects as “the relaxation response” was pure genius. It focuses on a central benefit of controlling those neurophysiological and corollary psychological reactions without getting bogged down in technical details a person doesn’t need to know in order to get the systems under control.</p>
<p>(What is Mantra Meditation, and how can you learn how to do it? To get our answers to these questions, click <a href="/2014/01/15/a-simple-way-to-sooth-and-comfort-yourself/">here</a>).</p>
<p>There are many types of meditation, and, in our experience, which one is seen as best seems to depend as much on the person trying to use it as on the meditation method itself.</p>
<p>Though mantra meditation is widely used, the current star of the show in our part of the world is mindfulness meditation. We have described how to engage in this practice <a href="/2011/03/02/basic-mindfulness-technique/">here</a>. The method we describe is an ancient one which has shown its usefulness over thousands of years.</p>
<p>We did a Google search to find out how well the effectiveness of mindfulness is supported by good research. For this kind of search, we use Google Scholar, which emphasizes research that has been reported in journals that are attentive to scientific standards of evidence. If you do an ordinary search, you may get as many sales pitches as scientific findings.</p>
<p><span id="more-1859"></span></p>
<p>This is a quick summary of what we found:</p>
<ul>
<li>Research is generally based on meditation techniques that are at quite a distance from traditional mindfulness meditation, typically blended with various procedures that are used in cognitive behavior therapy.</li>
<li>Standards of research design are not great, but they tend to support the idea that this meditation, on average, has some important positive effects in helping people deal with a wide range of different challenges.</li>
<li>A good way to describe this state of affairs is to say that mindfulness is <strong><em>robust in its positive effects</em></strong>. This seems to be about as much as we can expect in a world that is not likely to offer ideal levels of precision.</li>
</ul>
<p>Unless your goal is to publish your findings, the ultimate test of a technique is to find out whether it helps <strong><em>you</em></strong> with <strong><em>your</em></strong> current standards of what is worth the effort. Only you can be the judge of that, once you try it out.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=&amp;linkname=" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
