<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Resilience Research &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/resilience-research/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Yoga or Resilience Training: Do We Have to Choose?</title>
		<link>/2015/05/28/yoga-or-resilience-training-do-we-have-to-choose/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2015 03:18:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1904</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[What are the main differences between yoga and resilience training? Would it be a good idea to do both, or are they a bad mix? Around a year ago Debbie asked for a Yoga class as her birthday present. It &#8230; <a href="/2015/05/28/yoga-or-resilience-training-do-we-have-to-choose/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What are the main differences between yoga and resilience training? Would it be a good idea to do both, or are they a bad mix?</p>
<p>Around a year ago Debbie asked for a Yoga class as her birthday present. It was a great suggestion, and Yoga has helped her to cope with a stage in her life in which she has agreed to take responsibility for decisions about health care for her mother. Yoga worked for her and continues to be an important part of her life.</p>
<p>More recently a longstanding friend of mine suggested that I enroll in a beginner’s course in Yoga, and Debbie also urged that I take the course. For many years, I have been dealing with severe, chronic pain due to an arthritic spine that creates impingements on my spinal cord that result in chronic pain and problems with controlling how I walk.</p>
<p>I had just finished a very successful series of Physical Therapy interventions, so was interested in retaining the gains I had made through various forms of stretching and balancing.</p>
<p>Why did Debbie and I both reach out for help from another system instead of relying on the resilience techniques we already knew? Abraham Lincoln summarized one of the major reasons in a widely used quote about lawyers: “He who represents himself has a fool for a client.”</p>
<p>It’s helpful to get training from someone other than yourself. Distance provides a useful perspective.</p>
<p>In addition to that, though resilience training and Yoga superficially seem to have little in common, they are really very much alike. Both approaches use a wide range of techniques that enable you to know yourself at a deeper level and to soothe and calm yourself.</p>
<p>Yoga, as it is typically practiced in the United States, emphasizes working on changes of the body, and most resilience programs emphasize changes at the level of mind.<br />
But change in the body results in change in the mind and change at the level of the mind results in change in the body.</p>
<p>For example, if you are getting agitated, slowing and deepening your breathing pattern tends to calm both your mind and your body.</p>
<p>Similarly, you can make yourself salivate by imagining sucking on a lemon and you can make your hands get warmer by imagining yourself at the beach lying on a big towel and picturing the sun warming your hands.</p>
<p>For quite a few years a significant body of research in scientific psychology has focused a lot of its efforts on conducting studies to determine whether ancient techniques work. For the most part, those techniques have passed the tests and been integrated into psychological methods of treatment.</p>
<p>So our view is that ancient disciplines from the Far East tend to fit comfortably into recent, science-based resilience programs.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2015%2F05%2F28%2Fyoga-or-resilience-training-do-we-have-to-choose%2F&amp;linkname=Yoga%20or%20Resilience%20Training%3A%20Do%20We%20Have%20to%20Choose%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Resilience and Grit</title>
		<link>/2014/09/08/resilience-and-grit/</link>
		<comments>/2014/09/08/resilience-and-grit/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2014 06:17:14 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Research]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1722</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This post was based on our reactions to a YouTube Ted Talk by Angela Duckworth on the topic of grit. It is best to take a look at it and then come back to our discussion. The key idea in &#8230; <a href="/2014/09/08/resilience-and-grit/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This post was based on our reactions to a YouTube <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H14bBuluwB8">Ted Talk by Angela Duckworth on the topic of grit</a>. It is best to take a look at it and then come back to our discussion.</p>
<p><iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/H14bBuluwB8" frameborder="0" width="560" height="315"></iframe></p>
<p>The key idea in Dr. Duckworth’s talk is that grit is more important than IQ in predicting academic success. It is also linked to other benefits such as being happier and more satisfied with your life. Anything that can make people more successful, happier, and more satisfied with their lives deserves attention.</p>
<p>Given the apparent benefits of grit, you may well want to know how much of it you have. You can find out your own level of grit by taking the grit test Dr. Duckworth developed. It is <a href="http://www.sas.upenn.edu/~duckwort/images/12-item%20Grit%20Scale.05312011.pdf">here</a>.</p>
<p>You might also want to <strong><em>increase</em></strong> your grit. So far, there does not seem to be a clear path to developing more grit. We suspect that a major part of the path lies in increasing your resilience.</p>
<p><span id="more-1722"></span></p>
<p>A core, maybe even <strong><em>the</em></strong> core of grit is perseverance. Dr. Duckworth uses a racing metaphor. People with grit lead life as a marathon, not as a sprint.</p>
<p>One of the most notable characteristics of resilient people is that they are optimistic. And one of the characteristics of optimists is their perseverance. In fact, the perseverance of optimists is a characteristic that can be a problem for them because they may not know when it is time to stop and change direction.</p>
<p>People doing research and developing theories on topics like grit and resilience seem to be inclined to view some characteristics as simply “good for you” and others as simply “bad for you”.</p>
<p>But most things are good or bad, depending on how far you push them.</p>
<p>If you are too much of a butterfly that flits from flower to flower, you are not being gritty. On the other hand, if you push grittiness too far, you are may well harm yourself.</p>
<p>A good example of carrying persistence too far is working <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-04-04/work-days-of-11-hours-boost-risk-for-heart-disease-study-says.html">too many hours</a>. Many people today think that pushing their bodies to greater and greater limits is healthy but they are wrong to see no limits to the amount of exertion that is healthy.  Older research consistently showed that extending physical work too long kills people and contemporary research is showing the same thing.</p>
<p>Can too much grit damage your health? It would seem to be likely, in light of what we pointed out above. Duckworth and Eskreis-Winkler have  pointed out that <a href="http://www.psychologicalscience.org/index.php/publications/observer/2013/april-13/true-grit.html?utm_source=socialmedia&amp;utm_medium=sociallinks&amp;utm_campaign=twitter">we need research on that topic</a>.</p>
<p>Grit is a pretty new focus of attention, and we see an increase of research on the topic. We need to keep an eye on that research. We are likely to learn more about how to build grit. Hopefully there will be research on the relationship between grit and optimism.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F09%2F08%2Fresilience-and-grit%2F&amp;linkname=Resilience%20and%20Grit" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2014/09/08/resilience-and-grit/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Your Stress Responses and the Wisdom of the Body</title>
		<link>/2013/04/10/your-stress-responses-and-the-wisdom-of-the-body/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2013 04:13:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Genes and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1348</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In our last post, we discussed genetic variations that result in our having either a “worrier” or a “warrior” brain. We also mentioned that worriers can handle stress effectively, even function at the level of Navy Seals, if they are &#8230; <a href="/2013/04/10/your-stress-responses-and-the-wisdom-of-the-body/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In our last post, we discussed genetic variations that result in our having either a “worrier” or a “warrior” brain. We also mentioned that worriers can handle stress effectively, even function at the level of Navy Seals, if they are properly trained. Sufficiently trained, worriers can deal with demanding situations as well as warriors.</p>
<p>What makes this possible? Despite the bodily stress reactions we have that are inborn, how we <strong><em>interpret</em></strong> those reactions can dramatically shift how we react.</p>
<p><span id="more-1348"></span></p>
<p>In the early 1960s, two psychologists, <a href="http://faculty.babson.edu/krollag/org_site/soc_psych/schachter_epineph.html">Stanley Schachter and Jerome Singer</a> showed that <strong><em>cueing</em></strong> people about how to view their experiences can dramatically shift how they actually react.</p>
<p>Their studies were complex, but, basically, they assessed how the effects of a drug that produced high arousal (standard pharmaceutical adrenalin) changed, depending on the context in which the drug was administered.</p>
<p>If people injected with pharmaceutical adrenalin, which produces a typical stress response with rapid heart rate, sweating, and so forth), were in a situation in which a stooge feigned anger, they were more likely to be angry. If the stooge feigned euphoria, they became more silly and playful.</p>
<p>Anything that changes how we view our bodily reactions has the power to determine whether we end up distressed and defeated or end up feeling euphoric, or heaven knows what else. The point is that the physiological reaction is not the boss. It has a vote, but it’s not the boss.</p>
<p>So if you have powerful feelings and symptoms when you face stress, you can still fall back on your thought patterns to use that power to support you.</p>
<p>Bodily responses to life’s demands commonly provide protection from threats. So getting rid of those reactions is not necessarily a good path to resilience. <a href="http://digitalcommons.unl.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1215&amp;context=psychfacpub">Important research</a> shows that those who are resilient have physiological responses to stress as intense as those who are less resilient.</p>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fight-or-flight_response">Walter Cannon</a>, the scientist who first identified the “fight or flight” stress response did so in a book he entitled “The Wisdom of the Body”.  Wisdom? Can it be that these hated feelings we try to fight off when taking a difficult test, walking on stage to give a speech, etc. are based on bodily “wisdom”?</p>
<p>For example, isn’t your heart pounding rapidly bad for you?</p>
<p>Commonly it is not. Your heart pounds when you exercise vigorously, have sex or ride on a rollercoaster, and we don’t think of that as bad for you. The heart’s reaction during positive states can actually be more intense than it is during negative ones.</p>
<p>It <strong><em>can</em></strong> be bad for you if you have serious heart disease, but that doesn’t mean it’s bad for most of us. Exercise that pushes the heart to be fast and effective is commonly recommended to make us healthier.</p>
<p>The physiological reactions themselves can change depending on how we interpret them. For example, when we interpret something as manageable, our heart’s efficiency tends to increase and our blood vessels relax. When we view them as a threat beyond our control, the opposite happens.</p>
<p>Harvard Professor Jeremy Jamieson and his colleagues have done valuable <a href="http://wendyberrymendes.com/cms/uploads/CDPS_reappraisal-1.pdf">research</a> confirming that how we appraise or interpret our bodily reactions to demanding situations can determine how well we perform under stress.</p>
<p>For example, in one study, in a high-stakes testing situation half of the test-takers were told before the test that stress reactions we have during important, difficult tests predict better, not worse performance. They were also told that they should not feel concerned about their body’s reactions, but instead should remind themselves that this arousal could be helping them do well.</p>
<p>The group taught to see stress reactions as beneficial scored 65 points higher than controls!</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=&amp;linkname=" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Priming the Brain: Is the Research Valid?</title>
		<link>/2012/11/02/priming-the-brain-is-the-research-valid/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Nov 2012 16:43:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Research]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1192</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[We just finished our workshop, “From Negativity and Self-Criticism to Positivity and Self-Compassion: A Women’s Workshop”. We both enjoyed the experience. It was a great group. We are minimizing emphasis on lectures (hard for me to do!), and focusing on &#8230; <a href="/2012/11/02/priming-the-brain-is-the-research-valid/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We just finished our workshop, “From Negativity and Self-Criticism to Positivity and Self-Compassion: A Women’s Workshop”. We both enjoyed the experience. It was a great group.</p>
<p>We are minimizing emphasis on lectures (hard for me to do!), and focusing on using videos and our own audios to let people experience directly what we might otherwise talk about.</p>
<p>One topic included ways in which experiences we may not pay much attention to can influence how we behave, think, and experience subsequent events. In particular we introduced the group to “Priming” and “Emotional Contagion”.</p>
<p>Wikipedia provides a good technical <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Priming_%28psychology%29">definition of priming</a>: Priming is a form of memory, technically called  <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Implicit_memory">implicit memory</a>. Think of “how you ride a bike”. You just do it, and your conscious account of it might result in a crash. That is the sense in which it is implicit.</p>
<p>With priming, exposure to one stimulus influences a response to a later stimulus and conscious awareness of that influence is irrelevant.</p>
<p>A good example of priming, which I cited during the workshop, is a study in which people who were exposed to words that primed them to think of old age, e.g. Florida, Social Security, and the like, led them to walk more slowly and with a postural stoop linked to stereotypes of old age.</p>
<p>There are many studies on priming that have yielded similar results. For example, one study reported that people who were given cold versus warm drinks to hold tended to react to people subsequently encountered as warmer or colder, depending on whether they had held the warm or cold drink.</p>
<p>This is a useful effect for those of us who want to function better in the world. It implies that arranging our environment the right way, even in ways that our conscious minds might rate as irrelevant, can make us function better.</p>
<p>We got this information from a very nice lecture by Shawn Achor which was used as part of “Pledge Week” on Public TeIevision. We should have done a careful review of the original research and any follow ups. Unfortunately we were working so hard on designing our workshop that we didn’t even think of the possibility that there might be something wrong with the research we were citing.</p>
<p>Well, it turns out that at least one follow-up study indicated that the results depended on what the experimenters <strong><em>expected</em></strong> to happen. <a href="http://blogs.discovermagazine.com/notrocketscience/2012/01/18/primed-by-expectations-%E2%80%93-why-a-classic-psychology-experiment-isn%E2%80%99t-what-it-seemed/">Here</a> is a very good account of the critical research.</p>
<p><span id="more-1192"></span></p>
<p>Now for me to miss that is pretty close to inexcusable. I have been ranting about the importance of controlling for “experimenter effects” for decades in <a href="http://www.alibris.com/search/books/isbn/9780030895388">books that I wrote</a>. It’s a topic that comes up on many Saturdays when I do my walks in the woods with a dear friend. We talk about his field, Political Science, and mine, which I think you know about.</p>
<p>What are experimenter effects? They are ways in which biases and expectations of experimenters can lead to the results they expect. This is not deliberate fraud, but “unconscious” influence.</p>
<p>As it happens, I had a close relationship with a person who, as an undergraduate taking a course in Experimental Psychology, was duped into believing she had been assigned a “dumb” rat to train in a “Skinner box”. The idea was to train the rats to respond appropriately by pressing a bar that could lead to rewards.</p>
<p>The rats were, in fact, randomly selected. There was no reason to think they were dumber or smarter than others. But half of them were tagged as dumb, and the other half didn’t get that negative stereotype.</p>
<p>I remember how annoyed my friend was at being stuck with a “dumb” rat- just couldn’t teach it anything! The rat behaved in accord with its stereotype as dumb.</p>
<p>Over and over I have complained to my hiking friend about how the importance of experimenter effects has been forgotten. Yet, in this case, I forgot about it.</p>
<p>Which is a good lesson in how easily even those of us who know better can be taken over by social influences.</p>
<p>I suppose the best I can say is “Watch out and stay critical” when you read about results of experiments. Probably a good rule is to try out any new ways for attaining your goals that are backed by credible research, give them a fair chance to succeed or fail, then decide whether the principles work for you.</p>
<p>Published research should be viewed with caution. There are many incentives to report interesting findings, and few incentives to rain on the parade.</p>
<p>A word of caution: the person who published the study now called into question is <a title="arguing back" href="http://hardsci.wordpress.com/2012/03/12/some-reflections-on-the-bargh-doyen-elderly-walking-priming-brouhaha/">arguing back</a>. Our warning does not assume that the original finding is wrong. We will stay alert and see how it comes out.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2012%2F11%2F02%2Fpriming-the-brain-is-the-research-valid%2F&amp;linkname=Priming%20the%20Brain%3A%20Is%20the%20Research%20Valid%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
