<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Deep Relaxation &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/deep-relaxation/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Surgical Preparation: Specific Details.</title>
		<link>/2016/09/14/surgical-preparation-specific-details/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Benefits of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2131</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Recently we have been writing posts about preparing patients for surgery. Benefits can be mental, but our focus has been on learning mind-focused ways to improve patient&#8217;s physical reactions during and after surgery. We found that many published studies indicate &#8230; <a href="/2016/09/14/surgical-preparation-specific-details/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Recently we have been writing posts about preparing patients for surgery. Benefits can be mental, but our focus has been on learning mind-focused ways to improve patient&#8217;s physical reactions during and after surgery.</p>
<p>We found that many published studies indicate that outcomes are significantly improved in patients who were given presurgical training. For example, patients lose remarkably less blood if they are taught how to move the blood away from the spine during the surgery and then have it return to the spine to facilitate healing after surgery.</p>
<p>At this point, many readers may be thinking that there is no way for the mind to move blood around in the body. Patients who are being trained tend to feel that way too.</p>
<p>An important step is to explain how that can happen. Scientifically designed studies are normally kept very simple, but in clinical practice the methods may be more complex. A common method used in research is pointing out that our minds often trigger movement of blood. Remind the trainee that most people blush when they are embarrassed. We also move blood to our genitals by having erotic fantasies. You can direct your blood to your hands by relaxing, suggesting that your blood is flowing down your arm into your hands, and picturing the suggested flow. This is not at all remarkable, the &#8220;fight or flight&#8221; reaction includes moving blood away from the periphery of your body. Relaxation inhibits the &#8220;fight or flight&#8221; reaction, so it makes blood flow to the hands.</p>
<p>There is much more evidence that the mind can control supposedly &#8220;involuntary&#8221; bodily reactions, but for this post we want to describe Debbie&#8217;s experiences with preparing patients to deal with upcoming surgery. Like most clinicians, she uses methods that go far beyond the simple methods assessed in published studies.</p>
<p>In her words:</p>
<p>&#8220;As a therapist I had remarkable success in assisting some of my patients to prepare for surgery or other medical procedures.</p>
<p>In therapy sessions, I begin by having the patient talk about the surgery and what the aim or primary goal is particularly from their perspective. We explore any feelings or concerns that they have about the surgery. What is their relationship with the medical people including the surgeon? Have they had surgery in the past and how did it go? Were there any complications? Have there previously been any poor outcomes.</p>
<p>The potential benefits of preparing psychologically in advance of the surgery are explained. I cite examples from published literature and describe my own experiences with other patients to explain how beneficial preparation can be. If for example the patient does not trust the medical field or has had bad experiences, we work to come to some sort of peace with it, enough that this does not transfer to the present situation. If they have had bad outcomes from surgery we explore this together to see if there are differences in the present situation.</p>
<p>We talk about mentally shifting to a place where the patient can see the medical team as being there to help them achieve their objectives.</p>
<p>We discuss how getting to a place where they are trusting of the medical provider makes it possible for their body to cooperate with the surgeon and not fight against her/him. It is understandable that at some level the body will protest being cut into and it is best to get the surgeon and patient working together, helping the body to relax.</p>
<p>The patient  tries to find out as much as possible about the surgery and what the procedure consists of, including a description of the steps along the way.</p>
<p>The patient  learns some form of relaxation procedure and oftentimes  is provided an audio to practice at home. In the counseling sessions I use the same relaxation procedure and while the patient is relaxed begin to guide them in imagining the surgery and positive outcomes. I provide some of the &#8220;script&#8221; but also encourage them to offer input and improve it.</p>
<p>I re-emphasize that the surgeon is here to help the patient and cooperating with him/her is what is needed now. Usually they visualize the knife entering their body for a noble purpose and that the blood at the time moves away from the surgery site.</p>
<p>Surgical steps are reviewed and how particularly the patient, the surgeon and the patient&#8217;s body are cooperating. They visualize how the area of the body is being &#8220;corrected&#8221; and how wonderful it will be for the quality of their life and health afterwards.</p>
<p>They imagine the anesthesia wearing off in a pleasant manner. I suggest that, as the anesthesia wears off, they will soon want water and some food. We discuss their body eliminating in a normal way and the body vitals being such that they can soon go home.</p>
<p>Other images might include seeing loved ones arrive to take them home and how soon they see the anticipated surgical improvements. Any rehabilitation services can also be incorporated into the imagery exercise.</p>
<p>Typically, it is best  to have several weeks to prepare for the surgery but have seen benefit in just a few sessions.&#8221;</p>
<p>Notice that there are three main devices being used. They are relaxation, imagery and suggestion. This is a triad that can help get you through just about any difficult situation.</p>
<p>RELATED READINGS</p>
<p>For clinical techniques we recommend Stanley Fischer&#8217;s &#8220;Discovering the Power of Self Hypnosis : A New Approach for Enabling Change And Promoting Healing.&#8221; The book was published in 1991, so is likely to be out of print but you can probably get a good used one at Abebooks.com at a very low price.</p>
<p>For a very good review of research on the evidence that supports the efficacy of this kind of method for surgical preparation we recommend &#8220;Mind-Body Interventions for Surgery: Evidence and Exigency,&#8221;published in Advances in Mind-Body Medicine, volume 14, Number 3 in the Summer of 1998, Pages 165-234. You can probably get a copy at little or no cost from your library. Be sure to ask for an interlibrary loan. Reading the article will likely be a challenge unless you have background in scientific writing , including statistical methods.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tips for Resilient Aging 2</title>
		<link>/2016/02/16/tips-for-resilient-aging-2/</link>
		<comments>/2016/02/16/tips-for-resilient-aging-2/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2016 04:11:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Aging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2032</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This post is our second in a short series on resilient aging. In our previous post on successful aging we discussed research indicating that a great deal of the physiological changes thought to be due to aging may be due &#8230; <a href="/2016/02/16/tips-for-resilient-aging-2/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This post is our second in a short series on resilient aging.</p>
<p>In our previous post on successful aging we discussed research indicating that a great deal of the physiological changes thought to be due to aging may be due to shifting toward a sedentary lifestyle.</p>
<p>Giving elderly people a program of gradually increased exercise, stretching, and relaxation can lead to physiological changes that make elders physiologically more like those of the young. Furthermore, paying young people to shift to a sedentary lifestyle leads to physiological profiles more typical of the elderly.</p>
<p>So, to a considerable degree, our biological age can be controlled by adopting the right lifestyle.</p>
<p>One of the things most of us see as inevitably linked to getting older is memory loss. Research done comparing samples of elders versus younger adults has shown that memory is typically less reliable in older people.</p>
<p>However, there are techniques that can markedly improve memory. These are techniques known since ancient times, and still used by &#8220;mnemonists&#8221;, experts who can do such things as entertain audiences by introducing themselves to each person in a sizeable audience and then accurately remembering each persons name.</p>
<p>If the old are taught these techniques, they can perform as well as or better than younger people who lack the training. This is a pattern that is not limited to memory. Training in well-selected resilience techniques can compensate for a wide range of limitations related to aging.</p>
<p>Two gerontologists, Paul and Margret Baltes developed a model of how losses due to aging can be kept under control. It is called the SOC model, for &#8220;Selection, Optimization, and Compensation&#8221;.</p>
<p>Selection refers to picking abilities that are important to us and that we are willing to work to maintain. To illustrate selection, the Baltes once used the example of the great violinist, Yehudi Menuhin who was able to perform brilliantly into his elder years, in part by reducing the number of pieces he maintained in his repertoire.</p>
<p>&#8220;Selection&#8221; is familiar to most of us, since it is basically setting your goals.</p>
<p>The &#8220;O&#8221; in SOC refers to optimization. This means developing skills or other assets that help you attain your goals.</p>
<p>Resilience training is one such means of developing widely applicable skills and habits that can move you toward the goals you chose during the selection phase. Finding a good place to exercise, or friends to join you in your exercise are other examples.</p>
<p>Compensation is illustrated by another thing that enabled Yehudi Menuhin to keep performing at the highest professional level into advanced age. After deciding which things to keep in his repertoire, he intensified his practice of the musical pieces that remained.</p>
<p>Now what if you are neither a professional musician nor a person close to old age? Well, after developing the SOC model, it was applied to young people and its results were assessed.</p>
<p>The model works for younger people too!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2016/02/16/tips-for-resilient-aging-2/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tips for Resilient Aging 1</title>
		<link>/2016/01/28/tips-for-resilient-aging-1/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2016 18:15:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2023</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[It&#8217;s well known that the population of the US and other Developed Countries is getting older, and this shift has many consequences. A wide range of important stressors increase with age. Elderly people face many losses. Their friends and neighbors &#8230; <a href="/2016/01/28/tips-for-resilient-aging-1/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It&#8217;s well known that the population of the US and other Developed Countries is getting older, and this shift has many consequences.</p>
<p>A wide range of important stressors increase with age. Elderly people face many losses. Their friends and neighbors die, their appearance tends to drop below social standards for attractiveness, they typically become less agile and peppy. Eventually they often have to let go of their homes and many of their possessions; many people end up in assisted-living facilities with little beyond the things that fit into a small closet or chest.</p>
<p>This is, of course, only a tiny, hapharzardly selected, sample of stressors that tend to accompany the passage of years. Without regard to such details, the old quote from Bette Davis says it all &#8220;Getting old ain&#8217;t for sissies&#8221;. If you are smart, you will prepare for it.</p>
<p>Since it takes time and energy to develop techniques for enhancing resilience and turn them into personal habits, it is fortunate that resilience techniques are also have a myriad of benefits for dealing with any of life&#8217;s stages.</p>
<p>Several major studies have influenced our view of techniques that help us respond to aging with resilience. Our plan for this and the next few posts is to describe these influential bodies of evidence.</p>
<p>The first is based on research done by Herbert DeVries and colleagues. and summarized in a book entitled &#8220;Vigor Regained&#8221;.</p>
<p>DeVries determined &#8220;scientifically whether carefully planned and controlled exercise can help restore vigor to older people&#8221;, and solidly affirmed that it could. He found that sedentary people, even in their 70s,80s,or 90s were, after training, able to run a nonstop mile.</p>
<p><span id="more-2023"></span></p>
<p>His sedentary elders were given a slowly increasing program that started with walking at a comfortable pace, eventually punctuating the walks with short periods of jogging, which were slowly increased to full jogging.</p>
<p>Could it be that some losses thought to be due to aging are to a greater extent, due to a shortage of exercise? DeVries points out that in a previous study called &#8220;Operation Sacktime&#8221;, college-age people who had been payed to stay entirely inactive over a period of two or three weeks lost their ability to adjust to strenuous activity as indicated in measures of the reactions of heart, lungs, circulation, and muscles. Physiological indicators of fitness were like those of sedentary elders.</p>
<p>How can you make use of this information? You could get a copy of Vigor Regained. It is out of print, but we searched for it and our first hit offered a copy for less than a dollar. Try <a href="http://www.amazon.com/">Amazon</a> or <a href="http://www.abebooks.com/">Abebooks.com</a>.</p>
<p>The book is a bit technical in spots, but it isn&#8217;t necessary to focus on those details. Really, any source of information on how to develop a mild exercise program that can be slowly increased will probably do. Our main warnings are to be sure you are well enough to do the exercise before starting (ask your doctor), and avoid pushing too hard and turning it into grueling &#8220;Type A exercise&#8221;. (We see &#8220;Type A&#8217;s&#8221; at a park near our home, often many pounds overweight, running as hard as they can with dumbbells in their hands, oblivious to the harm they may be doing to themselves).</p>
<p>Make the experience positive. See if you can find a supportive friend to enjoy the experience with you.</p>
<p>Stretching was also an important part of his program. We think it&#8217;s a good idea to learn some yoga positions that provide stretching in a well-tested way. Signing up for a beginner&#8217;s yoga class is a good way to do that.</p>
<p>A third component of the program is relaxation. However, Devries did not develop a specific method of relaxation. To review some effective methods, just do a search for the term &#8220;relaxation&#8221; in this blog. Devries mentions Edmund Jacobson&#8217;s method of progressive relaxation, but does not provide a simple, self-taught way to induce deep relaxation. This is probably because he had discovered that a 15 minute brisk walk was more effective in producing relaxation than a tranquillizer.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=&amp;linkname=Tips%20for%20Resilient%20Aging%201" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Core Principles of Progressive Relaxation.</title>
		<link>/2015/07/08/the-core-principles-of-progressive-relaxation/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2015 04:00:29 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1940</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[While preparing our previous post on using breath control to relax, we ran into some technical barriers to uploading one of our relaxation audios to the post. Rather than add delays to uploading the post, we decided to select from &#8230; <a href="/2015/07/08/the-core-principles-of-progressive-relaxation/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>While preparing our previous post on using breath control to relax, we ran into some technical barriers to uploading one of our relaxation audios to the post. Rather than add delays to uploading the post, we decided to select from the multitude of videos offered on You Tube.</p>
<p>We were aghast to find that almost all of the videos made a fundamental mistake that would likely keep people from developing the awareness of muscular tension that is central to relaxation training in which you deliberately alternate tensing and relaxing carefully attending to and contrasting the two states.</p>
<p>Most of the videos instructed people to tighten muscles very strongly, even “as hard as you can”.</p>
<p>The central idea of progressive relaxation is to become sensitive even to slight amounts of tension and learn to shut that tension off.</p>
<p>Contracting strongly will relax you briefly because it is isometric exercise. It do little to teach you to recognize the tensions of anxiety or to control them.</p>
<p>Progressive Relaxation (PR) was developed by Edmund Jacobsen, an M.D. Ph.D with a strong background in physiological research. He also introduced a newly developed tool, the electromyography, so could measure tension objectively.</p>
<p>Anyone who has observed the direct readings of muscular tension that an EMG provides can tell you that it is common for people to report being totally relaxed when they are still far from it.</p>
<p>The main focus of PR was to learn to recognize muscular tension and how to release it. Jacobson’s technique started with learning to recognize tension when you place your forearm, bottom side down, on a flat surface and then gently point your fingers up toward the ceiling. At a later stage, he even had trainees lift the fingers only a small distance upward. This is far from tensing “as hard as you can”!</p>
<p>He also had trainees go through these procedures progressively, throughout the body until they reached a point where they were aware even of slight amounts of tension and knew how to shut the tension down.</p>
<p>PR has played an important role in many effective stress coping techniques so it’s worthwhile to review its core principles.<br />
<span id="more-1940"></span></p>
<p>Core Principles of Progressive Relaxation</p>
<p>• Normally people cannot identify muscular tension accurately.<br />
• If your brain stops sending your muscles signals to tense, you will be completely relaxed.<br />
• Relaxation is not doing. “Doing” works when you are trying to INITIATE an action to get something done. That creates more muscular tension, which is useful most of the time, but not when you are trying to relax.<br />
• If your muscles stop contracting, you will no longer be psychologically tense. The mind is much more dependent on muscular action than most of us realize.<br />
• You can relax below your “zero point” (the point where, as an untrained person you think you are fully relaxed).<br />
In our experience, really tense people may be utterly oblivious to sensations of tension, because their chronic tenseness becomes their normal “zero point”, and they think that anything below that is deep relaxation.</p>
<p>Where Jacobson Was Right and Where He Was Wrong</p>
<p>Evidence supports the idea that relaxation of muscles is a powerful relaxant of the mind, and Jacobson was right to give it a central place in his training. There has been strong evidence that his method works. It is wise to use relaxation techniques that are consistent with his core principles.</p>
<p>However, there is clear evidence that the mind, including the emotions, continues to function even when skeletal muscles are completely blocked by a drug. The drug used to show this was a refined derivative of curare. Curare is a drug put on the tips of darts by certain South American Indians to kill prey. We now know that it works by blocking the chemical transmitter that enables the nervous system to control the muscles.</p>
<p>During the mid-1940s two anesthesiologists, Frederick Prescott in the UK and Scott Smith in the US independently volunteered to be “guinea pigs” to test the effects of a purified form of curare. Their breathing was maintained mechanically.</p>
<p>They knew it would paralyze their muscles, but wanted to know whether it would also make them unconscious.Some doctors were doing surgery on the assumption that under the influence of the drug patients were unconscious and did not feel pain.</p>
<p>When these two doctors volunteered to be paralyzed by the drug, including high doses, they later reported that their mental processes, including emotions and feelings of distress, persisted. Curare and it’s more refined derivatives should not be used as an anesthetic.</p>
<p>Both had a rapid heartrate and elevated blood pressure. Prescott attributed this to emotion, saying that “… one cannot be paralyzed and remain perfectly tranquil”.</p>
<p>This clearly shows that, though relaxing skeletal muscles helps relax the mind, when the muscles are completely paralyzed, one can react with a loss of “tranquility”.</p>
<p>Progressive Relaxation is an excellent way to relax, but it’s is not a cure-all for distress.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=&amp;linkname=" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Breath Control to Shed Symptoms and Increase Resilience</title>
		<link>/2015/06/17/breath-control-to-shed-symptoms-and-increase-resilience/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2015 23:10:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Breath Control]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1917</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In two earlier posts on tactical breathing, here and here, we discussed several ways to change your breathing patterns in order to deal effectively with events that are difficult or even terrifying. Today we will discuss chronic hyperventilation (overbreathing), a &#8230; <a href="/2015/06/17/breath-control-to-shed-symptoms-and-increase-resilience/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In two earlier posts on tactical breathing, <a href="/2011/06/14/a-plain-vanilla-application-of-tactical-breathing-to-increase-resilience/">here </a>and <a href="/2011/06/02/tactical-breathing-can-stop-stress-on-the-spot/">here</a>, we discussed several ways to change your breathing patterns in order to deal effectively with events that are difficult or even terrifying.</p>
<p>Today we will discuss chronic hyperventilation (overbreathing), a very damaging pattern of breathing, and ways to deal with it. It happens that a major branch of classic yoga is pranayama, a discipline dedicated to breath-training.</p>
<p>But isn’t breathing automatic? When you fall asleep or even are knocked unconscious, you continue breathing. There is no need to understand<br />
how you breathe because it is regulated by primitive parts of the brain at its very deepest levels, even without guidance from higher parts of the brain.</p>
<p>However, breathing can also be controlled by higher areas of the brain, including the most advanced cortical areas. And pranayama, tactical breathing, and some modern research on chronic hyperventilation all suggest that learning new breathing patterns, and especially turning them into ingrained habits, can help us to be more resilient in stressful situations and to shed symptoms that are due to faulty patterns of breathing.</p>
<p><strong>What kind of symptoms are we talking about?</strong></p>
<p>The answer to this question is most readily found in papers on the effects of chronic hyperventilation. The symptoms are incredibly diverse, and are often viewed as “in your head”, “neurotic” or “due to anxiety”. These patients go from one doctor after another and rarely get real relief.</p>
<p>A good short list of the symptoms can be found in a paper by <a href="http://www.members.westnet.com.au/pkolb/lum.htm">L.C. Lum, Table 1</a>. They include symptoms of diseases of the heart, lungs, intestines, nervous system as well as psychological symptoms, e.g. anxiety, tension, etc.</p>
<p>How can such a variety of symptoms result from something as simple as a pattern of breathing? It does, indeed, seem to treat breath control as a kind of cure-all. But the linkage of this array of symptoms and overbreathing makes sense because this kind of breathing results in a rapid drop of blood carbon dioxide by 50%, and carbon dioxide rapidly and dramatically changes the activity of nerve tissue. (If you are interested in technical details, see <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1440257/">this article</a> by R.A. Cluff. Be sure to click link to the complete article.)</p>
<p><strong>What You Should Do If You Think You May Be Hyperventilating?</strong></p>
<p>The two links mentioned in the first sentence of this post provide several useful ways to change your breathing pattern to increase your resilience. They can give you relief on the spot. However, to make longer term changes, you will have to practice regularly for some time.</p>
<p>If you want to go beyond those options, and get some coaching and support from others, many programs are available. Try looking into yoga studios, checking whether they have courses that emphasize pranayama or at least give it some priority. Pranayama is based on almost 3000 years of varying and practicing breath patterns and carefully observing their effects. So it is the most thorough breath control discipline.</p>
<p>Papworth hospital in Cambridge, England has a method of retraining hyperventilators that succeeds in a very large proportion of cases, but Papworth is not easily accessible for most of us, and their technique involves inpatient training.</p>
<p>First they show the patient that they can reproduce their symptoms by rapid, shallow breathing from the chest. Then they train them twice daily to do slow, diaphragmatic deep breathing, until their breathing rate is around six times per minute, which tends to be about one third of their original rate.</p>
<p>To help you try out diaphragmatic breathing, watch this video, then practice regularly. There are many more videos teaching diaphragmatic breathing on Youtube done by teachers of Yoga, Pilates, Hand Therapy, Physical Therapy, and more. Obviously, if you want personal training, it is widely available.</p>
<p>The Papworth method also includes a version of progressive relaxation training. Relaxation training instruction is widely available for free on You Tube. Unfortunately, most of the videos have serious errors that are incompatible with the core concepts of Progressive Relaxation, which appears to be the method they are striving to demonstrate.</p>
<p>The central goal of Progressive Relaxation is for people to really learn the difference between tension and relaxation. To do so, they have to train themselves to recognize increases in bodily tension as clearly as they recognize sights and sounds.</p>
<p>Most of the free videos demonstrate exercises that are inconsistent with learning to sense tension. For example, they have people tighten muscles as hard as possible without damaging themselves. That makes sensations of pain and strain that get in the way of observing ordinary tension.</p>
<p>We will explain other details of Progressive Relaxation in future posts. For now, <a href="http://www.columbiamo.va.gov/audiofiles/Track_2.mp3">here</a> is an audio you can use for deep relaxation.<code></code></p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2015%2F06%2F17%2Fbreath-control-to-shed-symptoms-and-increase-resilience%2F&amp;linkname=Breath%20Control%20to%20Shed%20Symptoms%20and%20Increase%20Resilience" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
	<enclosure url="http://www.columbiamo.va.gov/audiofiles/Track_2.mp3" length="41367760" type="audio/mpeg" />
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Distractions Play a Central Role in Producing the Benefits of Meditation</title>
		<link>/2015/05/07/distractions-play-a-central-role-in-producing-the-benefits-of-meditation/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2015 15:30:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1884</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[When you meditate, your experiences fall into two categories : 1. The object on which you intend to focus, and 2. Distractions. Here we want to focus on distractions, particularly on where they come from and what you should do &#8230; <a href="/2015/05/07/distractions-play-a-central-role-in-producing-the-benefits-of-meditation/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When you meditate, your experiences fall into two categories : 1. The object on which you intend to focus, and 2. Distractions.<br />
Here we want to focus on distractions, particularly on where they come from and what you should do with them. </p>
<p>At first we may be inclined to say that distractions are mere chaos of the mind. When we call them “chatter” we come close to implying that view of them.If you take a step back and observe distractions, you can see that they are meaningful. In our ordinary, non-meditative life, they are calls to needed actions, attempts to solve problems that we face, strategies for fending off painful thoughts, etc.</p>
<p>During meditation, they are not allowed to take center stage.We keep our attention on the object of our meditation by gently turning away from the distractions. We do not wage an internal war against them. Instead we take a calm, passive attitude toward them, and let the distractions pass through, neither grasping them nor fighting them off.</p>
<p>What happens as you get better and better at letting thoughts that have usually driven you to action go unappeased is that the distraction loses its power over you, and you start remaining calm and centered instead of jumping to action.<br />
You can see why meditation can make you calm, relaxed, and in control of your own actions.</p>
<h2>Autogenic Discharge</h2>
<p>One particular type of distraction calls for special attention. We call it “discharge”, a term taken from Autogenic Training, which can be observed over a wide range of techniques that involve calming the mind and body. For example, in Zen meditation it is called “<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Makyo">Makyo</a>”, and Zen masters inquire about it regularly with their students.</p>
<p>These discharges may include a wide range of symptoms such as dizziness, anxiety, headache, nausea, twitching, disturbing images, crying etc. In some ways their texture is similar to that of experiences people may have just before they go to sleep.</p>
<p>The best thing to do when you have these experiences is to gently turn your attention back to the object of your meditation. Generally, such experiences are self-limiting. If you stay with your meditative focus, they will fade away.</p>
<p>However, if they feel unbearably disturbing, stop meditating. It’s best not to try toughing out the experience.</p>
<p>A number of adjustments can be made in your meditation routine in order to minimize the occurrence of such highly disturbing experiences.<span id="more-1884"></span></p>
<p>1. Reduce the length and/or the frequency of your sessions. Shorter methods tend to produce fewer discharges, as does reducing the frequency of sessions.</p>
<p>2. Shift from a highly passive method to one that is more active. For example, a relaxation procedure that has you tense and relax body parts, attending to the feelings of tension and relaxation is less passive than simply observing your breath.</p>
<p>3. Be sure that the context in which you are doing the work makes you feel safe. Your view of your setting has a powerful effect on how you interpret your experiences. To illustrate, there are a number of psychological studies showing that people given a drug that speeds the heart can produce reactions as diverse as increasing anger and increasing laughter. The situation determines the meaning of the state of arousal.</p>
<p>Finally, we pointed out earlier that each time meditators minimize their reactions to distractions, gently turning their attention back to the object of their meditation, the distractions lose more and more of their power to control you. For that reason the distractions are actually a very important part of the meditation.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2015%2F05%2F07%2Fdistractions-play-a-central-role-in-producing-the-benefits-of-meditation%2F&amp;linkname=Distractions%20Play%20a%20Central%20Role%20in%20Producing%20the%20Benefits%20of%20Meditation" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Build Your “Toughness” and Become More Resilient</title>
		<link>/2014/10/08/build-your-toughness-and-become-more-resilient/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2014 23:28:15 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Cognitive Reappraisal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Toughness]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1758</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In the late 1980s, a Professor from the University of Nebraska published an important article on something he called “toughness”. He pointed out that the prevalent belief of experts was that the “arousal” that is stimulated by stress is just &#8230; <a href="/2014/10/08/build-your-toughness-and-become-more-resilient/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the late 1980s, a Professor from the University of Nebraska published an <a href="http://digitalcommons.unl.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1215&amp;context=psychfacpub&amp;sei-redir=1&amp;referer=http%3A%2F%2Fscholar.google.com%2Fscholar%3Fhl%3Den%26q%3Ddienstbier%2Btoughness%26btnG%3D%26as_sdt%3D1%252C26%26as_sdtp%3D#search=%22dienstbier%20toughness%22">important article</a> on something he called “toughness”. He pointed out that the prevalent belief of experts was that the “arousal” that is stimulated by stress is just plain BAD. (This word “arousal” in ordinary parlance usually refers to sex, but here it means having the brain highly activated and the body prepared for action, the kind of action that enables you to confront a threat and either escape or defeat it).</p>
<p>The Professor, Richard Dienstbier, summarized a wide range of research showing that this arousal could damage you, but could also toughen you. In some cases it can even be exhilarating and good for your health.</p>
<p>This is where the technical sense of “arousal” and the sexual sense of it converge. During sex the body responds in many of the same ways it responds to threats, for example, with fast and strong heartbeats and elevated blood pressure. It also recovers quickly and fully.</p>
<p>Quick and full recovery are at the heart of toughness and resilience.</p>
<p>If you do not recover, and have high arousal over long periods with few times at rest, THAT is damaging.</p>
<p>So if you are a person who suffers from constant distress, what can you do? Here are a few examples.</p>
<ol>
<li>Develop the Knowledge and Skills that Enable You to Recover promptly from Stress for example, learn how to <a href="/2010/12/06/a-key-step-in-resilience-training-is-learning-deep-relaxation/">relax <em>deeply</em></a><em>.</em></li>
<li>Practice some form of <a href="/2014/01/15/a-simple-way-to-sooth-and-comfort-yourself/">meditation</a>.</li>
<li>Exercise regularly, and include aerobic exercise such as brisk walking, jogging, or cycling.</li>
</ol>
<p>Just click the links and you will find instructions how to do each of the listed techniques.</p>
<p>Further Possibilities: Exposure Training</p>
<p>Dienstbier’s work focused attention on the key role of recovery from stress, but that is not all it did. It also led us to see <em>how valuable exposure to stressors could be</em>. Being exposed to stress from which you can recover promptly will make you physiologically tougher.</p>
<p>This is exactly what we do when we engage in regular exercise that is moderate.</p>
<p>We can do the same sort of thing with just about any kind of stressor. For example, most people find public speaking very stressful, and many of them join <a href="http://www.toastmasters.org/">Toastmasters</a>, where they regularly give speeches to groups of people who are also working to develop their public speaking skills.</p>
<p>Cognitive Reappraisal</p>
<p>Two things interact to produce stress reactions. First is the event itself, and second is our interpretation of the event. The interpretation can be at least as important as the event. Dienstbier makes use of a well-known model of stress reactions (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a8FEMHCRowM">Lazarus and Folkman</a>). Their view is that we make two appraisals, a ”primary appraisal” and a “secondary appraisal.&#8221; Primary is an appraisal of the level of threat the stressor presents. Secondary is an appraisal of the resources you have to cope with the stressor.</p>
<p>If you judge that a stressor is beyond what you can manage, you are facing a <strong>threat</strong>. If you judge that you can handle the stressor, you are dealing with a <strong>challenge</strong>. And challenges can be opportunities to toughen yourself, and maybe even have fun.</p>
<p>Appraisals need not be set in concrete. They are, after all, in our minds. A good deal of research has been focused on teaching people to <strong>reappraise</strong> life events, and it turns out that these reappraisals can really improve performance.</p>
<p>To clarify the concept of reappraisal, imagine a student who does poorly on an important exam. The student interprets this failing as evidence that s/he is “stupid” and “hopeless”.</p>
<p>Now suppose the student is guided to consider that the failure was due to lack of skills of note taking, studying, and/or test taking. The new appraisal implies that there are things s/he can do to perform better the next time. Now a threat has been changed to a challenge.  And dealing with it can make the student tougher.</p>
<p>Cognitive reappraisal has a wide range of applications. Good research has shown that is helpful in dealing with PTSD, fighting food temptations, reducing negative feelings, and reducing anxiety. And this is very far from a complete list.</p>
<p>We will be saying more about cognitive reappraisal in future posts.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F10%2F08%2Fbuild-your-toughness-become-more-resilient%2F&amp;linkname=Build%20Your%20%E2%80%9CToughness%E2%80%9D%20Become%20More%20Resilient" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>More Resilience Training Can Produce Richer, More Powerful Results.</title>
		<link>/2014/08/04/many-resilience-techniques-can-be-brief-and-easy-but-more-training-can-produce-richer-more-powerful-results/</link>
		<comments>/2014/08/04/many-resilience-techniques-can-be-brief-and-easy-but-more-training-can-produce-richer-more-powerful-results/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2014 18:55:57 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[How Hard Is It To Change Resilience?]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1709</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[We have often pointed out, maybe even emphasized, how easy it is to learn techniques that are helpful in resisting and recovering from stress. The techniques are not only easy, but are typically pleasant and comforting. Most resilience training methods &#8230; <a href="/2014/08/04/many-resilience-techniques-can-be-brief-and-easy-but-more-training-can-produce-richer-more-powerful-results/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We have often pointed out, maybe even emphasized, how <em>easy</em> it is to learn techniques that are helpful in resisting and recovering from stress.</p>
<p>The techniques are not only easy, but are typically pleasant and comforting. Most resilience training methods make you feel somewhere in the range of good to very good.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, too many people practice for a while, but then get embedded in the demands of ordinary life and never get to see how rich the benefits might be if they continued over the long term.</p>
<p>Take <a href="/2010/12/06/a-key-step-in-resilience-training-is-learning-deep-relaxation/">deep relaxation</a> as an example. A large majority of people who try basic methods of deep relaxation find the states they induce both useful and pleasant.</p>
<p>They should consider persisting at least a little longer. For some methods of relaxation and calming, there is evidence that practice can continue to improve, even over many years.</p>
<p>A striking example is the work of a Japanese researcher, Tomio Hirai. He studied changes in brain waves that take place when people practice Zen Meditation. (It is called “Zazen” and is essentially identical to the currently popular “Mindfulness Meditation”).</p>
<p><span id="more-1709"></span></p>
<p>Zazen involves sitting in a stable posture and attending to your breathing. The goal is to do that and nothing else.</p>
<p>Beginners count their inhalations and exhalations from one to ten; then they go back to one and start over again. If you try this for a while you will find yourself counting numbers like “42”, indicating that your mind has wandered without your noticing it. When this happens you just calmly go back to one.</p>
<p>As time goes on, brain wave patterns shift from fast to slow (an indication of calm, deep relaxation, the antithesis of a stress response, a “relaxation response”).</p>
<p>Hirai found that even after decades of practice meditators <a href="http://is.muni.cz/www/178816/EEG_and_Zazen.pdf">are still improving</a>.</p>
<p>But their commitment to meditation is not just to deal with life’s frustrations. As part of a Buddhist tradition, it is done to achieve some form of “enlightenment”, a profound and highly beneficial readjustment of their perceptions of themselves and of the world.</p>
<p>Zen masters recognize and accept that many people who practice Zazen, do so in order to function better in their ordinary lives. The term “<a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=KczYq22WAeYC&amp;pg=PA49&amp;lpg=PA49&amp;dq=bompu+zen&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=igVZJ2sn_3&amp;sig=7PRrXKcW1ep0fUHZCShYKcRc_cc&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=3rfdU_POGKLT8AGjvoCgCg&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CFIQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=bompu%20zen&amp;f=false">Bompu Zen</a>” is used for this more basic approach.</p>
<p>What resilience training normally aims to achieve is at the level of Bompu Zen. This does not meant that it is <em>merely</em> bompu Zen. We, for example, include the most effective techniques from a wide variety of traditions and other sources, as long as their effectiveness is robust enough to be empirically confirmed.</p>
<p>It appears that “the sky is the limit” when it comes to how far you can go with your training. Whether you reach for the sky depends on your ultimate goals. It depends on whether you seek a radically new perspective on the world and your life or just want to deal more effectively with life’s familiar demands, which is, incidentally, the humble goal we have chosen for this blog.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F08%2F04%2Fmany-resilience-techniques-can-be-brief-and-easy-but-more-training-can-produce-richer-more-powerful-results%2F&amp;linkname=Many%20Resilience%20Techniques%20Can%20Be%20%20Brief%20and%20Easy%2C%20but%20More%20Training%20Can%20Produce%20Richer%2C%20More%20Powerful%20Results." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2014/08/04/many-resilience-techniques-can-be-brief-and-easy-but-more-training-can-produce-richer-more-powerful-results/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Map of the Path to Increased Resilience.</title>
		<link>/2013/06/20/a-map-of-the-path-to-increased-resilience/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2013 05:19:14 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Attitudes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1392</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Underlying our posts is a three-factor model of resilience which was derived from research done as part of my role as a professor. Our posts tend to be on specific attitudes or actions that are statistically confirmed aspects of one &#8230; <a href="/2013/06/20/a-map-of-the-path-to-increased-resilience/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Underlying our posts is a three-factor model of resilience which was derived from research done as part of my role as a professor. Our posts tend to be on specific attitudes or actions that are statistically confirmed aspects of one of the three factors. That is not because we select them only if they match our model. Our model just matches the data.</p>
<p>The blog was not started to publicize or support the model. It started as an outlet to keep me from constantly adding new findings to a book Debbie and I wrote to teach people how to improve their resilience.</p>
<p>To identify the core factors that underlie resilience we used a method called factor analysis. Done correctly, it can reveal the deep structure of whatever you are studying. So, for example, if you used it on three dimensional objects, like boxes, it would tell you that there are three dimensions, height, width and length.</p>
<p>We determined the dimensions of resilience and found that there were three. We also replicated that finding in two additional studies, and both of them confirmed the three dimensions.</p>
<p>To explain the factors here would be redundant, since we have already done that in <a href="/2011/01/11/the-three-core-factors-that-can-make-you-more-resilient/">this post</a>.</p>
<p>For now, we will discuss the number one factor that improves resilience.</p>
<h2>What good is this to you?</h2>
<p>Knowing the core dimensions will help you pinpoint all you can do to improve your resilience.</p>
<p>The number one influence on resilience is developing resilience-promoting  <strong><em>attitudes</em></strong> and <strong><em>skills</em></strong>.  These account for so much of resilience that, for a while, I was tempted to think of Factor One alone as just plain resilience, and ignore the other two factors. But too much evidence showed that those factors can be crucial for many people.</p>
<p>So what are the attitudes and skills you should try to develop?</p>
<p><span id="more-1392"></span></p>
<ul>
<li>Being optimistic and hopeful instead of pessimistic and hopeless.</li>
<li>Seeing distressing or painful life events as problems to be solved instead of things to be lamented and cursed.</li>
<li>Looking for and maybe even finding meaning in what we do and what we experience instead of just slogging through life.</li>
<li>Learning how to sooth, calm and replenish yourself, and then <strong><em>applying what you have learned </em></strong>to your everyday life when you are distressed, and also when you are feeling okay. (The latter is important in order to develop <strong><em>habits</em></strong> of resilience.).</li>
</ul>
<p>Some of the attitudes under factor one that help us be more resilient are</p>
<ol start="1">
<li>Being optimistic and hopeful versus viewing life with pessimism or despair.</li>
</ol>
<p>Here are posts that tell you how to do that:</p>
<p><a href="/2011/01/01/less-pessimism-and-more-optimism-will-build-your-resilience/">Increasing your optimism.</a></p>
<p><a href="/2012/08/02/reducing-negativity-in-your-mind-and-your-life/">Decreasing your negativity.</a></p>
<ol start="2">
<li>Viewing our lives, our choices, and our actions as meaningful versus seeing them as meaningless.</li>
</ol>
<p>Here is a post to help you do that.</p>
<p><a href="/2011/11/28/finding-meaning-and-purpose-can-help-you-deal-with-distress-no-matter-how-extreme/">Finding  meaning.</a></p>
<ol start="3">
<li>Taking a problem-solving attitude toward stressful situations and anticipating predictable complications.</li>
</ol>
<p>Here is a post that shows you how to do that:</p>
<p><a href="/2012/08/02/reducing-negativity-in-your-mind-and-your-life/">Problem-Solving Attitude.</a></p>
<ol start="4">
<li>Learning and applying  the skills that sooth and replenish you instead of taking actions that make things worse.</li>
</ol>
<p>There are many posts that show how to do that:</p>
<p><a href="/2011/03/02/basic-mindfulness-technique/">Training yourself in mindfulness.</a></p>
<p><a href="/2011/06/02/tactical-breathing-can-stop-stress-on-the-spot/">Breath control for resilience.</a></p>
<p><a href="/2010/12/06/a-key-step-in-resilience-training-is-learning-deep-relaxation/">Learning deep relaxation.</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F06%2F20%2Fa-map-of-the-path-to-increased-resilience%2F&amp;linkname=A%20Map%20of%20the%20Path%20to%20Increased%20Resilience." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Some Things You Can Learn From Abraham Lincoln about How to Manage Your Life.</title>
		<link>/2013/02/05/some-things-you-can-learn-from-abraham-lincoln-about-how-to-manage-your-life/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2013 18:08:12 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1307</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[A recent article in the New York Times showed that Abraham Lincoln’s methods of managing the country can serve as a guide to managing a business. It struck me that each of us is the CEO of her or his &#8230; <a href="/2013/02/05/some-things-you-can-learn-from-abraham-lincoln-about-how-to-manage-your-life/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A <a href="../Dropbox/New%20folder/Abraham%20Lincoln,%20as%20Management%20Guru%20-%20NYTimes.com.htm">recent article</a> in the New York Times showed that Abraham Lincoln’s methods of managing the country can serve as a guide to managing a business.</p>
<p>It struck me that each of us is the CEO of her or his own life. Could it be that Lincoln’s way of managing the country can teach us something about managing our own lives?</p>
<p>I think it can, and the purpose of this post is to explain why I believe that, and to show how you can try it out.</p>
<p><span id="more-1307"></span></p>
<p>At one point in the New York Times article, it pointed out that Lincoln displayed the ability to learn and grow amidst great calamity. I had never thought of it this way, but that is really a pretty good way to describe resilience.</p>
<p>People who are not resilient cannot “learn and grow amidst great calamity”, largely because, in the face of calamity, they tend to do things that amplify and spread the impact of the calamity. Don’t do that!</p>
<p>We have to train ourselves to minimize the impact of calamity. Otherwise, all of our mental resources are drained as we imagine catastrophic possible outcomes, focus on who is to blame, or consult with people who will concur with our worst expectations about what is going to happen.</p>
<p>It is important to practice talking to yourself in an optimistic and hopeful way rather than catastrophizing over imagined bad outcomes, most of which never happen.</p>
<p>You should train yourself to relax enough to keep a clear head when things go badly. There are many ways to relax deeply; a very simple, easy one is <a href="/2010/12/06/a-key-step-in-resilience-training-is-learning-deep-relaxation/">here</a>. All you have to do is get in a reasonably quiet place, then listen the audio, following the instructions. It’s best to do that regularly for a few weeks, and then use it as needed.</p>
<p>Lincoln suffered from horrible losses while he was taking responsibility for the Civil War. His generals failed him, sometimes miserably. His 11 year old son died, triggering events that deprived him of much support from his wife, instead demanding that he direct his personal resources to helping her get through the pain and distress, when he must have had few resources to spare.</p>
<p>He also suffered from severe depression. Still, he continued to make effective and responsible decisions. He exemplified an important aspect of resilience: we are not ruled by our moods and emotions. We can let ourselves be aware of them yet still know that they are not the arbiters of reality and we are not enslaved by them.</p>
<p>It is easy to say that we are not ruled by our moods and emotions, but putting that view into practice is hard, and is best done by regularly training yourself to have a clear sense that feelings are there, but they are just feelings that come and go.</p>
<p>Meditation is a path to developing clarity about the role of our emotions. Currently “mindfulness meditation” is very much in vogue, and it works. <a href="/2011/03/02/basic-mindfulness-technique/">Here</a> is a short description of a way to do this kind of meditation.</p>
<p>Lincoln tended to ponder a great deal before making decisions. He did not just lock himself in a room and think about how to turn facts he already knew into a decision. He sought out the views of others, making sure that a wide range of perspectives were included in the raw material he used for making decisions.</p>
<p>This does not mean that he ended up indecisive. He distilled those many perspectives into the closest thing to realism he could reach and then made his decisions firmly.</p>
<p>For all of us, it can be tempting to avoid information that might not fit into our mental model of the world. Sometimes that works for a while, but sooner or later we have to face reality. Lincoln provides a good template for how to reach the best match to reality you can.</p>
<p>Notice that Lincoln understood the importance of reaching out to others. This is an important aspect of living well.</p>
<p>One last principle for managing our lives gleaned from Lincoln is that we should stay true to a higher purpose. I recall many years ago reading about psychologist, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abraham_Maslow">Abraham Maslow</a>, who pointed out that many of the people who came to him for treatment really did not have an illness. He felt that they just needed to “take on a task worthy of themselves”.</p>
<p>Now I know many readers will believe that they cannot have such lofty goals, that all they have the time and energy for is to slog through wretched days that come upon them. Contrary to that belief, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viktor_Frankl">Victor Frankl</a> pointed out that finding meaning in life as a prisoner in a Nazi Concentration Camp was essential to survival.</p>
<p>It’s very doubtful that our painful situations are as bad as one of those camps. And finding meaning in your life will not drain you. It will energize you.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F02%2F05%2F1307%2F&amp;linkname=" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
