<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Resilience Training &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/resilience-training/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Yoga or Resilience Training: Do We Have to Choose?</title>
		<link>/2015/05/28/yoga-or-resilience-training-do-we-have-to-choose/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2015 03:18:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1904</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[What are the main differences between yoga and resilience training? Would it be a good idea to do both, or are they a bad mix? Around a year ago Debbie asked for a Yoga class as her birthday present. It &#8230; <a href="/2015/05/28/yoga-or-resilience-training-do-we-have-to-choose/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What are the main differences between yoga and resilience training? Would it be a good idea to do both, or are they a bad mix?</p>
<p>Around a year ago Debbie asked for a Yoga class as her birthday present. It was a great suggestion, and Yoga has helped her to cope with a stage in her life in which she has agreed to take responsibility for decisions about health care for her mother. Yoga worked for her and continues to be an important part of her life.</p>
<p>More recently a longstanding friend of mine suggested that I enroll in a beginner’s course in Yoga, and Debbie also urged that I take the course. For many years, I have been dealing with severe, chronic pain due to an arthritic spine that creates impingements on my spinal cord that result in chronic pain and problems with controlling how I walk.</p>
<p>I had just finished a very successful series of Physical Therapy interventions, so was interested in retaining the gains I had made through various forms of stretching and balancing.</p>
<p>Why did Debbie and I both reach out for help from another system instead of relying on the resilience techniques we already knew? Abraham Lincoln summarized one of the major reasons in a widely used quote about lawyers: “He who represents himself has a fool for a client.”</p>
<p>It’s helpful to get training from someone other than yourself. Distance provides a useful perspective.</p>
<p>In addition to that, though resilience training and Yoga superficially seem to have little in common, they are really very much alike. Both approaches use a wide range of techniques that enable you to know yourself at a deeper level and to soothe and calm yourself.</p>
<p>Yoga, as it is typically practiced in the United States, emphasizes working on changes of the body, and most resilience programs emphasize changes at the level of mind.<br />
But change in the body results in change in the mind and change at the level of the mind results in change in the body.</p>
<p>For example, if you are getting agitated, slowing and deepening your breathing pattern tends to calm both your mind and your body.</p>
<p>Similarly, you can make yourself salivate by imagining sucking on a lemon and you can make your hands get warmer by imagining yourself at the beach lying on a big towel and picturing the sun warming your hands.</p>
<p>For quite a few years a significant body of research in scientific psychology has focused a lot of its efforts on conducting studies to determine whether ancient techniques work. For the most part, those techniques have passed the tests and been integrated into psychological methods of treatment.</p>
<p>So our view is that ancient disciplines from the Far East tend to fit comfortably into recent, science-based resilience programs.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2015%2F05%2F28%2Fyoga-or-resilience-training-do-we-have-to-choose%2F&amp;linkname=Yoga%20or%20Resilience%20Training%3A%20Do%20We%20Have%20to%20Choose%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Distractions Play a Central Role in Producing the Benefits of Meditation</title>
		<link>/2015/05/07/distractions-play-a-central-role-in-producing-the-benefits-of-meditation/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2015 15:30:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1884</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[When you meditate, your experiences fall into two categories : 1. The object on which you intend to focus, and 2. Distractions. Here we want to focus on distractions, particularly on where they come from and what you should do &#8230; <a href="/2015/05/07/distractions-play-a-central-role-in-producing-the-benefits-of-meditation/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When you meditate, your experiences fall into two categories : 1. The object on which you intend to focus, and 2. Distractions.<br />
Here we want to focus on distractions, particularly on where they come from and what you should do with them. </p>
<p>At first we may be inclined to say that distractions are mere chaos of the mind. When we call them “chatter” we come close to implying that view of them.If you take a step back and observe distractions, you can see that they are meaningful. In our ordinary, non-meditative life, they are calls to needed actions, attempts to solve problems that we face, strategies for fending off painful thoughts, etc.</p>
<p>During meditation, they are not allowed to take center stage.We keep our attention on the object of our meditation by gently turning away from the distractions. We do not wage an internal war against them. Instead we take a calm, passive attitude toward them, and let the distractions pass through, neither grasping them nor fighting them off.</p>
<p>What happens as you get better and better at letting thoughts that have usually driven you to action go unappeased is that the distraction loses its power over you, and you start remaining calm and centered instead of jumping to action.<br />
You can see why meditation can make you calm, relaxed, and in control of your own actions.</p>
<h2>Autogenic Discharge</h2>
<p>One particular type of distraction calls for special attention. We call it “discharge”, a term taken from Autogenic Training, which can be observed over a wide range of techniques that involve calming the mind and body. For example, in Zen meditation it is called “<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Makyo">Makyo</a>”, and Zen masters inquire about it regularly with their students.</p>
<p>These discharges may include a wide range of symptoms such as dizziness, anxiety, headache, nausea, twitching, disturbing images, crying etc. In some ways their texture is similar to that of experiences people may have just before they go to sleep.</p>
<p>The best thing to do when you have these experiences is to gently turn your attention back to the object of your meditation. Generally, such experiences are self-limiting. If you stay with your meditative focus, they will fade away.</p>
<p>However, if they feel unbearably disturbing, stop meditating. It’s best not to try toughing out the experience.</p>
<p>A number of adjustments can be made in your meditation routine in order to minimize the occurrence of such highly disturbing experiences.<span id="more-1884"></span></p>
<p>1. Reduce the length and/or the frequency of your sessions. Shorter methods tend to produce fewer discharges, as does reducing the frequency of sessions.</p>
<p>2. Shift from a highly passive method to one that is more active. For example, a relaxation procedure that has you tense and relax body parts, attending to the feelings of tension and relaxation is less passive than simply observing your breath.</p>
<p>3. Be sure that the context in which you are doing the work makes you feel safe. Your view of your setting has a powerful effect on how you interpret your experiences. To illustrate, there are a number of psychological studies showing that people given a drug that speeds the heart can produce reactions as diverse as increasing anger and increasing laughter. The situation determines the meaning of the state of arousal.</p>
<p>Finally, we pointed out earlier that each time meditators minimize their reactions to distractions, gently turning their attention back to the object of their meditation, the distractions lose more and more of their power to control you. For that reason the distractions are actually a very important part of the meditation.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2015%2F05%2F07%2Fdistractions-play-a-central-role-in-producing-the-benefits-of-meditation%2F&amp;linkname=Distractions%20Play%20a%20Central%20Role%20in%20Producing%20the%20Benefits%20of%20Meditation" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mental Contrasting: An Important Technique for Reaching Your Goals.</title>
		<link>/2014/12/07/mental-contrasting-an-important-technique-for-reaching-your-goals/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2014 22:02:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Habits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mental contrasting]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1785</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In this post we hope to show you the value of a technique called “mental contrasting”. We want to explain that concept, to cite evidence that mental contrasting really helps people change their habits to healthier and more productive ones, &#8230; <a href="/2014/12/07/mental-contrasting-an-important-technique-for-reaching-your-goals/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this post we hope to show you the value of a technique called “mental contrasting”. We want to explain that concept, to cite evidence that mental contrasting really helps people change their habits to healthier and more productive ones, and to tell you what you need to know in order to use it yourself.</p>
<p><span id="more-1785"></span></p>
<p>In an<a title="earlier post" href="/2010/12/06/getting-yourself-to-act-on-what-you-learn-about-building-resilience/"> earlier post </a>we discussed Gabrielle Oettingen’s method of “mental contrasting” as a way to keep yourself practicing resilience skills. If you want to build these skills and turn them into habits you have to practice. But it is hard to change habits, and we all have trouble getting ourselves to persist in habit-changing practices until we reach our goals.</p>
<p>Mental contrasting has a very credible basis to claim that it is an important technique to help us persist in needed practices.</p>
<p>An article written by Oettingen <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/10/26/opinion/sunday/the-problem-with-positive-thinking.html?_r=0">appeared in the October 24<sup>th</sup> New York Times</a>, and has been in our “to do” folder ever since. This week, we had a good opportunity to digest its content.</p>
<p>If you find a better summary of mental contrasting and its uses, please let us know. This one is excellent. It identifies research done on mental contrasting, showing that it helps “college students wanting a date, hip-replacement patients hoping to get back on their feet, graduate students looking for a job, (and) schoolchildren wishing to get good grades.” In addition, the study we cited earlier was on helping women lose weight. It helps.</p>
<p>So it’s clear that this is a technique that is both effective and widely applicable. It has helped people reach a variety of goals; in addition, the studies were done in both the United States and Germany. So the methods work in a variety of contexts.</p>
<p>The final test is: Do they work for you?</p>
<p>Would you like to try it for one of your goals? Here is Oettingen’s description of how to do that:</p>
<p>“…Think of a wish. For a few minutes, imagine the wish coming true, letting your mind wander and drift where it will. Then shift gears. Spend a few more minutes imagining the obstacles that stand in the way of realizing your wish.”</p>
<p>It’s as simple as that. If you try it, let us know how it works for you. We will share the results with a lot of other people.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F12%2F05%2Fmental-contrasting-an-important-technique-for-reaching-your-goals%2F&amp;linkname=Mental%20Contrasting%3A%20An%20Important%20Technique%20for%20Reaching%20Your%20Goals." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>More Resilience Training Can Produce Richer, More Powerful Results.</title>
		<link>/2014/08/04/many-resilience-techniques-can-be-brief-and-easy-but-more-training-can-produce-richer-more-powerful-results/</link>
		<comments>/2014/08/04/many-resilience-techniques-can-be-brief-and-easy-but-more-training-can-produce-richer-more-powerful-results/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2014 18:55:57 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[How Hard Is It To Change Resilience?]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1709</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[We have often pointed out, maybe even emphasized, how easy it is to learn techniques that are helpful in resisting and recovering from stress. The techniques are not only easy, but are typically pleasant and comforting. Most resilience training methods &#8230; <a href="/2014/08/04/many-resilience-techniques-can-be-brief-and-easy-but-more-training-can-produce-richer-more-powerful-results/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We have often pointed out, maybe even emphasized, how <em>easy</em> it is to learn techniques that are helpful in resisting and recovering from stress.</p>
<p>The techniques are not only easy, but are typically pleasant and comforting. Most resilience training methods make you feel somewhere in the range of good to very good.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, too many people practice for a while, but then get embedded in the demands of ordinary life and never get to see how rich the benefits might be if they continued over the long term.</p>
<p>Take <a href="/2010/12/06/a-key-step-in-resilience-training-is-learning-deep-relaxation/">deep relaxation</a> as an example. A large majority of people who try basic methods of deep relaxation find the states they induce both useful and pleasant.</p>
<p>They should consider persisting at least a little longer. For some methods of relaxation and calming, there is evidence that practice can continue to improve, even over many years.</p>
<p>A striking example is the work of a Japanese researcher, Tomio Hirai. He studied changes in brain waves that take place when people practice Zen Meditation. (It is called “Zazen” and is essentially identical to the currently popular “Mindfulness Meditation”).</p>
<p><span id="more-1709"></span></p>
<p>Zazen involves sitting in a stable posture and attending to your breathing. The goal is to do that and nothing else.</p>
<p>Beginners count their inhalations and exhalations from one to ten; then they go back to one and start over again. If you try this for a while you will find yourself counting numbers like “42”, indicating that your mind has wandered without your noticing it. When this happens you just calmly go back to one.</p>
<p>As time goes on, brain wave patterns shift from fast to slow (an indication of calm, deep relaxation, the antithesis of a stress response, a “relaxation response”).</p>
<p>Hirai found that even after decades of practice meditators <a href="http://is.muni.cz/www/178816/EEG_and_Zazen.pdf">are still improving</a>.</p>
<p>But their commitment to meditation is not just to deal with life’s frustrations. As part of a Buddhist tradition, it is done to achieve some form of “enlightenment”, a profound and highly beneficial readjustment of their perceptions of themselves and of the world.</p>
<p>Zen masters recognize and accept that many people who practice Zazen, do so in order to function better in their ordinary lives. The term “<a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=KczYq22WAeYC&amp;pg=PA49&amp;lpg=PA49&amp;dq=bompu+zen&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=igVZJ2sn_3&amp;sig=7PRrXKcW1ep0fUHZCShYKcRc_cc&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=3rfdU_POGKLT8AGjvoCgCg&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CFIQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=bompu%20zen&amp;f=false">Bompu Zen</a>” is used for this more basic approach.</p>
<p>What resilience training normally aims to achieve is at the level of Bompu Zen. This does not meant that it is <em>merely</em> bompu Zen. We, for example, include the most effective techniques from a wide variety of traditions and other sources, as long as their effectiveness is robust enough to be empirically confirmed.</p>
<p>It appears that “the sky is the limit” when it comes to how far you can go with your training. Whether you reach for the sky depends on your ultimate goals. It depends on whether you seek a radically new perspective on the world and your life or just want to deal more effectively with life’s familiar demands, which is, incidentally, the humble goal we have chosen for this blog.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F08%2F04%2Fmany-resilience-techniques-can-be-brief-and-easy-but-more-training-can-produce-richer-more-powerful-results%2F&amp;linkname=Many%20Resilience%20Techniques%20Can%20Be%20%20Brief%20and%20Easy%2C%20but%20More%20Training%20Can%20Produce%20Richer%2C%20More%20Powerful%20Results." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2014/08/04/many-resilience-techniques-can-be-brief-and-easy-but-more-training-can-produce-richer-more-powerful-results/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>How Much Training Does It Take to Develop a Resilience Skill?</title>
		<link>/2014/07/15/how-much-training-does-it-take-to-develop-a-resilience-skill/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2014 20:03:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[How Hard Is It To Change Resilience?]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1685</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Our core purpose at OnResilience is to explain how and why you should train to be more resilient. We want to help people learn techniques that can help them get through difficult situations and come out able to at least &#8230; <a href="/2014/07/15/how-much-training-does-it-take-to-develop-a-resilience-skill/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Our core purpose at OnResilience is to explain how and why you should train to be more resilient. We want to help people learn techniques that can help them get through difficult situations and come out able to at least stay in the game, and maybe also having learned things that make them more effective in handling difficulties to come.</p>
<p>Debbie and I both know from published research, our own personal experiences, and our work as trainers and therapists that the techniques we teach will help most people to deal more effectively with painful, threatening situations .</p>
<p>A fortunate few can get benefits from just a few training sessions. But most people need more help, and, especially, more practice than that. However, it is safe to say that no one who neglects practice will reach their potential even if they are in the above-mentioned “fortunate few”.</p>
<p>Why do so many people fail to practice resilience-inducing procedures?</p>
<p>A possible reason is that people in technically advanced parts of the world have become accustomed to treatments that require little effort. Most of us have gotten prescriptions that quickly relieved us of distressing diseases, and we may tend now to expect a quick, almost effortless resolution to any of our problems. The old Alka-Seltzer line, “Relief is just a swallow away”, says it all.</p>
<p>That “take a pill” model is usually not a good one for making changes in the way the mind, or, if you prefer, the brain, influences the body. Nor does it work particularly well if we need to maneuver our way through complicated situations, such as a troubled marriage. In these situations, many factors influence what happens, and these factors may include some that can be influenced by chemicals, but we are far from having pills, injections, or surgical procedures that do much to turn complex situations from bad to good.</p>
<p>For the most part, neither can listening to a lecture or two, or practicing mind-body techniques a few times.</p>
<p>To get the most out of resilience training you need “practice, practice, and practice”.</p>
<p>But many, many people just do not see any room in their available <em>time</em> to fit practice in.</p>
<p><span id="more-1685"></span></p>
<p>Both Debbie and I have “been there and done that”.  We understand how hard it can be to find the time and energy to practice.</p>
<p>So, granting that we have to practice in order to see what resilience techniques can really do to make our lives better, <strong><em>how much</em></strong> practice is required?</p>
<p>Malcolm Gladwell in his best-selling book, “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Outliers-Story-Success-Malcolm-Gladwell/dp/0316017930/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1405436934&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=gladwell+outliers">Outliers</a>” concluded that mastering a skill requires practicing 10,000 times. Fortunately, in the video below, the speaker makes a case for 20 practice sessions as enough to reach the modest goals most of us set for ourselves.</p>
<p>Gladwell has been a brilliant commentator on life, but this encouraging video should help those of you who cannot fit that much practice into the stream of your life. It deals with people who, like most of us, are not aiming for goals that would make us world champions, but, rather for goals that make our lives better and, perhaps goals that make us stand out as notably good at what we are trying to do.</p>
<p>Watch the video for encouraging information on what you can gain from fairly modest effort.</p>
<p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/5MgBikgcWnY" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Sweet Talk versus Resilience Training.</title>
		<link>/2013/12/05/listening-to-sweet-talk-versus-resilience-training/</link>
		<comments>/2013/12/05/listening-to-sweet-talk-versus-resilience-training/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2013 04:06:54 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1551</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Debbie and I often discuss our concerns about the quality of research on resilience. But we are even more troubled by guidance from sources that make no distinction between advice based on well-established facts and advice that is based on &#8230; <a href="/2013/12/05/listening-to-sweet-talk-versus-resilience-training/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Debbie and I often discuss our concerns about the quality of research on resilience. But we are even more troubled by guidance from sources that make no distinction between advice based on well-established facts and advice that is based on mere opinion, advice that is merely “sweet talk”.</p>
<p>What is sweet talk? It’s hard to give it an air-tight definition, but you can recognize it if:</p>
<ul>
<li>It briefly makes you feel hopeful, but is soon forgotten.</li>
<li>It doesn’t give you a “recipe” for how you can implement its ideas or suggestions.</li>
<li>It is short on evidence that it will work. It may be empty claims, opinions (or even rehashes of other peoples’s opinions) that are only loosely based on evidence.</li>
<li>It doesn’t show you specific ways you can apply its suggestions to your own life.</li>
<li>It gives you little or no guidance about how to develop skills that make you more resilient.</li>
</ul>
<p><span id="more-1551"></span></p>
<p>Basically “sweet talk” creates the illusion that change is easy. It is almost entirely focused on gains while omitting a discussion of costs (that is, the planning and work you need to do to become more resilient).</p>
<p>Often, we find lists that tell you to do things like “be positive” or “be confident”.  The changes are desirable, but also can be hard to make. Often missing is an explanation of what you can do to make those changes.</p>
<p>Sweet talk feels good to hear, but may not be well-rooted in reality or have much effect on your resilience and your life.</p>
<p>The truth is that life is challenging. Life calls upon us to use and develop the gifts that we start with or that fall in our laps by luck. It also tempts us to avoid the effort needed to do what we must do to cultivate our full potential.</p>
<p>Admittedly, sweet talk sometimes helps. Sweet talk can be like the match that lights the fuse that sets off a powerful reaction. The energy and abilities are already there, but some sweet talk may help to activate them.</p>
<p>Sweet talk can give you the illusion that you have learned how to better your life without showing you how to do that.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F12%2F05%2Flistening-to-sweet-talk-versus-resilience-training%2F&amp;linkname=Listening%20to%20Sweet%20Talk%20versus%20Resilience%20Training." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2013/12/05/listening-to-sweet-talk-versus-resilience-training/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Does Secure Attachment to Others Lead to High Resilience?</title>
		<link>/2013/02/21/does-secure-attachment-to-others-lead-to-high-resilience/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2013 04:15:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[How Hard Is It To Change Resilience?]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1321</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[There is interesting research showing that how securely we attach to our caregivers as young children plays an important role in our resilience as adults. Children who develop a secure attachment to their mother (or other caregiver) tend, as adults, &#8230; <a href="/2013/02/21/does-secure-attachment-to-others-lead-to-high-resilience/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There is interesting research showing that how securely we attach to our caregivers as young children plays an important role in our resilience as adults. Children who develop a secure attachment to their mother (or other caregiver) tend, as adults, to be resilient in the face of challenges.</p>
<p>Does this mean that your level of resilience became a settled matter when you were little, and nothing can be done about it now? We don’t think so.</p>
<p><span id="more-1321"></span></p>
<p>Attachment style is developed in very early childhood, and has been extensively studied. Usually there are deemed to be three basic styles, Secure, Anxious-Ambivalent, and Avoidant. This attachment style developed in early childhood appears to stay with us throughout our lives.</p>
<p>Those who are “Secure”, apparently had a good fit between their inborn temperament and parental responses that enabled them to build inner resources. These inner resources enable them to connect well with others, and to feel confident in potentially scary, unfamiliar environments. Both the Anxious-Ambivalent and the Avoidant people are less effective in dealing with such environments.</p>
<p>Avoidant people appear to be comfortable without close relationships, and avoid dependency on others. This is viewed as a defense, and can, under enough distress, break down.</p>
<p>Avoidant people may seem to be secure unless the environment is too challenging, and under those circumstances, they can seem more like those who are Anxious-Ambivalent.</p>
<p>Anxious-Ambivalent people long for emotionally close relationships, but tend to feel uncomfortable with them. It is hard for them to trust or depend on others.</p>
<p>For our purposes here, we can look at those who are just “Secure” or “Non-Secure”.</p>
<p>Mario Mikulincer and Victor Florian have <a href="http://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=hWe5-aSgZmcC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA143&amp;dq=mikulincer+florian&amp;ots=zjtx_xOZK5&amp;sig=KVc2PtHo1ap0q86eXi5AyA9k3SU#v=onepage&amp;q=mikulincer%20florian&amp;f=false (">summarized the research on how Secures and Non-Secures react to a wide range of demanding circumstances</a>, and have consistently shown that Secures are more resilient than Non-Secures.</p>
<p>Their review includes studies of reactions to significant life challenges. Very consistently they indicate that Secures handle such challenges better than Non-Secures. Here are examples:</p>
<ul>
<li>In the military training, Anxious Ambivalents perceived more threat, felt a greater sense of personal inadequacy and helplessness in dealing with the training.</li>
<li>When facing the threat of death, Secures had less fear.</li>
<li>In time of war, when threatened with missile attacks, Secures sought more support from others and had fewer symptoms of post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD).</li>
<li>Prisoners of War who were Secures had fewer symptoms of PTSD than Non Secures.</li>
<li>Secures handled loss of significant others better than Non-Secures.</li>
<li>In experiments testing reactions to personal failure, Secures handled the failures better.</li>
<li>Women facing the challenges of new <strong>motherhood </strong>who were secure handled them better than non-secures.</li>
<li>Mothers with handicapped children dealt with the extra challenges better if they were Secures.</li>
<li>People coping with chronic pain who are secure react much more effectively than those who are insecure.</li>
</ul>
<p>So, here is more evidence that resilience helps us deal with life’s challenges. But, if attachment style is determined when we are no more than toddlers, doesn’t it seem we are either blessed or doomed by early experiences to be resilient or not?</p>
<p>One interesting fact in the work of Mikulincer and Florian provides considerable room for hope. In Israel, during the first Persian Gulf War, some people had to deal with Scuds missile attacks. They had to face the possibility of instant death, and had no personal control over the source of that threat.</p>
<p>Yet the less resilient people reacted the same way as those who were resilient. Why? Presumably because public service messages consistently told them to check on each other during and after the attacks. With these instructions, anxious ambivalent and avoidant people reacted by reaching out to others, just as secure people would likely have done without the instructions.</p>
<p>So mere instructions from the government were able to override the knee jerk reactions of insecures to either hem and haw (anxious-ambivalents) or deal with the threats solely on their own (avoidant).</p>
<p>We can reasonably expect that real resilience training can be even more effective than mere instructions.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F02%2F21%2Fdoes-secure-attachment-to-others-lead-to-high-resilience%2F&amp;linkname=Does%20Secure%20Attachment%20to%20Others%20Lead%20to%20High%20Resilience%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Some Ways to Manage Your Mind and Therefore to Manage Your Body</title>
		<link>/2012/11/14/some-ways-to-manage-your-mind-and-therefore-to-manage-your-body/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Nov 2012 17:59:31 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1278</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I want to discuss life changing lessons I have learned from people who taught me how to train the mind in a way that produces improvements I and others want and maybe even desperately need. The first of these people &#8230; <a href="/2012/11/14/some-ways-to-manage-your-mind-and-therefore-to-manage-your-body/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I want to discuss life changing lessons I have learned from people who taught me how to train the mind in a way that produces improvements I and others want and maybe even desperately need.</p>
<p>The first of these people is Theodore Xenophon Barber, known by people who were connected to him as “Ted”.</p>
<p>Ted was famous for publishing many papers, I think in the hundreds of them, which are widely viewed as somehow refuting hypnosis. His studies repeatedly showed that people who were asked to pretend that they were hypnotized could perform what were generally regarded as remarkable feats <strong><em>due to</em></strong> hypnosis, even though they were merely told to act <strong><em>as if</em></strong> they were hypnotized.</p>
<p>For example, a demonstration of the powers of hypnosis was (and probably still is) to show that a small woman could, under hypnosis, carry the weight of a heavy guy who sat on her stomach when her head was on one chair and her feet on another. This was a common feat of stage hypnosis.</p>
<p>Ted showed that small people who were only told to pretend they were hypnotized could also do this kind of feat.</p>
<p>This is a good lesson about how much we underestimate our capabilities. I think we could honestly say that there is an “epidemic of self-underestimation”.</p>
<p>If you attempt to do this at home, it might or might not work. We DO massively underestimate our abilities, but we also have to activate them in the right way. For example, the person bearing the weight has to have her (or his) upper body arranged so that the shoulders, not the head are on one of the chairs.</p>
<p>We do not want to give more details that might encourage people to try this on their own. That is not a good idea. We only want to illustrate that there is a bit of finesse required for it to work. The results are remarkable, even taking the “finesse” into account.  The need to finesse the details illustrates the important point that, to use your mind effectively, you need training in the details. In this case, without being adequately trained, you might end up with a neck injury.</p>
<p>I suppose you can see why Ted was seen as a person who had refuted hypnosis. He was saying that most of us ordinary people can do what are regarded as extraordinary feats due to hypnosis.</p>
<p><span id="more-1278"></span></p>
<p>When I first met Ted, I had already read a many of his books and papers; that is why I worked to arrange for him to give some lectures and training for the faculty and students at our Department of Psychology. Since I was the faculty member who had arranged for him to come, I was charged with picking him up at the airport.</p>
<p>On the way into town, he asked me what kind of work I do.</p>
<p>I said, “I am teaching people how to use mental imagery to help them maneuver through life”.  He responded, “Oh, you are also using hypnosis.”  I responded, “No, I just use things like guided imagery”.</p>
<p>We went through several rounds of this, and he finally said, “You will understand why I am calling what you do “hypnosis” after you attend my workshop.”</p>
<p>He was right. I now see that we are all hypnotized all of the time. All of us live in a “cultural trance” that is affirmed and strengthened by others in our culture.</p>
<p>His research had not refuted hypnosis; it had shown that what has been labeled “hypnosis” is an ordinary way that we all guide our minds, whether effectively or ineffectively. Many people guide their minds to make their lives miserable and ruin their health. That same mental power could as well make them happy and healthy.</p>
<p>In Ted’s training session he gave several demonstrations. For example, he asked us to rest an elbow on the desk in front of us (It was a college classroom), and then guided us into imagining that we had received an anesthetic injection. He asked to think and imagine with him as he suggested, step by step, what would happen if we had actually been anesthetized. The large majority of people in the audience experienced what he suggested.</p>
<p>We can call this “hypnosis”, but it is a natural ability we all have and use all the time. We can suggest to ourselves that “Life sucks”, that we are “useless”, or what have you. On the other hand we can think and imagine in ways that guide us to feeling that life is good and that we can make it better and better.</p>
<p>I think I first got a sense of what Ted’s research had taught him when I took him to lunch before we went to the University. At one point the waitress asked if we wanted anything else. He answered her with a look and tone that struck me as that of an enthusiastic child and said “Can I have some more milk?”</p>
<p>He had taught himself to get real joy out of simple things in life.</p>
<p>Later, in the training workshop, he talked about working with people who wanted to quit smoking. At first he did something that is common in our “cultural trance”, being negative and punitive.</p>
<p>He had his clients think and imagine the horrible consequences of smoking. He described taking a man step by step through imagining that he had a cough that didn’t go away, that he went to a doctor who, after some tests, told him he had lung cancer. He had him imagine the subsequent steps all the way to the client’s being in a coffin lowered into his grave as his young daughter sobbed and  said, “Daddy, if only you had quit smoking!”.</p>
<p>Well, that did not work.</p>
<p>Then he described what DID work. He suggested that people who were having trouble giving up cigarettes were depressed and did not know how to savor simple pleasures in life. Then he had them imagine and think about enjoying various aspects of life. One of them was the pleasure of drinking a beverage that they really liked.</p>
<p>Hearing him mention the example of enjoying a beverage, I thought of the way he asked for “more milk”. Then I knew he was telling us how he had learned to live an exuberant life.</p>
<p>Later, I will tell you some details of what Ted had discovered about effective ways to guide the mind in ways that work for you.</p>
<p>(<em>Edited by Debbie S. Sheridan)</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2012%2F11%2F14%2Fsome-ways-to-manage-your-mind-and-therefore-to-manage-your-body%2F&amp;linkname=Some%20Ways%20to%20Manage%20Your%20Mind%20and%20Therefore%20to%20Manage%20Your%20Body" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Self-Help Programs Must Acknowledge the Elephant in the Room.</title>
		<link>/2012/09/26/self-help-programs-must-acknowledge-the-elephant-in-the-room/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2012 17:03:33 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[How Hard Is It To Change Resilience?]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1157</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The often unmentioned elephant in the room for those of us who are promoting self-help is “How do we effectively help people to actually DO what we know will help them?” And to be frank, “How do we get ourselves &#8230; <a href="/2012/09/26/self-help-programs-must-acknowledge-the-elephant-in-the-room/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The often unmentioned elephant in the room for those of us who are promoting self-help is “How do we effectively help people to actually DO what we know will help them?” And to be frank, “How do we get <strong><em>ourselves</em></strong> to do what we know will lead to a better life?”</p>
<p>Harvard happiness guru, <a title="Shawn Achor" href="http://goodthinkinc.com/experts/shawn-achor/">Shawn Achor,</a> emphasizes that we need to make sure we have arranged to minimize the effort it takes to carry through on our decisions. We need to minimize the “activation energy’ required to get going.</p>
<p><span id="more-1157"></span></p>
<p>Achor uses his own failed effort to learn how to play the guitar to explain the use of activation energy. He kept his guitar in the closet, but never got around to taking it out to practice. He even timed how long it took to get the guitar out and sit down to practice. It was only 21 seconds!</p>
<p>So, he set things up so the guitar was no longer in the closet. He put it right where he couldn’t avoid contact with it. Result? He now plays the guitar.</p>
<p>Debbie and I have done a similar, though reversed, version of this. We usually eat a pretty low fat diet. With that kind of diet, it’s not unusual to get hungry before bedtime. We decided to include nuts in our diet. But once before we had tried an Atkins-like diet, and used peanuts as our snack. We decided to drop that diet, but kept on eating the peanuts. I, she, and our dog, Sam, all gained weight.</p>
<p>So now we put the nuts on a shelf in the basement. When we decide to eat them, we take a small container (designed to hold spices) downstairs and fill it. I think it probably takes less than a minute to get the nuts, but I don’t think we have ever gone back for a refill.</p>
<p>It strikes me as a quirk of the mind that manipulating such small expenditures of energy can have so much influence on what we do. One answer to the self-improvement’s elephant-in-the-room issue may lie in understanding these “quirks”. We will have more to say about this in our next post.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2012%2F09%2F26%2Fself-help-programs-must-acknowledge-the-elephant-in-the-room%2F&amp;linkname=Self-Help%20Programs%20Must%20Acknowledge%20the%20Elephant%20in%20the%20Room." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Here we go again! Is positivity really bad for you?</title>
		<link>/2012/08/23/here-we-go-again-is-positivity-really-bad-for-you/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 23 Aug 2012 03:08:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Harvard Grant Study]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1120</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In today’s post we will discuss a recent article, , “The Power of Negative Thinking”, published in the New York Times on August 4th. It would be reasonable to expect that anything that appears in the NYT is well-vetted, but &#8230; <a href="/2012/08/23/here-we-go-again-is-positivity-really-bad-for-you/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In today’s post we will discuss a recent article, , “The Power of Negative Thinking”, published in the New York Times on August 4th.</p>
<p>It would be reasonable to expect that anything that appears in the NYT is well-vetted, but you shouldn’t count on that. We read it regularly, and it often publishes articles that help us to think of timely new posts. Sometimes, though, they publish articles that just are not up to snuff.</p>
<p>The article, by Oliver Burkeman, begins by describing an event in which several people, apparently guided by the motivational speaker, Tony Robbins, attempted to walk barefoot over hot, burning coals. Twenty one of them had to be treated for burns. No big surprise for us.</p>
<p>Burkeman points out that physics tells us that “with quick, light steps, you’ll usually be fine”.  He goes on from that “lesson in physics” to turn the event into evidence against positivity.<span id="more-1120"></span></p>
<p>Well, there is overwhelming evidence that positivity helps us to flourish in life. With positivity we recover more quickly from surgery, perform better at work and in sports, are more successful in relationships, live longer, etc.</p>
<p>One would think that the “flagship” of newspapers in this country would require of its authors an awareness of at least a lot of this evidence, but apparently it does not. If you want to challenge the idea that positivity is good for people, why not include the body of serious research that supports this idea?</p>
<p>So, our first point is that this article shows no evidence of the author’s having reviewed the vetted, published literature on positivity and its outcomes.</p>
<p>Mr. Burkeman cites an article by Gabriele Oettingen, who is a real scientist, showing that people who were experimentally water-deprived and asked to picture a refreshing glass of water experienced a marked decline of energy levels compared to those who engaged in negative or neutral fantasies.</p>
<p>Anyone who has kept up with Dr. Oettingen’s research will understand that most of her work shows how effective positive imagining is when we contrast our future selves with and without taking constructive action designed for improvement. We routinely suggest this method to people who attend our workshops.</p>
<p>The body of Oettingen’s work demonstrates the effectiveness of positivity, not its ineffectiveness. It also points out important <span style="text-decoration: underline;">nuances</span> about how we can gain from positivity. So a second point is that the article has taken work out of context in a way that conceals the work&#8217;s overall significance. The nuances of positivity are missing.</p>
<p>Also the article lacks clarity about the definition of positivity. Living in a fantasy world is not the same as cultivating a life of positivity. It has long been known that mere fantasy is not likely to lead to success. George Vaillant in his <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Adaptation-Life-George-E-Vaillant/dp/0674004140">book on the Harvard Grant Study</a>, provides compelling evidence of that. Things like substituting fantasy for taking action to improve our lives and living in denial of the downside of our choices are not what research on positivity represents. Denial and fantasy have long been viewed as <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Defence_mechanism#Level_1_-_Pathological">immature or even pathological defense mechanism</a>, i.e. ways of fending off urges that are in conflict with our sense of self. Vaillant’s work shows that fantasy and denial are maladaptive.</p>
<p>Space limitations do not permit a more thorough analysis of the misconceptions in Burkeman’s article, but one, last point is that the author seems to assume that the cultivation of positivity entails the absence of negativity. Anyone who has read our last few posts will know that current evidence indicates that the needed ratio of positivity to negativity is around 3 positives to 1 negative, not 3 versus zero negatives.</p>
<p>Burkeman also cites Barbara Enrenreich’s grand rejection of positivity as authoritative. We have dealt with that in a <a href="/2010/12/18/is-optimism-really-toxic-5/">previous post</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
