<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Habits &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/habits/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>How to Develop Habits that Increase Resilience</title>
		<link>/2015/10/08/how-to-develop-habits-that-increase-resilience/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2015 16:34:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Habits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mental contrasting]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1989</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Ultimately, resilience training should result in new habits that make you more resistant to stress. We have pointed out a number of times that listening to a lecture or reading an article on coping with stress is not likely to &#8230; <a href="/2015/10/08/how-to-develop-habits-that-increase-resilience/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ultimately, resilience training should result in new habits that make you more resistant to stress.</p>
<p>We have pointed out a number of times that listening to a lecture or reading an article on coping with stress is not likely to be enough to result in more resilient habits. You may get useful information, maybe even inspiration, both of which can be valuable, but that is not enough to produce new habits.</p>
<p>Usually we recommend “practice, practice, practice”. We also described “<a href="/2014/12/07/mental-contrasting-an-important-technique-for-reaching-your-goals/">mental contrasting</a>”, a method that asks you to imagine yourself as you are now, and to alternate that with imagining yourself after you have developed a new resilience habit. This differs from a widely used method of simply imagining yourself as having achieved the desired goal. The latter method has proven to be ineffective.</p>
<p>Research shows that mental contrasting improves results. For example, see Amit Amin’s paper here. Details of how to practice mental contrasting were published in the Harvard Business Review<a href="https://hbr.org/2011/02/nine-things-successful-people"> here</a>.</p>
<p>We now have the concept of the habit loop, which can act as a guide on how to develop new habits. This model of habit change contrasts with a long familiar approach of just giving yourself rewards when you engage in the behavior you want to make habitual. Instead, it focuses heavily on turning attention to the cues or triggers that elicit the behavior.<span id="more-1989"></span> </p>
<p>The power of cues is striking. We had a friend (now deceased) who never smoked in front of his parents. For a long time, he could not quit smoking. But when he visited his parents, often for long periods, he told us that he never felt an urge to smoke. The cue or cues were missing, so the urge never appeared.</p>
<p>It is important to look for the cues that trigger your behaviors because, by manipulating the cues you can control habits.</p>
<p>It is also important to develop cues to trigger habits you are trying to develop. Shawn Achor provided a very good illustration of effectively developing <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Happiness-Advantage-Principles-Psychology-Performance/dp/0307591549/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1444256134&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=the+happiness+advantage">a cue to trigger practicing on his guitar.</a></p>
<p>Achor wanted to learn to play the guitar. At first he put the guitar in a closet. He could get it out in a matter of seconds. Yet, after some time he noted that he had not practiced guitar at all! So he took it out of the closet and placed it in the living room. Then, the guitar acted as a cue for him to practice, and soon he had developed a well-cued habit.</p>
<p>Several writers who wanted to develop a steady habit of exercising have put exercise clothing next to the bed. The clothing triggers a response of dressing for the workout and then doing it.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2015%2F10%2F07%2Fhow-to-develop-habits-that-increase-resilience%2F&amp;linkname=How%20to%20Develop%20Habits%20that%20Increase%20Resilience" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Path to Greater Resilience: From Attitudes to Skills and to Habits.</title>
		<link>/2015/09/09/the-path-to-greater-resilience-from-attitudes-to-skills-and-to-habits/</link>
		<comments>/2015/09/09/the-path-to-greater-resilience-from-attitudes-to-skills-and-to-habits/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2015 20:41:26 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Attitudes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Habits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1982</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[When we discussed the Sense of Coherence in our previous post, we said that it was a match for the first factor in our three factor model of resilience. In both popular culture (e.g. Rev. Normal Vincent Peale’s “The Power &#8230; <a href="/2015/09/09/the-path-to-greater-resilience-from-attitudes-to-skills-and-to-habits/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When we discussed the Sense of Coherence in our previous post, we said that it was a match for the first factor in our three factor model of resilience.</p>
<p>In both popular culture (e.g. Rev. Normal Vincent Peale’s “The Power of Positive Thinking” which had a huge impact in the United States and elsewhere) and scientifically developed theory (e.g. Barbara Frederickson’s book, “Positivity”), the value of positivity has been recognized as playing a major role in lives well-lived.</p>
<p>But we see a distinction between attitudes of positivity and positive skills that are closely connected to those attitudes.</p>
<p>Probably most people would predict that positive attitudes and thoughts are related to resilience. But having skills such as knowing ways to calm and soothe yourself when distressed have been given less attention. In addition, many of us possess the needed skills, but do not implement them.</p>
<p>Once we take the skills to the point where we actually implement them when they are needed, we have reached the third level of using resilience tools, the level of habit.</p>
<p>In sum, we have to go from attitudes to skills and on to habits.</p>
<p>Isn’t this a lot of work? It can be, but for the most part the process is very enjoyable, even exhilarating at times.</p>
<p>Do we need to say that we think you should give it a try?</p>
<p>If you decide to do that, <a href="/2014/12/22/prepare-for-your-later-life-by-accumulating-skills-and-habits-of-resilience/">this</a> and <a href="/2014/10/08/build-your-toughness-and-become-more-resilient/">this</a> will help get you started.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2015%2F09%2F09%2Fthe-path-to-greater-resilience-from-attitudes-to-skills-and-to-habits%2F&amp;linkname=The%20Path%20to%20Greater%20Resilience%3A%20From%20Attitudes%20to%20Skills%20and%20to%20Habits." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2015/09/09/the-path-to-greater-resilience-from-attitudes-to-skills-and-to-habits/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mental Contrasting: An Important Technique for Reaching Your Goals.</title>
		<link>/2014/12/07/mental-contrasting-an-important-technique-for-reaching-your-goals/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2014 22:02:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Habits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mental contrasting]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1785</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In this post we hope to show you the value of a technique called “mental contrasting”. We want to explain that concept, to cite evidence that mental contrasting really helps people change their habits to healthier and more productive ones, &#8230; <a href="/2014/12/07/mental-contrasting-an-important-technique-for-reaching-your-goals/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this post we hope to show you the value of a technique called “mental contrasting”. We want to explain that concept, to cite evidence that mental contrasting really helps people change their habits to healthier and more productive ones, and to tell you what you need to know in order to use it yourself.</p>
<p><span id="more-1785"></span></p>
<p>In an<a title="earlier post" href="/2010/12/06/getting-yourself-to-act-on-what-you-learn-about-building-resilience/"> earlier post </a>we discussed Gabrielle Oettingen’s method of “mental contrasting” as a way to keep yourself practicing resilience skills. If you want to build these skills and turn them into habits you have to practice. But it is hard to change habits, and we all have trouble getting ourselves to persist in habit-changing practices until we reach our goals.</p>
<p>Mental contrasting has a very credible basis to claim that it is an important technique to help us persist in needed practices.</p>
<p>An article written by Oettingen <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/10/26/opinion/sunday/the-problem-with-positive-thinking.html?_r=0">appeared in the October 24<sup>th</sup> New York Times</a>, and has been in our “to do” folder ever since. This week, we had a good opportunity to digest its content.</p>
<p>If you find a better summary of mental contrasting and its uses, please let us know. This one is excellent. It identifies research done on mental contrasting, showing that it helps “college students wanting a date, hip-replacement patients hoping to get back on their feet, graduate students looking for a job, (and) schoolchildren wishing to get good grades.” In addition, the study we cited earlier was on helping women lose weight. It helps.</p>
<p>So it’s clear that this is a technique that is both effective and widely applicable. It has helped people reach a variety of goals; in addition, the studies were done in both the United States and Germany. So the methods work in a variety of contexts.</p>
<p>The final test is: Do they work for you?</p>
<p>Would you like to try it for one of your goals? Here is Oettingen’s description of how to do that:</p>
<p>“…Think of a wish. For a few minutes, imagine the wish coming true, letting your mind wander and drift where it will. Then shift gears. Spend a few more minutes imagining the obstacles that stand in the way of realizing your wish.”</p>
<p>It’s as simple as that. If you try it, let us know how it works for you. We will share the results with a lot of other people.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F12%2F05%2Fmental-contrasting-an-important-technique-for-reaching-your-goals%2F&amp;linkname=Mental%20Contrasting%3A%20An%20Important%20Technique%20for%20Reaching%20Your%20Goals." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
