<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Resilience Skills &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/resilience-skills/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The Powers of the Mind 1</title>
		<link>/2016/06/01/the-powers-of-the-mind-1/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2016 18:53:11 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2082</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[There is a graph that has stayed alive in Jerry&#8217;s mind for decades. It was in a study designed to see what happens if a person is given gradual increases in the dosage of isoproterenol, a drug that imitates adrenaline, &#8230; <a href="/2016/06/01/the-powers-of-the-mind-1/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There is a graph that has stayed alive in Jerry&#8217;s mind for decades. It was in a study designed to see what happens if a person is given gradual increases in the dosage of isoproterenol, a drug that imitates adrenaline, the familiar &#8220;fight or flight&#8221; hormone. It is used primarily to deal with abnormally  slow and weak heartbeat  ( bradycardia), and heart block.</p>
<p>(Heart Block is an abnormal heart rhythm in which the heart beats too slowly. In this condition, the electrical signals that tell the heart to contract are blocked between the heart&#8217;s upper and lower chambers.)</p>
<p>The study appears to have been a routine one of the &#8220;dose-response curve&#8221;, to observe changes in heart rate as the dosage of the drug was gradually increased. Isoproterenol works by making changes in the junctions between the nervous system  and the heart muscle.</p>
<p>Not surprisingly, heart rate increased with each increment of the drug dosage, but there was one person whose heart followed the expected pattern as the dose was increased from zero to .1 on to .5 micrograms, but then began slowing down as the dose continued to be increased to 1.0, 2.0, and on to 4.0 micrograms.</p>
<p>The heart rate of the unusual person went from around 68 beats per minute (bpm) before any drug was given, to above 80 bpm at a dosage but then went down steadily to end up at around 53 bpm when the drug was at its top level. At this top dosage the other participants had a heart rate around 90 bpm.</p>
<p>What was going on? When the researchers asked the outlier that question, she said she had become bored and started meditating just before bher heart rate slowed down.</p>
<p>On occasion, there are reports of remarkable bodily control on the part of people who have devoted a great deal of their lives engaged in training that results in unusual control of mind over body. For example a Yogi, the Swami Rama was studied at the Menninger Clinic, and was able to make one part of his hand warm up while cooling a nearby part. He also showed that he could stop his heart from pumping while connected to an electronic device that measured his physiological reactions. This device would make it impossible to do any tricks to give an unreal impression of  bodily control.</p>
<p>If you want more detail on Swami Rama, the person who acted as his personal assistant in the  United States wrote a book, &#8220;Swami&#8221;, about him. It appears to be out of print, but inexpensive copies are available at Abebooks.com.</p>
<p>A lesson that we can take from such accomplishments is that regular practice of effective procedures such as meditation  can lead to our developing skills that enable us to gain remarkable control over our minds and bodies.</p>
<p>The woman who lowered her heart rate was able to challenge and defeat the biological system that underlies fight or flight. It is a system that also underlies &#8220;losing one&#8217;s temper&#8221; and even violent acts under some circumstances. It also underlies such things as stage fright, and a score of other things that we might want to bring under our control.</p>
<p>It is interesting to know that the woman who controlled her heart was self- trained. It is usually best to have a trainer, but some people can do well even on their own. The take-home message is that self-control is probably within your reach. The key is &#8220;practice, practice, practice&#8221;.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tips on Resilient Aging 3</title>
		<link>/2016/03/17/tips-on-resilient-aging-3/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2016 18:05:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Harvard Grant Study]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2041</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[&#160; (Note: we are dealing with a long chain of  technological failures, so this post was prepared on our iPad. Please forgive errors.) &#160; This is the third of a series of groundbreaking studies dealing with aging that we are &#8230; <a href="/2016/03/17/tips-on-resilient-aging-3/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>(Note: we are dealing with a long chain of  technological failures, so this post was prepared on our iPad. Please forgive errors.)</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>This is the third of a series of groundbreaking studies dealing with aging that we are covering in this blog-the Harvard Grant Study.</p>
<p>I For many decades there has been a study going on of characteristics leading to overall life success of Harvard students. To give you a sense of how long the study has been taking place, President John Kennedy was one of the undergraduates studied, and it is still going on.</p>
<p>The meaning of &#8220;overall life success&#8221; was borrowed from Freud, who defined it as the ability to love and to work, i.e. to develop stable loving relationships and a productive, satisfying career.</p>
<p>For many years, the head of the Grant Study was George Vaillant and he published &#8220;Adaptation to Life&#8221;, a very useful book for anyone interested in details on how others have lived happy, fruitful lives.</p>
<p>Vaillant described several adaptive styles that led to success. Here is a list of them:</p>
<p>1. Anticipation: being aware of future challenges and planning how you will avoid being blinded by them.<br />
2. Suppression: After doing what can be done about difficult circumstances, being able to put them aside and direct your attention to things that are in your control.<br />
3. Humor: People who used humor to help deal with stress did better than the humorless.<br />
4. Altruism: Taking the needs of others seriously, and letting them be important to you in the ways your own needs are important.<br />
5. Sublimation: Fulfilling unconscious yet unacceptable urges by putting your energy into doing something that is socially useful and acceptable that fulfills those urges. Two participants in the study illustrated this contrast. Both went hungry in their youth. One of them became determined to never be deprived again. The other sublimated his feelings by working<br />
for the US Department of Agriculture in the area of food aid.</p>
<p>How can you make use of this information?</p>
<p>Vaillant interpreted the studies within a Freudian framework. He saw these adaptive styles as &#8220;defense mechanisms&#8221;, which are ways we control our anxieties and keep undesirable desires out of our conscious awareness. Normally defense mechanisms are not seen as controllable by the conscious mind. Our purpose in this blog has never been to do psychotherapy,especially not depth therapy,like psychoanalysis,that attempts to uncover thoughts and feelings from the unconscious. Instead,we teach people to change their thoughts and habits,and even environments,to ones that help them do well in life. Looking at the five items in our list above, here are some ways to put some of them to use without venturing into depth psychology.</p>
<p>Anticipation</p>
<p>Anticipation is looking ahead, and planning for ways we might be able to get control of predictable stressors,then using the results of our planning to maximize good outcomes and minimize bad ones.</p>
<p>Try this: Imagine how you would like to be in the future(for example, six months or a year from now). Imagine the obstacles that might get in the way of your reaching your goals.Pick one of the barriers and plan ways to get past it. When opportunities arise to do this again, repeat with another barrier. Continue this until you can clearly imagine a reasonably smooth path to success.</p>
<p>Suppression:</p>
<p>Suppression is allowing yourself to be aware of your feelings without acting on them. An example of useful suppression: The idea that &#8220;I&#8217;ll cry tomorrow&#8221; allows you to be aware of your sadness, but also allows you to do what you need to do until the time is right for expressing the feeling.</p>
<p>Humor</p>
<p>A few decades ago, Norman Cousins, had a disease that his doctors could not cure. He decided to cure himself by watching films that made him laugh. He wrote a book about how this worked out, and felt it was quite successful.</p>
<p>The research literature on the healing effects of laughter, or of humor in general, despite having some evidence of such healing effects, does not lead to sound conclusions. However the use of laughter in common experiences lends support to the idea that laughter is beneficial. Laughter can engage us in ways that enable us to put aside painful thoughts, for a time even painful realities. In the meanwhile our resilience resources can replenish us and give us the stamina to settle the situation.</p>
<p>We need more and better research on various aspects of humor before reaching solid conclusions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Path to Greater Resilience: From Attitudes to Skills and to Habits.</title>
		<link>/2015/09/09/the-path-to-greater-resilience-from-attitudes-to-skills-and-to-habits/</link>
		<comments>/2015/09/09/the-path-to-greater-resilience-from-attitudes-to-skills-and-to-habits/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2015 20:41:26 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Attitudes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Habits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1982</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[When we discussed the Sense of Coherence in our previous post, we said that it was a match for the first factor in our three factor model of resilience. In both popular culture (e.g. Rev. Normal Vincent Peale’s “The Power &#8230; <a href="/2015/09/09/the-path-to-greater-resilience-from-attitudes-to-skills-and-to-habits/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When we discussed the Sense of Coherence in our previous post, we said that it was a match for the first factor in our three factor model of resilience.</p>
<p>In both popular culture (e.g. Rev. Normal Vincent Peale’s “The Power of Positive Thinking” which had a huge impact in the United States and elsewhere) and scientifically developed theory (e.g. Barbara Frederickson’s book, “Positivity”), the value of positivity has been recognized as playing a major role in lives well-lived.</p>
<p>But we see a distinction between attitudes of positivity and positive skills that are closely connected to those attitudes.</p>
<p>Probably most people would predict that positive attitudes and thoughts are related to resilience. But having skills such as knowing ways to calm and soothe yourself when distressed have been given less attention. In addition, many of us possess the needed skills, but do not implement them.</p>
<p>Once we take the skills to the point where we actually implement them when they are needed, we have reached the third level of using resilience tools, the level of habit.</p>
<p>In sum, we have to go from attitudes to skills and on to habits.</p>
<p>Isn’t this a lot of work? It can be, but for the most part the process is very enjoyable, even exhilarating at times.</p>
<p>Do we need to say that we think you should give it a try?</p>
<p>If you decide to do that, <a href="/2014/12/22/prepare-for-your-later-life-by-accumulating-skills-and-habits-of-resilience/">this</a> and <a href="/2014/10/08/build-your-toughness-and-become-more-resilient/">this</a> will help get you started.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2015%2F09%2F09%2Fthe-path-to-greater-resilience-from-attitudes-to-skills-and-to-habits%2F&amp;linkname=The%20Path%20to%20Greater%20Resilience%3A%20From%20Attitudes%20to%20Skills%20and%20to%20Habits." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2015/09/09/the-path-to-greater-resilience-from-attitudes-to-skills-and-to-habits/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>True Grit: a Remarkable Display of Resilience Guided by a Problem-Solving Attitude.</title>
		<link>/2015/03/02/true-grit-a-remarkable-display-of-resilience-guided-by-a-problem-solving-attitude/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 02 Mar 2015 22:55:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1843</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[A recent article in the New Yorker was written by Jonathan Kalb, who, after a period of unexplained, severe headache woke up unable to smile on one side of his face. His face on that side just drooped, though he &#8230; <a href="/2015/03/02/true-grit-a-remarkable-display-of-resilience-guided-by-a-problem-solving-attitude/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2015/01/12/give-smile">A recent article in the New Yorker</a> was written by Jonathan Kalb, who, after a period of unexplained, severe headache woke up unable to smile on one side of his face. His face on that side just drooped, though he seemed to have normal responses on the other side. He had experienced an attack of  “<a href="http://www.ninds.nih.gov/disorders/bells/detail_bells.htm#259373050">Bell’s Palsy</a>”</p>
<p>This kind of functional loss is particularly disturbing because it can distort the facial expression of emotions. Thus, it can impair the ability to interact with others.</p>
<p>In Kalb’s case, the problem was increased by his role as a journalist, whose job called for him to interact normally and to form a kind of bond with strangers.</p>
<p>Those symptoms could even influence his ability to maintain a normal relationship with his immediate family.</p>
<p>What if his wife had been put off by his distorted smile? What if his son was embarrassed by him?</p>
<p>You can see that he had plummeted into a threat to his normal family relationships as well as his job and his social interactions in general.</p>
<p>Yet, his article focuses not on his woes, but instead on how he continued his life despite the problem that had haphazardly come his way. In other words, it focuses on the tactics he used to respond with resilience.</p>
<p>All of us have, at times, faced blows that made our lives harder. So we have something in common with Mr. Kalb. We can learn to improve our own resilience by seeing how people with troubling challenges like his can respond successfully.</p>
<p>So what did he do?</p>
<p><span id="more-1843"></span></p>
<p>Kalb responded with an approach that suited his personality as well as with his life experience as one who gathered information. He applied something that must have been natural to him, a “problem-solving attitude”.</p>
<p>Our research has shown us that this attitude clusters with such things as hopefulness, optimism and persistence. Probably all of these contributed to the effective way in which he dealt with his problem.</p>
<p>To begin with, he learned as much as he could about the capacities he had lost and the ways in which others react to distortion of those capacities. One thing he learned was that people tend to be disturbed by the confusing mix of smile and frown that they might see on his face.</p>
<p>A frown is bad, but a confusing frown mixed with a smile is worse.</p>
<p>Fortunately, through his studies he also came to understand that, if others <strong><em>firs</em></strong>t saw parts of his face that signaled good will, this helped to control how they reacted when they saw the rest of his face later. This is the familiar power of first impressions. These early impressions tend to guide subsequent reactions by providing a template for them.</p>
<p>So at first he focused on limiting others’ view of his face to its functionally intact side.</p>
<p>His problem-solving attitude also led him to ask for help from his wife in keeping his frowning side away from others who were not yet acclimatized to his more welcoming side.</p>
<p>When going into social situations, he arranged for his wife to move to his “bad” side when he was meeting new people. Since this led him to look at her during his conversations, it prevented the new people from forming their first impressions based on looking at his impaired, frowning side, or a disorienting combination of the frowning and smiling sides.</p>
<p>Note that his wife’s help was crucial to his resilience. Resilience is not entirely internal to us as individuals. Other people are a crucial resource.</p>
<p>He even got help from his young son when he happened to be resting his chin on his hand in a way that led his son to say “Daddy, you just smiled!”  So he found out he had another way to keep the problematic facial expressions away and to start off with facial signals of warmth and positivity. He could just find inconspicuous ways to prop up the drooping side of his face.</p>
<p>You should read <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2015/01/12/give-smile">the original article</a> for more details of the tactics he used to keep him from losing his standing in the social world.</p>
<p>It seems very likely that, even in the full article, he is only discussing selected elements of his resilience tactics. He makes no mention of how he dealt with <strong><em>his emotional reactions</em></strong> to the symptoms. This has to have been a major part of his experience. It has to have been a frightening experience.</p>
<p>As regular readers of this blog will know, we identified <a href="/2011/01/11/the-three-core-factors-that-can-make-you-more-resilient/">three  different factors</a>  that underlie resilience. However, we are well aware that trying to build your resilience by changing too many of them at once is likely to overwhelm rather strengthen you.</p>
<p>Our view is that <a href="/2013/08/27/the-magic-of-small-changes/">small changes</a> can add up to result in large improvements.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2015%2F03%2F02%2Ftrue-grit-a-remarkable-display-of-resilience-guided-by-a-problem-solving-attitude%2F&amp;linkname=True%20Grit%3A%20a%20Remarkable%20Display%20of%20Resilience%20Guided%20by%20a%20Problem-Solving%20Attitude." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mental Contrasting: An Important Technique for Reaching Your Goals.</title>
		<link>/2014/12/07/mental-contrasting-an-important-technique-for-reaching-your-goals/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2014 22:02:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Habits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mental contrasting]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1785</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In this post we hope to show you the value of a technique called “mental contrasting”. We want to explain that concept, to cite evidence that mental contrasting really helps people change their habits to healthier and more productive ones, &#8230; <a href="/2014/12/07/mental-contrasting-an-important-technique-for-reaching-your-goals/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this post we hope to show you the value of a technique called “mental contrasting”. We want to explain that concept, to cite evidence that mental contrasting really helps people change their habits to healthier and more productive ones, and to tell you what you need to know in order to use it yourself.</p>
<p><span id="more-1785"></span></p>
<p>In an<a title="earlier post" href="/2010/12/06/getting-yourself-to-act-on-what-you-learn-about-building-resilience/"> earlier post </a>we discussed Gabrielle Oettingen’s method of “mental contrasting” as a way to keep yourself practicing resilience skills. If you want to build these skills and turn them into habits you have to practice. But it is hard to change habits, and we all have trouble getting ourselves to persist in habit-changing practices until we reach our goals.</p>
<p>Mental contrasting has a very credible basis to claim that it is an important technique to help us persist in needed practices.</p>
<p>An article written by Oettingen <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/10/26/opinion/sunday/the-problem-with-positive-thinking.html?_r=0">appeared in the October 24<sup>th</sup> New York Times</a>, and has been in our “to do” folder ever since. This week, we had a good opportunity to digest its content.</p>
<p>If you find a better summary of mental contrasting and its uses, please let us know. This one is excellent. It identifies research done on mental contrasting, showing that it helps “college students wanting a date, hip-replacement patients hoping to get back on their feet, graduate students looking for a job, (and) schoolchildren wishing to get good grades.” In addition, the study we cited earlier was on helping women lose weight. It helps.</p>
<p>So it’s clear that this is a technique that is both effective and widely applicable. It has helped people reach a variety of goals; in addition, the studies were done in both the United States and Germany. So the methods work in a variety of contexts.</p>
<p>The final test is: Do they work for you?</p>
<p>Would you like to try it for one of your goals? Here is Oettingen’s description of how to do that:</p>
<p>“…Think of a wish. For a few minutes, imagine the wish coming true, letting your mind wander and drift where it will. Then shift gears. Spend a few more minutes imagining the obstacles that stand in the way of realizing your wish.”</p>
<p>It’s as simple as that. If you try it, let us know how it works for you. We will share the results with a lot of other people.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F12%2F05%2Fmental-contrasting-an-important-technique-for-reaching-your-goals%2F&amp;linkname=Mental%20Contrasting%3A%20An%20Important%20Technique%20for%20Reaching%20Your%20Goals." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Reconsidering Your Initial View of Stressful Situations Can Help You Respond with Greater Resilience.</title>
		<link>/2014/11/20/reconsidering-your-initial-view-of-stressful-situations-can-help-you-respond-with-greater-resilience/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2014 05:17:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cognitive Reappraisal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1773</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Inevitably life confronts us with situations that are hard to handle. Sometimes our ability to handle them falls far short, and we are forced to go through a period in which we struggle and take some painful hits. If we &#8230; <a href="/2014/11/20/reconsidering-your-initial-view-of-stressful-situations-can-help-you-respond-with-greater-resilience/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Inevitably life confronts us with situations that are hard to handle. Sometimes our ability to handle them falls far short, and we are forced to go through a period in which we struggle and take some painful hits.</p>
<p>If we manage to get through such situations “in one piece”, we can be strengthened instead of being defeated.  When that happens, we have increased our resilience.</p>
<p>There are many different ways to come out on top of our struggles, or at least to keep them from utterly defeating us. If you take a quick trip through our 100+ posts in this blog, you will almost certainly find some that you can use as tools for getting through experiences you may encounter in the future.</p>
<p>A tool that has been occupying our attention lately is “Cognitive Reappraisal”.  It will be the central focus of this post.</p>
<p>What is cognitive reappraisal? It is a way to regulate our emotions. It calls on us to focus on finding alternative interpretations of what we are going through. This includes appraisals of the events that trigger our emotional reaction, the bodily responses that have been triggered, and of any other aspect of the total experience.</p>
<p><span id="more-1773"></span></p>
<p>To reappraise, we look for interpretations that shift us toward a more positive experience. For example, when having an experience that could be viewed as threatening we may have a hard time viewing it any other way. With reappraisal, we search for interpretations that help us see our situation as a challenge rather than a threat, and may even shift us from fear and hopelessness to excitement.</p>
<p>Cognitive reappraisal really works. Here are a few examples of its outcomes:</p>
<ul>
<li>It improves performance on difficult tasks, e.g. <a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022103109002200">taking high stakes tests</a> that can determine access to a good career.</li>
<li>It can enable you to <a href="http://www.wjh.harvard.edu/~nock/nocklab/Jamieson-2013.pdf">use the energy and power of your physiological responses to stress</a> into positive ones that are linked to excitement rather than fear or rage.</li>
<li>It can increase your <a href="http://rmkaplan.bol.ucla.edu/Robert_M._Kaplan/1983_publications_files/0071.pdf">ability to endure painful situations</a>, e.g. a painful medical procedure.</li>
</ul>
<p>Notice that these examples cover a wide range of situations.  We have no reason to think that reappraisal applies only to a few specific circumstances.</p>
<h3><strong>What, Specifically Do We Reappraise?</strong></h3>
<p>We can reappraise our interpretation of the stressful <strong><em>event</em></strong>.</p>
<p>This involves looking for appraisals that are more encouraging, helpful, and supportive.</p>
<p>How do you find these new interpretations?</p>
<ol>
<li>Simply consider alternative interpretations of what has happened. Try to come up with a list of several alternative ones.</li>
</ol>
<p>Often we are very convinced that our first interpretation is the one and only realistic one. There is good evidence human judgments are often wrong. Our minds are subject to many cognitive biases. Furthermore, being certain about our judgments has little to do with how accurate they are.</p>
<p>This is worth a try: Imagine someone with a different personality who tends to be more positive than you and think about how that person might interpret what happened.</p>
<ol>
<li>Realize that you can “contain” your reactions to stress.</li>
</ol>
<p>Being in a stressful, scary situation need not mean that the only option you have is to escape from that situation. Many stage performers get intensely anxious before doing a performance. Some, even some of the greatest performers, vomit from the anxiety. Yet they step right out on the stage and wow the audience.</p>
<p>You can have intense feelings and urges to flee, then breathe deeply and do what the situation requires by allowing the feelings to be there, and observing them, but not letting them to take over control of what you do.</p>
<ol>
<li>You can reappraise the meaning of your physiological reactions to the stressful situation.</li>
</ol>
<p>e.g. The “fight or flight” response is <strong><em>adaptive.</em></strong> This means it can <strong><em>help you</em></strong> function well in difficult situations by sending the right chemicals to your organs that help your body perform at its highest levels. What you experience while under stress is an amalgam of the body’s reactions and the interpretations you add to them.</p>
<p><strong><em>Mastering the art of interpretation is the key to turning negative responses to stress into positive ones.</em></strong></p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=&amp;linkname=Reconsidering%20Your%20Initial%20View%20of%20Stressful%20Situations%20Can%20Help%20You%20Respond%20with%20Greater%20Resilience." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>More Resilience Training Can Produce Richer, More Powerful Results.</title>
		<link>/2014/08/04/many-resilience-techniques-can-be-brief-and-easy-but-more-training-can-produce-richer-more-powerful-results/</link>
		<comments>/2014/08/04/many-resilience-techniques-can-be-brief-and-easy-but-more-training-can-produce-richer-more-powerful-results/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2014 18:55:57 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[How Hard Is It To Change Resilience?]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1709</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[We have often pointed out, maybe even emphasized, how easy it is to learn techniques that are helpful in resisting and recovering from stress. The techniques are not only easy, but are typically pleasant and comforting. Most resilience training methods &#8230; <a href="/2014/08/04/many-resilience-techniques-can-be-brief-and-easy-but-more-training-can-produce-richer-more-powerful-results/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We have often pointed out, maybe even emphasized, how <em>easy</em> it is to learn techniques that are helpful in resisting and recovering from stress.</p>
<p>The techniques are not only easy, but are typically pleasant and comforting. Most resilience training methods make you feel somewhere in the range of good to very good.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, too many people practice for a while, but then get embedded in the demands of ordinary life and never get to see how rich the benefits might be if they continued over the long term.</p>
<p>Take <a href="/2010/12/06/a-key-step-in-resilience-training-is-learning-deep-relaxation/">deep relaxation</a> as an example. A large majority of people who try basic methods of deep relaxation find the states they induce both useful and pleasant.</p>
<p>They should consider persisting at least a little longer. For some methods of relaxation and calming, there is evidence that practice can continue to improve, even over many years.</p>
<p>A striking example is the work of a Japanese researcher, Tomio Hirai. He studied changes in brain waves that take place when people practice Zen Meditation. (It is called “Zazen” and is essentially identical to the currently popular “Mindfulness Meditation”).</p>
<p><span id="more-1709"></span></p>
<p>Zazen involves sitting in a stable posture and attending to your breathing. The goal is to do that and nothing else.</p>
<p>Beginners count their inhalations and exhalations from one to ten; then they go back to one and start over again. If you try this for a while you will find yourself counting numbers like “42”, indicating that your mind has wandered without your noticing it. When this happens you just calmly go back to one.</p>
<p>As time goes on, brain wave patterns shift from fast to slow (an indication of calm, deep relaxation, the antithesis of a stress response, a “relaxation response”).</p>
<p>Hirai found that even after decades of practice meditators <a href="http://is.muni.cz/www/178816/EEG_and_Zazen.pdf">are still improving</a>.</p>
<p>But their commitment to meditation is not just to deal with life’s frustrations. As part of a Buddhist tradition, it is done to achieve some form of “enlightenment”, a profound and highly beneficial readjustment of their perceptions of themselves and of the world.</p>
<p>Zen masters recognize and accept that many people who practice Zazen, do so in order to function better in their ordinary lives. The term “<a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=KczYq22WAeYC&amp;pg=PA49&amp;lpg=PA49&amp;dq=bompu+zen&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=igVZJ2sn_3&amp;sig=7PRrXKcW1ep0fUHZCShYKcRc_cc&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=3rfdU_POGKLT8AGjvoCgCg&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CFIQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=bompu%20zen&amp;f=false">Bompu Zen</a>” is used for this more basic approach.</p>
<p>What resilience training normally aims to achieve is at the level of Bompu Zen. This does not meant that it is <em>merely</em> bompu Zen. We, for example, include the most effective techniques from a wide variety of traditions and other sources, as long as their effectiveness is robust enough to be empirically confirmed.</p>
<p>It appears that “the sky is the limit” when it comes to how far you can go with your training. Whether you reach for the sky depends on your ultimate goals. It depends on whether you seek a radically new perspective on the world and your life or just want to deal more effectively with life’s familiar demands, which is, incidentally, the humble goal we have chosen for this blog.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F08%2F04%2Fmany-resilience-techniques-can-be-brief-and-easy-but-more-training-can-produce-richer-more-powerful-results%2F&amp;linkname=Many%20Resilience%20Techniques%20Can%20Be%20%20Brief%20and%20Easy%2C%20but%20More%20Training%20Can%20Produce%20Richer%2C%20More%20Powerful%20Results." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2014/08/04/many-resilience-techniques-can-be-brief-and-easy-but-more-training-can-produce-richer-more-powerful-results/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>How Much Training Does It Take to Develop a Resilience Skill?</title>
		<link>/2014/07/15/how-much-training-does-it-take-to-develop-a-resilience-skill/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2014 20:03:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[How Hard Is It To Change Resilience?]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1685</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Our core purpose at OnResilience is to explain how and why you should train to be more resilient. We want to help people learn techniques that can help them get through difficult situations and come out able to at least &#8230; <a href="/2014/07/15/how-much-training-does-it-take-to-develop-a-resilience-skill/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Our core purpose at OnResilience is to explain how and why you should train to be more resilient. We want to help people learn techniques that can help them get through difficult situations and come out able to at least stay in the game, and maybe also having learned things that make them more effective in handling difficulties to come.</p>
<p>Debbie and I both know from published research, our own personal experiences, and our work as trainers and therapists that the techniques we teach will help most people to deal more effectively with painful, threatening situations .</p>
<p>A fortunate few can get benefits from just a few training sessions. But most people need more help, and, especially, more practice than that. However, it is safe to say that no one who neglects practice will reach their potential even if they are in the above-mentioned “fortunate few”.</p>
<p>Why do so many people fail to practice resilience-inducing procedures?</p>
<p>A possible reason is that people in technically advanced parts of the world have become accustomed to treatments that require little effort. Most of us have gotten prescriptions that quickly relieved us of distressing diseases, and we may tend now to expect a quick, almost effortless resolution to any of our problems. The old Alka-Seltzer line, “Relief is just a swallow away”, says it all.</p>
<p>That “take a pill” model is usually not a good one for making changes in the way the mind, or, if you prefer, the brain, influences the body. Nor does it work particularly well if we need to maneuver our way through complicated situations, such as a troubled marriage. In these situations, many factors influence what happens, and these factors may include some that can be influenced by chemicals, but we are far from having pills, injections, or surgical procedures that do much to turn complex situations from bad to good.</p>
<p>For the most part, neither can listening to a lecture or two, or practicing mind-body techniques a few times.</p>
<p>To get the most out of resilience training you need “practice, practice, and practice”.</p>
<p>But many, many people just do not see any room in their available <em>time</em> to fit practice in.</p>
<p><span id="more-1685"></span></p>
<p>Both Debbie and I have “been there and done that”.  We understand how hard it can be to find the time and energy to practice.</p>
<p>So, granting that we have to practice in order to see what resilience techniques can really do to make our lives better, <strong><em>how much</em></strong> practice is required?</p>
<p>Malcolm Gladwell in his best-selling book, “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Outliers-Story-Success-Malcolm-Gladwell/dp/0316017930/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1405436934&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=gladwell+outliers">Outliers</a>” concluded that mastering a skill requires practicing 10,000 times. Fortunately, in the video below, the speaker makes a case for 20 practice sessions as enough to reach the modest goals most of us set for ourselves.</p>
<p>Gladwell has been a brilliant commentator on life, but this encouraging video should help those of you who cannot fit that much practice into the stream of your life. It deals with people who, like most of us, are not aiming for goals that would make us world champions, but, rather for goals that make our lives better and, perhaps goals that make us stand out as notably good at what we are trying to do.</p>
<p>Watch the video for encouraging information on what you can gain from fairly modest effort.</p>
<p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/5MgBikgcWnY" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Facing Situations That You May Not Be Able to Handle? Develop a Problem Solving Attitude.</title>
		<link>/2014/06/25/facing-situations-that-you-may-not-be-able-to-handle-develop-a-problem-solving-attitude/</link>
		<comments>/2014/06/25/facing-situations-that-you-may-not-be-able-to-handle-develop-a-problem-solving-attitude/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2014 18:30:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Benefits of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1667</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Having a “problem solving attitude” is an important influence on resilience. This attitude is a form of positivity, which is a well-known key to resilience. It is a facet of the first and most influential factor influencing resilience. It is &#8230; <a href="/2014/06/25/facing-situations-that-you-may-not-be-able-to-handle-develop-a-problem-solving-attitude/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Having a “problem solving attitude” is an important influence on resilience. This attitude is a form of positivity, which is a well-known key to resilience. It is a facet of the <a href="/2011/01/11/the-three-core-factors-that-can-make-you-more-resilient/">first and most influential factor influencing resilience</a>. It is linked to “positivity”, which is a key to resilience.</p>
<p>What, exactly is a “problem-solving attitude”? The best way to explain this is to describe what people with this attitude are likely to believe about life’s challenges.</p>
<p>People with this kind of attitude tend to react to mistakes by trying to figure out how to avoid them in the future.</p>
<p>You might say, “Isn’t that what everybody does?”</p>
<p><span id="more-1667"></span></p>
<p>No! It is very common for people to spend much more time looking for who is to blame for what happened, and, in particular, trying to convince themselves and others that nothing they did contributed to the bad outcome. That results in learning nothing about how to make things better.</p>
<p>Are there steps you can take to improve your problem solving attitude?</p>
<p>One thing you should do when faced with difficult situations is mentally take a step back and review the nature of the problem. Too often people jump into active attempts to solve a problem without first reviewing the details of the situation that are giving rise to the problem.</p>
<p>A good example is how people react when their computer or mobile device will not respond the way it should. It is all too common to become frustrated and angry, maybe muttering expletives while quickly trying out various solutions without really thinking through what is likely to work. Muttering expletives doesn’t repair electronic equipment.</p>
<p>It’s best to settle down and think through the nature of the problem and then select a few potential solutions to try out. Then try them out, being sure to keep track of what you are trying and of the results.</p>
<p>Don’t start telling yourself how bad it will be if you fail to come up with a quick solution. The problem is likely to be less consequential than it seems when you are immersed in it. As Nobel Prize winning psychologist, Daniel Kahneman said “Nothing in life is as important as you think it is, while you are thinking about it”.</p>
<p>Emphasize that this is a <em>problem</em> to be <em>solved</em> and there may well be many solutions. Do not fall into the trap of thinking the problem simply cannot be solved.</p>
<p>Think of the centuries in which people insisted that it was impossible for humans to fly. Then the Wright brothers built their flying machine and then, over the next several years developed it into a stable way of flying. After that, many more ways of flying came to light.</p>
<p>One thing you should train yourself <strong><em>not </em></strong>to do is focus on criticizing yourself for making mistakes. If you do that, it is likely to engulf you, leaving little or no mental space for thinking about how to make things better. Attacking yourself is a matter of changing the subject from how to solve the problem to a mental discussion of your worth. At that point, you stop problem solving.</p>
<p>Avoid being one of the many people who actually <em>insist on hopelessness</em>. The last thing you should do is adopt any resilience-draining approach of quickly deciding that nothing can be done to improve results. That is the path of hopelessness.</p>
<p>You don’t have to be a baseball fan to appreciate the following story:</p>
<p>In his book “The Mental ABC’s of Pitching: A Handbook for Performance Enhancement”, Major League pitching coach and sports psychologist, Harvey Dorfman, provided a clarifying example of how easy it may be to succeed if you just focus your mind on looking for solutions.</p>
<p>He describes an encounter with a pitcher, Steve Mura, who had spent six seasons in the Major Leagues and won 12 games for the 1983 Cardinals He was the starting pitcher for that night’s game.</p>
<p>Dorfman was chatting with him, and Mura shook his head silently. When asked what that was about, he said, “I can never win on this mound.” In the ensuing discussion, Dorfman told Mura, “There is a difference between, ‘I have not won and I cannot win’.” After all, there are many things we accomplish for the first time. Otherwise there would be no such thing as breaking one’s personal record.</p>
<p>Dorfman was already guiding Mura toward a problem solving approach by disabusing him of the illusion that past failures <strong><em>must</em></strong> continue forever. Can you see what a silly idea that is? To start with, how many things in life, whether good or bad, last forever?</p>
<p>When questioned further, Mura complained about the height and slope of the pitching mound. Dorfman asked him what kind of adjustments he could make to deal with that. Mura thought it over and came up with a strategy. He had never thought that way before. Instead he had spent his energy telling himself that he couldn’t win in that ballpark.</p>
<p>Mura pitched seven innings that night and gave up only two runs on hits. For those of you who don’t understand baseball, that is a very respectable performance.</p>
<p>Mura began in a state of pessimism and hopelessness. He wasn’t even applying the power of his mind to find solutions. As Dorfman pointed out, why should anyone think about solving the problem if failure is foreordained? And if they do not even begin problem solving, they obviously cannot persist in finding a way to succeed.</p>
<p>Once Mura shifted from pessimism and hopelessness to a problem-solving mode, it took only a few minutes to develop a plan of adjustments that led to success.</p>
<p>We are not saying that it will always be that easy, but you are much more likely to find solutions if you invest your energy in looking for them</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=&amp;linkname=Facing%20Situations%20That%20You%20May%20Not%20Be%20Able%20to%20Handle%3F%20Develop%20a%20Problem%20Solving%20Attitude." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2014/06/25/facing-situations-that-you-may-not-be-able-to-handle-develop-a-problem-solving-attitude/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Stop Doing Things That Make You More Vulnerable and Less Resilient</title>
		<link>/2014/04/30/stop-doing-things-that-make-you-more-vulnerable-and-less-resilient/</link>
		<comments>/2014/04/30/stop-doing-things-that-make-you-more-vulnerable-and-less-resilient/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2014 16:58:24 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1641</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Are you doing things that impair your resilience? Here are some things that can reduce resilience. Don’t develop skills that enable you to sooth, calm, and comfort yourself. (Many, if not most, of our posts on this blog explain what &#8230; <a href="/2014/04/30/stop-doing-things-that-make-you-more-vulnerable-and-less-resilient/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Are you doing things that <strong><em>impair</em></strong> your resilience? Here are some things that can reduce resilience.</p>
<ol start="1">
<li>Don’t develop skills that enable you to sooth, calm, and comfort yourself. (Many, if not most, of <a href="/category/self-soothing/">our posts</a> on this blog explain what those skills are and how to develop them.) The basic ones are very easy to learn.</li>
<li>Don’t fail to apply your resilience skills when they are needed. (You know, “too busy”, “too tired”, “I’ll do this tomorrow”). Here are <a href="/2010/12/06/getting-yourself-to-act-on-what-you-learn-about-building-resilience/">some methods</a> that can help you to get past those excuses and really use the resilience skills that you have.</li>
<li>Don’t underestimate the importance of other people to increasing your resilience (not to mention your health and your success!). For example, be aware of what you may lose by directing your anger and frustration toward supporters. Dumping your distress on supportive others may tempt them to give up or even direct spite at you. For your own sake, you should guide and encourage them. Let them know how they can help, and even give them pep talks.</li>
<li>Don’t do things that increase your distress. For example, inwardly talking to yourself in ways that pump up your anger at people you see as having treated you unfairly. Or selling yourself on the idea that things that distress you make you a helpless victim, who lacks any control over her/his reactions.</li>
<li>Don’t numb your distressed feelings with alcohol or other drugs without even trying to find ways to control your own reactions with skills instead of chemicals.</li>
<li>Don’t allow your routine life to become chaotic without developing at least a few predictable routines. Simplifying your life makes it easier to cope with potentially distressing situations that inevitably come by.</li>
</ol>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>In Contrast, Here Is How Resilient People See It and Do It.</p>
<ul>
<li>I frequently take good care of, calm, and comfort myself.</li>
<li>My typical reaction to a bad situation is to think and do things that make me feel calmer and better.</li>
<li>I know some things I can do to make me feel better when I am upset, and I usually do those things when I am under stress.</li>
<li>I have many predictable routines in my life that give me comfort.</li>
<li>I know that people who try to help me through hard times need some encouragement, and I do my best to give it to them.</li>
<li>I often get to enjoy myself.</li>
<li>I have learned enough about self-calming and self-soothing to recover from challenges by the time I face the difficulties of the next day.</li>
</ul>
<p>To use an already overused saying “Rome wasn’t built in a day”. If things have gotten out of control for you, you will have to take toddler steps toward shifting to a more resilient way of living. Why not work toward developing skills and routines that help make your life less stressful and more successful?</p>
<p>And for heaven’s sake don’t lead with your chin and do things that turn up the intensity of your stress.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F04%2F30%2Fstop-doing-things-that-make-you-more-vulnerable-and-less-resilient%2F&amp;linkname=Stop%20Doing%20Things%20That%20Make%20You%20More%20Vulnerable%20and%20Less%20Resilient" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2014/04/30/stop-doing-things-that-make-you-more-vulnerable-and-less-resilient/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
