<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Mindfulness &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/mindfulness/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Why Not Put Meditation Through the Ultimate Test? Try It Out!</title>
		<link>/2015/03/23/why-not-put-meditation-through-the-ultimate-test-try-it-out/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 18:23:36 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Mantra Meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mindfulness]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1859</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Prior to the 1960s claims about psychological and, especially physical improvements from mind training practices, got about as much serious attention as claims that the earth is actually flat. A variety of influences encouraged those who are scientifically oriented to &#8230; <a href="/2015/03/23/why-not-put-meditation-through-the-ultimate-test-try-it-out/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Prior to the 1960s claims about psychological and, especially physical improvements from mind training practices, got about as much serious attention as claims that the earth is actually flat.</p>
<p>A variety of influences encouraged those who are scientifically oriented to take a second look at these techniques. A very significant shift in readiness to take them seriously resulted from the work of Herbert Benson, a senior cardiologist at Harvard’s Medical School.</p>
<p>His work was presumably stimulated by popular demand, stemming from such things as the wildly popular Beatles’ taking up “Transcendental Meditation”, a very well packaged program centered on an ancient method of “Mantra Meditation”.</p>
<p>In a nutshell, Benson confirmed that mantra meditation induced something he called the “relaxation response”. This was a clear and simple label for a complex pattern of physiological replenishment responses along with corollary psychological feelings of calm and relaxation.</p>
<p>The mind-body pattern was familiar to the few people who understood how our nervous systems respond when we are distressed versus when we are comfortable and calm. The pattern was based on activity in a number of neural systems that can only be understood after much study of neurophysiology.</p>
<p>So his simply calling their effects as “the relaxation response” was pure genius. It focuses on a central benefit of controlling those neurophysiological and corollary psychological reactions without getting bogged down in technical details a person doesn’t need to know in order to get the systems under control.</p>
<p>(What is Mantra Meditation, and how can you learn how to do it? To get our answers to these questions, click <a href="/2014/01/15/a-simple-way-to-sooth-and-comfort-yourself/">here</a>).</p>
<p>There are many types of meditation, and, in our experience, which one is seen as best seems to depend as much on the person trying to use it as on the meditation method itself.</p>
<p>Though mantra meditation is widely used, the current star of the show in our part of the world is mindfulness meditation. We have described how to engage in this practice <a href="/2011/03/02/basic-mindfulness-technique/">here</a>. The method we describe is an ancient one which has shown its usefulness over thousands of years.</p>
<p>We did a Google search to find out how well the effectiveness of mindfulness is supported by good research. For this kind of search, we use Google Scholar, which emphasizes research that has been reported in journals that are attentive to scientific standards of evidence. If you do an ordinary search, you may get as many sales pitches as scientific findings.</p>
<p><span id="more-1859"></span></p>
<p>This is a quick summary of what we found:</p>
<ul>
<li>Research is generally based on meditation techniques that are at quite a distance from traditional mindfulness meditation, typically blended with various procedures that are used in cognitive behavior therapy.</li>
<li>Standards of research design are not great, but they tend to support the idea that this meditation, on average, has some important positive effects in helping people deal with a wide range of different challenges.</li>
<li>A good way to describe this state of affairs is to say that mindfulness is <strong><em>robust in its positive effects</em></strong>. This seems to be about as much as we can expect in a world that is not likely to offer ideal levels of precision.</li>
</ul>
<p>Unless your goal is to publish your findings, the ultimate test of a technique is to find out whether it helps <strong><em>you</em></strong> with <strong><em>your</em></strong> current standards of what is worth the effort. Only you can be the judge of that, once you try it out.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=&amp;linkname=" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Can We Make Ourselves Biologically Younger?</title>
		<link>/2013/10/17/can-we-make-ourselves-biologically-younger/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2013 05:47:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Benefits of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mindfulness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience and Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1516</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Some years ago we became aware of the important role of telomeres in aging, and the role of stress in speeding up the aging process. Telomeres are genetic components that are linked to biological aging. Usually, the older you are &#8230; <a href="/2013/10/17/can-we-make-ourselves-biologically-younger/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Some years ago we became aware of the important role of telomeres in aging, and the role of stress in speeding up the aging process. Telomeres are genetic components that are linked to biological aging. Usually, the older you are the shorter your telomeres become.</p>
<p>What did this have to do with resilience? Well, resilience controls stress, and it turns out that higher levels of stress result in increased shortening of telomeres. So your calendar age is not the only determinant of how old your cells are. Stress is a highly significant influence.</p>
<p>In fact, women who reported being highly stressed were biologically, as indexed by telomere length, about ten years older than those who did not report high stress.</p>
<p>In one of our early resilience workshops, one person in the group asked an obvious question that hadn’t occurred to us. “Is there anything that can enable us to <strong><em>lengthen</em></strong> our telomeres?&#8221; We paused, and had to say that we did not know.</p>
<p>Since that time, a good deal of research has shown that we can indeed lengthen our telomeres through lifestyle changes.</p>
<p>We were working on our usual exhaustive examination of the scientifically respectable evidence that people can lengthen their telomeres when we discovered the following interview of Dr. Dean Ornish, who recently completed a study on how the telomeres can be lengthened. We decided to re-post his video, which does a very good job of explaining what we need to do to lengthen our telomeres. We weren&#8217;t likely to improve, in a short post, on what he says in this interview. And it isn&#8217;t just a promotion of his own work; he talks about a wide range or research pointing in the same direction as his.</p>
<p><iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/QPpJU8Je-lE" frameborder="0" width="420" height="315"></iframe></p>
<p>It appears that telomeres can indeed be lengthened, and that well established healthy lifestyle changes can produce the lengthening.</p>
<p>Naturally attempts are being made to develop a kind of &#8220;Fountain of Youth&#8221; pill that can lengthen telomeres. We would recommend that such pills be viewed with great caution. It&#8217;s one thing to do things we already know are good for you and thus lengthen telomeres and quite another to take a new pill that needs lengthy testing.</p>
<p>As we have pointed out previously in this blog, the body is a highly complex, interactive ecosystem. Change one thing and many other unpredictable changes are likely to occur. The enzyme, telomerase stimulates growth of telomeres. But there is a lot of telomerase in certain malignant tumors. So who can say what kinds of side effects might result from artificial tampering?</p>
<p>On the other hand, sensible exercise, eating a healthy diet, learning to live peacefully with others, and calming ourselves through meditation have been around for centuries, and we know that their side effects improve lives</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F10%2F17%2Fcan-we-make-ourselves-biologically-younger%2F&amp;linkname=Can%20We%20Make%20Ourselves%20Biologically%20Younger%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Depressed, Anxious, Being Hard on Yourself? New Insights about the Value of Learning to Be both Self-Compassionate and Self-Soothing.</title>
		<link>/2012/02/16/depressed-anxious-being-hard-on-yourself-new-insights-about-the-value-of-learning-to-be-both-self-compassionate-and-self-soothing/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2012 04:10:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Self-Criticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mindfulness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Physical Contact]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Compassion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=956</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Most of us are aware that we have an inner critic that can make it hard to enjoy life, and, in the more severe instances, induce such things as anxiety and depression. We have written several posts about the inner &#8230; <a href="/2012/02/16/depressed-anxious-being-hard-on-yourself-new-insights-about-the-value-of-learning-to-be-both-self-compassionate-and-self-soothing/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Most of us are aware that we have an inner critic that can make it hard to enjoy life, and, in the more severe instances, induce such things as anxiety and depression.</p>
<p>We have written several posts about the inner critic and how to deal with it through changing your inner self-talk.</p>
<p>We have also encouraged the use of <em>mindfulness meditation. </em>With mindfulness we observe the flow of our experiences with compassion and acceptance, the opposite of self-criticism.</p>
<p>This post is about an important new insight into what it may take to stop unhelpful self-criticism. It involves learning to be compassionate toward the inner critic, which is, after all, an aspect of ourselves. This means to understand that the self-criticism is something you learned in order to adapt to the environment in which you grew up.</p>
<p>In addition we must also learn ways to sooth ourselves.</p>
<p><span id="more-956"></span></p>
<p>According to British psychologist, <a href="http://www.compassionatemind.co.uk/resources/Compassion_Group_Therapy_Paper.pdf">Paul Gilbert</a>, besides reducing the critical self-talk, we need to shift from feelings of “self-directed hostility, contempt, and self-loathing” to   “feelings of self-reassurance, warmth, and self-soothing”.</p>
<p>“Some high self-critics could understand the logic of CBT and generate alternative thoughts to self-criticism but rarely felt reassured by such efforts”.  (CBT is cognitive behavior therapy; a self-help version can be found <a href="../../../../../2011/02/20/to-increase-your-resilience-avoid-being-too-hard-on-yourself/">here</a>.)</p>
<p>In his view, besides changing our self-talk, many of us need to learn ways to sooth ourselves, and thus to experience the warm feelings that accompany self-compassion and self-soothing.</p>
<p>But how do we do that?  Check out our post on “<a href="../../../../../2010/11/04/natural-stress-defeaters/">Natural Stress Defeaters</a>” for some simple methods of self-soothing that have worked for others, and that you can easily bring into your own life. Also <a href="../../../../../2010/12/06/a-key-step-in-resilience-training-is-learning-deep-relaxation/">deep relaxation</a> produces feelings of relaxation and warmth, and it, too, is easy to fit into your life. The previous link has a free audio that is designed to help you to feel warmer and more at peace.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.compassionatemind.co.uk/8.html">Dr. Gilbert</a> provides many mental exercises crafted to induce the desired feelings of warmth and peacefulness. They can be found in his book “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Compassionate-Mind-Approach-Lifes-Challenges/dp/1572248408/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1329364432&amp;sr=1-1">The Compassionate Mind</a>”.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2012%2F02%2F16%2Fdepressed-anxious-being-hard-on-yourself-new-insights-about-the-value-of-learning-to-be-both-self-compassionate-and-self-soothing%2F&amp;linkname=Depressed%2C%20Anxious%2C%20Being%20Hard%20on%20Yourself%3F%20New%20Insights%20about%20the%20Value%20of%20Learning%20to%20Be%20both%20Self-Compassionate%20and%20Self-Soothing." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sleeplessness: Should You Medicate of Meditate?</title>
		<link>/2011/11/15/sleeplessness-should-you-medicate-of-meditate/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2011 16:28:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Perfectionism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Self-Criticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mindfulness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Understanding]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Women's Resilience]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=858</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I think it is safe to say that a large majority of us gravely underestimate the powers of our minds and overestimate the powers of medicine. Whether your problem is sleeplessness, pain or some other potentially overwhelming challenge, your mind, &#8230; <a href="/2011/11/15/sleeplessness-should-you-medicate-of-meditate/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think it is safe to say that a large majority of us gravely underestimate the powers of our minds and overestimate the powers of medicine. Whether your problem is sleeplessness, pain or some other potentially overwhelming challenge, your mind, especially if you train and develop its powers, can work wonders in corralling and controlling your problem.</p>
<p>Fortunately the title of this post implies a false dichotomy. Why not meditate AND medicate? Why not do what you can to control your problem by training your mind and then minimize the use of medical interventions.</p>
<p>Why should you take the trouble to train your mind? Well, the human body is a complex ecosystem. Every attempt to control such a system by tampering with its inner workings triggers an avalanche of unpredictable results. Our body’s complexity makes it subject to what has been called “<a href="http://www.imho.com/grae/chaos/chaos.html">the butterfly effect</a>”.  The butterfly effect refers to the fact that the tiny effect of a butterfly flapping its wings in China may change the weather in, say, Los Angeles. (Click the link above for a more detailed explanation.)</p>
<p>This effect implies that complex systems can be heavily influenced by tiny variations in factors that scientists would usually see as negligible. The butterfly effect clarifies why all medicines have “side effects”, and also why It is wise to minimize the risks of putting alien substances into our bodies.</p>
<p>In light of this, I had a strong reaction to a recent article in the New York Times <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/06/fashion/mothers-and-sleep-medication.html?_r=2&amp;src=rechp">referring to sleep medications as “mother’s little helper”.</a></p>
<p>There are useful non-medical ways to deal with sleeplessness and they can powerfully improve the effects of medical treatment while minimizing the risks entailed in taking medication. For example most of the sleepless mothers described in the New York Times article could not sleep because they were obsessively ruminating over tasks that needed to be done.</p>
<p>Meditation can help reduce such rumination. While meditating you deal with mental distractions by gently and compassionately returning your mind to the object on which you are meditating.</p>
<p>Think of it in terms of deeply ingrained stimulus-response bonds; the thought is the stimulus and it demands that you respond. One illustrative example from the Times article is a mother who said “There’s always the worry another e-mail has come in” (stimulus). &#8220;It’s hard to resist getting up and checking your emai&#8221;l (response).</p>
<p>But when you meditate, you learn over and over not to do things like taking that last peek; instead you train your mind to go back to your chosen object of meditation. This breaks the stimulus-response bond. Think of it, there are probably thousands of thoughts that create in you an urge to take action, but your meditation breaks the bond between thought and action.  It reduces the linkage to the point where the response becomes optional instead of compulsive. That will make you calmer.</p>
<p>Earlier we posted <a href="../../../../../2011/03/02/basic-mindfulness-technique/">a traditional way of doing mindfulness meditation</a>, and also an <a href="../../../../../2010/12/06/a-key-step-in-resilience-training-is-learning-deep-relaxation/">audio</a> that can have a similar effect. Nether of these aids take up much of your time. You should consider trying one or both of them.</p>
<p>This is only one small way of changing how your mind works. We will be discussing many more in later posts.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2011%2F11%2F15%2Fsleeplessness-should-you-medicate-of-meditate%2F&amp;linkname=Sleeplessness%3A%20Should%20You%20Medicate%20of%20Meditate%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Basic Mindfulness Technique</title>
		<link>/2011/03/02/basic-mindfulness-technique/</link>
		<comments>/2011/03/02/basic-mindfulness-technique/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 07:44:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mindfulness]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=601</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Mindfulness meditation emphasizes acceptance of and compassion for whatever we experience. It is a useful practice for almost anyone, but especially for someone who is inclined to be harsh and critical toward herself or himself. The details of mindfulness technique &#8230; <a href="/2011/03/02/basic-mindfulness-technique/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Mindfulness meditation emphasizes acceptance of and compassion for whatever we experience. It is a useful practice for almost anyone, but especially for someone who is inclined to be harsh and critical toward herself or himself.</p>
<p>The details of mindfulness technique vary all over the map, but all of them teach us to be aware of what we are experiencing in the moment, and to allow it to BE, without criticism.</p>
<p>This is our preferred approach:</p>
<ul>
<li>Arrange a reasonably quiet      environment to help you acquire the skills needed to practice mindfulness.      (Later you can practice in any environment).</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>You can practice while      sitting or lying down.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Fix your attention on the      rising and falling of the abdomen as you breathe in and out. You can      inwardly say to yourself “rising” as you inhale and “falling” as you      exhale. Your attention should be directed at the rising and falling of the      abdomen and not on the breathing itself.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Each time your attention      strays you should make a mental note of it, and then gently but firmly      return your attention to the rising and falling of your abdomen.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>If extraneous thoughts      come to you, categorize them by naming them. For example you could use the      labels “worrying”, “imagining”, “remembering”, or simply “wandering”.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>If a distraction keeps      coming back, you should shift your attention to that distraction and use      it as the object of contemplation instead of using the rising and falling.</li>
</ul>
<p>It&#8217;s that simple. Just attend to what is present in each moment and learn to be uncritically accepting of whatever experience presents itself.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2011%2F03%2F02%2Fbasic-mindfulness-technique%2F&amp;linkname=Basic%20Mindfulness%20Technique" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2011/03/02/basic-mindfulness-technique/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
