<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>resilience &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/resilience/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Yoga or Resilience Training: Do We Have to Choose?</title>
		<link>/2015/05/28/yoga-or-resilience-training-do-we-have-to-choose/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2015 03:18:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1904</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[What are the main differences between yoga and resilience training? Would it be a good idea to do both, or are they a bad mix? Around a year ago Debbie asked for a Yoga class as her birthday present. It &#8230; <a href="/2015/05/28/yoga-or-resilience-training-do-we-have-to-choose/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What are the main differences between yoga and resilience training? Would it be a good idea to do both, or are they a bad mix?</p>
<p>Around a year ago Debbie asked for a Yoga class as her birthday present. It was a great suggestion, and Yoga has helped her to cope with a stage in her life in which she has agreed to take responsibility for decisions about health care for her mother. Yoga worked for her and continues to be an important part of her life.</p>
<p>More recently a longstanding friend of mine suggested that I enroll in a beginner’s course in Yoga, and Debbie also urged that I take the course. For many years, I have been dealing with severe, chronic pain due to an arthritic spine that creates impingements on my spinal cord that result in chronic pain and problems with controlling how I walk.</p>
<p>I had just finished a very successful series of Physical Therapy interventions, so was interested in retaining the gains I had made through various forms of stretching and balancing.</p>
<p>Why did Debbie and I both reach out for help from another system instead of relying on the resilience techniques we already knew? Abraham Lincoln summarized one of the major reasons in a widely used quote about lawyers: “He who represents himself has a fool for a client.”</p>
<p>It’s helpful to get training from someone other than yourself. Distance provides a useful perspective.</p>
<p>In addition to that, though resilience training and Yoga superficially seem to have little in common, they are really very much alike. Both approaches use a wide range of techniques that enable you to know yourself at a deeper level and to soothe and calm yourself.</p>
<p>Yoga, as it is typically practiced in the United States, emphasizes working on changes of the body, and most resilience programs emphasize changes at the level of mind.<br />
But change in the body results in change in the mind and change at the level of the mind results in change in the body.</p>
<p>For example, if you are getting agitated, slowing and deepening your breathing pattern tends to calm both your mind and your body.</p>
<p>Similarly, you can make yourself salivate by imagining sucking on a lemon and you can make your hands get warmer by imagining yourself at the beach lying on a big towel and picturing the sun warming your hands.</p>
<p>For quite a few years a significant body of research in scientific psychology has focused a lot of its efforts on conducting studies to determine whether ancient techniques work. For the most part, those techniques have passed the tests and been integrated into psychological methods of treatment.</p>
<p>So our view is that ancient disciplines from the Far East tend to fit comfortably into recent, science-based resilience programs.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2015%2F05%2F28%2Fyoga-or-resilience-training-do-we-have-to-choose%2F&amp;linkname=Yoga%20or%20Resilience%20Training%3A%20Do%20We%20Have%20to%20Choose%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Map of the Path to Increased Resilience.</title>
		<link>/2013/06/20/a-map-of-the-path-to-increased-resilience/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2013 05:19:14 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Attitudes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1392</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Underlying our posts is a three-factor model of resilience which was derived from research done as part of my role as a professor. Our posts tend to be on specific attitudes or actions that are statistically confirmed aspects of one &#8230; <a href="/2013/06/20/a-map-of-the-path-to-increased-resilience/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Underlying our posts is a three-factor model of resilience which was derived from research done as part of my role as a professor. Our posts tend to be on specific attitudes or actions that are statistically confirmed aspects of one of the three factors. That is not because we select them only if they match our model. Our model just matches the data.</p>
<p>The blog was not started to publicize or support the model. It started as an outlet to keep me from constantly adding new findings to a book Debbie and I wrote to teach people how to improve their resilience.</p>
<p>To identify the core factors that underlie resilience we used a method called factor analysis. Done correctly, it can reveal the deep structure of whatever you are studying. So, for example, if you used it on three dimensional objects, like boxes, it would tell you that there are three dimensions, height, width and length.</p>
<p>We determined the dimensions of resilience and found that there were three. We also replicated that finding in two additional studies, and both of them confirmed the three dimensions.</p>
<p>To explain the factors here would be redundant, since we have already done that in <a href="/2011/01/11/the-three-core-factors-that-can-make-you-more-resilient/">this post</a>.</p>
<p>For now, we will discuss the number one factor that improves resilience.</p>
<h2>What good is this to you?</h2>
<p>Knowing the core dimensions will help you pinpoint all you can do to improve your resilience.</p>
<p>The number one influence on resilience is developing resilience-promoting  <strong><em>attitudes</em></strong> and <strong><em>skills</em></strong>.  These account for so much of resilience that, for a while, I was tempted to think of Factor One alone as just plain resilience, and ignore the other two factors. But too much evidence showed that those factors can be crucial for many people.</p>
<p>So what are the attitudes and skills you should try to develop?</p>
<p><span id="more-1392"></span></p>
<ul>
<li>Being optimistic and hopeful instead of pessimistic and hopeless.</li>
<li>Seeing distressing or painful life events as problems to be solved instead of things to be lamented and cursed.</li>
<li>Looking for and maybe even finding meaning in what we do and what we experience instead of just slogging through life.</li>
<li>Learning how to sooth, calm and replenish yourself, and then <strong><em>applying what you have learned </em></strong>to your everyday life when you are distressed, and also when you are feeling okay. (The latter is important in order to develop <strong><em>habits</em></strong> of resilience.).</li>
</ul>
<p>Some of the attitudes under factor one that help us be more resilient are</p>
<ol start="1">
<li>Being optimistic and hopeful versus viewing life with pessimism or despair.</li>
</ol>
<p>Here are posts that tell you how to do that:</p>
<p><a href="/2011/01/01/less-pessimism-and-more-optimism-will-build-your-resilience/">Increasing your optimism.</a></p>
<p><a href="/2012/08/02/reducing-negativity-in-your-mind-and-your-life/">Decreasing your negativity.</a></p>
<ol start="2">
<li>Viewing our lives, our choices, and our actions as meaningful versus seeing them as meaningless.</li>
</ol>
<p>Here is a post to help you do that.</p>
<p><a href="/2011/11/28/finding-meaning-and-purpose-can-help-you-deal-with-distress-no-matter-how-extreme/">Finding  meaning.</a></p>
<ol start="3">
<li>Taking a problem-solving attitude toward stressful situations and anticipating predictable complications.</li>
</ol>
<p>Here is a post that shows you how to do that:</p>
<p><a href="/2012/08/02/reducing-negativity-in-your-mind-and-your-life/">Problem-Solving Attitude.</a></p>
<ol start="4">
<li>Learning and applying  the skills that sooth and replenish you instead of taking actions that make things worse.</li>
</ol>
<p>There are many posts that show how to do that:</p>
<p><a href="/2011/03/02/basic-mindfulness-technique/">Training yourself in mindfulness.</a></p>
<p><a href="/2011/06/02/tactical-breathing-can-stop-stress-on-the-spot/">Breath control for resilience.</a></p>
<p><a href="/2010/12/06/a-key-step-in-resilience-training-is-learning-deep-relaxation/">Learning deep relaxation.</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F06%2F20%2Fa-map-of-the-path-to-increased-resilience%2F&amp;linkname=A%20Map%20of%20the%20Path%20to%20Increased%20Resilience." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Resilience Is More than Bouncing Back From Stress</title>
		<link>/2011/07/05/resilience-is-more-than-bouncing-back-from-stress/</link>
		<comments>/2011/07/05/resilience-is-more-than-bouncing-back-from-stress/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2011 06:06:12 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Why Resilience?]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=800</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In this post I want to take a closer look at what resilience is and who can gain from training to increase it. People often tell me that I should explain resilience as the ability to “bounce back” from stress. &#8230; <a href="/2011/07/05/resilience-is-more-than-bouncing-back-from-stress/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this post I want to take a closer look at what resilience is and who can gain from training to increase it.</p>
<p>People often tell me that I should explain resilience as the ability to “bounce back” from stress. I hate that view of resilience. It always reminds me of those inflated dummies that are designed to come right back to an upright position after they are punched, setting themselves up to be punched again. That is not resilience. It is mindlessness, literally in this case.</p>
<p>A much better description of resilience is “playing a poor hand well”. There is a pretty good <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Playing-Poor-Hand-Well-Professional/dp/0393702324" target="_self">book by that title</a>, and I commend the author for the book and the title.</p>
<p>But even that title fails to get it quite right. Resilience is having the ability to play <em>any</em> hand well. If you were dealt a poor hand, resilience is the set of abilities that enable you to perform above expectations. If you were dealt a good hand, it is the set of abilities that enable you to make the most of it. In other words, resilience enables you to deal with stress efficiently and effectively, to recover from stress more quickly and more completely. But, stress aside, it enables you to perform at your best level, whether in your work, in sports, or in relationships.</p>
<p>So it is not easy to target precisely who needs resilience training because the audience is really just about everybody. Maybe the best way to pinpoint who is a good match for training and who is not is to break people down into:</p>
<ul>
<li>Those who need help in developing      their skills for dealing with stress and living up to their potential in      life and also know they need help.</li>
<li>Those who need help in      developing those skills and do not know it.</li>
</ul>
<p>A final word.</p>
<p>Years ago I used to lend a large set of my data on stress and resilience for use in an advanced statistics class, where the students were learning to find the meanings hidden in masses of data. The instructor always invited me to sit in on a long session in which each student reported on their findings. In one of those classes a student who was a real standout in statistics reported that she had detected a very large factor in the data, for which she had struggled to give an adequate name. She decided to call it “Good Life”.</p>
<p>It was the factor that made the largest contribution to resilience. After many more years of study, we identified that factor as “resilient attitudes and skills”. I often think that “Good Life” gives an excellent sense of what developing resilient attitudes and skills might provide.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2011%2F07%2F05%2Fresilience-is-more-than-bouncing-back-from-stress%2F&amp;linkname=Resilience%20Is%20More%20than%20Bouncing%20Back%20From%20Stress" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2011/07/05/resilience-is-more-than-bouncing-back-from-stress/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
