<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Sense of Coherence &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/sense-of-coherence/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Finding Meaning and Purpose Can Help You Deal with Distress, No Matter How Extreme.</title>
		<link>/2011/11/28/finding-meaning-and-purpose-can-help-you-deal-with-distress-no-matter-how-extreme/</link>
		<comments>/2011/11/28/finding-meaning-and-purpose-can-help-you-deal-with-distress-no-matter-how-extreme/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2011 16:03:03 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sense of Coherence]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=865</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Studies of holocaust survivors indicate that how we react is, even in extreme circumstances, crucial in determining how much damage is done. Though we have little or no control over outside circumstances, we can still influence our inner reactions to &#8230; <a href="/2011/11/28/finding-meaning-and-purpose-can-help-you-deal-with-distress-no-matter-how-extreme/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Studies of holocaust survivors indicate that<em> how we react</em> is, even in extreme circumstances, crucial in determining how much damage is done. Though we have little or no control over outside circumstances, we can still influence our inner reactions to them.</p>
<p>Today, many people face exceptionally harsh conditions, and they are unaccustomed to the levels of stress they have to endure. It is hard for them to believe there is anything they can do to make things better. The problem is outside of them and beyond their control. How they react to their circumstances may seem irrelevant.</p>
<p>But research on holocaust survivors indicates that how one reacts even in the most heinous situations has a powerful effect on survival and well-being.</p>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salutogenesis" target="_self">Aaron Antonovsky </a>studied survivors of the camps, and concluded that, though they were largely helpless on the outside, their inner attitudes could make a great difference. Prior to that work, Victor Frankl, a survivor of the camps, had written about his own views on this topic from an inside perspective. He and Antonovsky came to very similar conclusions about which ways of reacting were best.</p>
<p><span id="more-865"></span></p>
<p>Frankl wrote an outstanding book called “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Mans-Search-Meaning-Viktor-Frankl/dp/0671023373">Man’s Search for Meaning</a>” about how he dealt with the concentration camp experience.  To him the key was finding meaning and purpose. This might seem impossible in a situation so horrific, but he found meaning there in two ways.</p>
<ul>
<li>He was a medical doctor      able to help others in the camp, and that gave meaning to his painful      life. He even chose not to take a chance to escape because he, as a      doctor, could help others survive.</li>
<li>He also found meaning in      refusing to cooperate with the attempts that were made to force him to behave      in ways that were meant to degrade his full humanity, which was one of the      goals of his captors (See the movie Sophie&#8217;s Choice).</li>
</ul>
<p>Frankl lived a rich life till the age of 92.</p>
<p>Here is an old, black and white <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wr6itOBLVQA">video</a> of Frankl, at the age of 72 advising us how to treat others in a way that can help them realize their full potential as human beings, and also how to set goals for ourselves.</p>
<p>The video is worth viewing just to see how alive and passionate a person can be despite having lived through hell.</p>
<p>For both Frankl and Antonovsky, finding meaning and purpose was of central importance. It is also an important facet of the resilience model we derived from statistical analyses of resilience factors.</p>
<p>The first and most important factor included being realistically optimistic, having a problem-solving attitude toward difficult situations, and finding meaning and value in what you choose to do.</p>
<p>Fortunately there are tested ways to coach yourself to develop these qualities. That is what this blog is all about.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2011%2F11%2F28%2Ffinding-meaning-and-purpose-can-help-you-deal-with-distress-no-matter-how-extreme%2F&amp;linkname=Finding%20Meaning%20and%20Purpose%20Can%20Help%20You%20Deal%20with%20Distress%2C%20No%20Matter%20How%20Extreme." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2011/11/28/finding-meaning-and-purpose-can-help-you-deal-with-distress-no-matter-how-extreme/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Through Adversity to the Stars</title>
		<link>/2011/01/27/through-adversity-to-the-stars/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 27 Jan 2011 16:10:33 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Harvard Grant Study]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sense of Coherence]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=555</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The title of this post (in Latin) is cut in stone on the entryway to the gym at the University where I spent the great bulk of my working life. Nietzsche said something very similar, “Whatever does not kill me &#8230; <a href="/2011/01/27/through-adversity-to-the-stars/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The title of this post (in Latin) is cut in stone on the entryway to the gym at the University where I spent the great bulk of my working life. Nietzsche said something very similar, “Whatever does not kill me makes me stronger”. Statements like these are much contested on the Internet; taken too literally they are dubious at best.  However, I think we should lighten up and understand they are part poetry and part wisdom.</p>
<p>The quotations point toward an important question. <em>Can going through adversity actually improve your ability to pull through distressing experiences?</em> The New York Times recently published an <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/01/04/health/04mind.html">article</a> describing research on close to 2000 people who were asked to indicate all of the upsetting life events they had experienced before entering the study and any new ones that occurred along the way. Examples of such events included divorce, the death of a friend or parent, a serious illness, and being in a natural disaster.</p>
<p>The mental well-being of the participants was monitored over several years. The mental well-being measures were compared for those who reported no such life events, those who reported 2 to 6 such events, and those who presented 7 or more.</p>
<p>Those who reported no events were not highest in mental well-being. In fact, their well-being was like that of participants who reported 12 or more adverse events. Intermediate levels of adversity were associated with the greatest well-being.</p>
<p>The NYT article goes on to make two points: 1. We cannot accurately predict who will emerge from adversity well or even stronger and 2. It may be that dealing with adversity is important because it provides opportunities to hone skills for dealing with challenging situations.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, the first point is not quite accurate and the second, though sensible, is mere speculation. The main thrust of this post is to object to the first point.</p>
<p>For a long time we could only speculate about which qualities enabled some people to go through hellish challenges and come out of them healthy, happy, and successful. But there is now a well-developed science of resilience.</p>
<p>I will briefly discuss two examples, but there are many:</p>
<p><span id="more-555"></span></p>
<ol>
<li>George Vaillant summarized      the results of a  <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2009/06/what-makes-us-happy/7439/">major      study over the lifespan of Harvard Students</a>. The students were studied      from their undergraduate years into old age, and copious information      collected on how they coped with life and on how successful their lives      had been. Success in life was defined as the ability to love and to work.      In other words, could they form good, solid relationships and were they      successful in their work? Good outcomes depended on the following:</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Using humor to deal with adversity.</li>
<li>Facing reality, but also having the ability to put challenges aside when nothing more can be done about them.</li>
<li>Being able to look ahead and notice what might cause you trouble later, and to take action to minimize the distress that might result.</li>
<li>Taking the needs of others seriously and including them in the orb of people whose needs are important to you.</li>
<li>Finding socially constructive ways to give expression to your deep needs, e.g. putting aggression into sport.</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salutogenesis">Aaron Antonosky</a> observed      that holocaust survivors commonly have a very hard time dealing with      challenges later in life, e.g. menopause. However, many survivors emerged      as outstandingly resilient people. He studied women who were survivors and      found that an orientation to life he called “Sense of Coherence”      characterized these remarkably resilient survivors.</li>
</ol>
<p>It’s true that we cannot predict how an individual will react at a given time. Even predictions in the “hard” sciences are generally about averages, not about individuals. Researchers have discovered many characteristics that make it more likely, on average, that someone will emerge from a difficult situation intact and maybe even stronger.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2011%2F01%2F27%2Fthrough-adversity-to-the-stars%2F&amp;linkname=Through%20Adversity%20to%20the%20Stars" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
