<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Benefits of Resilience &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/benefits-of-resilience/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Surgical Preparation: Specific Details.</title>
		<link>/2016/09/14/surgical-preparation-specific-details/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Benefits of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2131</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Recently we have been writing posts about preparing patients for surgery. Benefits can be mental, but our focus has been on learning mind-focused ways to improve patient&#8217;s physical reactions during and after surgery. We found that many published studies indicate &#8230; <a href="/2016/09/14/surgical-preparation-specific-details/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Recently we have been writing posts about preparing patients for surgery. Benefits can be mental, but our focus has been on learning mind-focused ways to improve patient&#8217;s physical reactions during and after surgery.</p>
<p>We found that many published studies indicate that outcomes are significantly improved in patients who were given presurgical training. For example, patients lose remarkably less blood if they are taught how to move the blood away from the spine during the surgery and then have it return to the spine to facilitate healing after surgery.</p>
<p>At this point, many readers may be thinking that there is no way for the mind to move blood around in the body. Patients who are being trained tend to feel that way too.</p>
<p>An important step is to explain how that can happen. Scientifically designed studies are normally kept very simple, but in clinical practice the methods may be more complex. A common method used in research is pointing out that our minds often trigger movement of blood. Remind the trainee that most people blush when they are embarrassed. We also move blood to our genitals by having erotic fantasies. You can direct your blood to your hands by relaxing, suggesting that your blood is flowing down your arm into your hands, and picturing the suggested flow. This is not at all remarkable, the &#8220;fight or flight&#8221; reaction includes moving blood away from the periphery of your body. Relaxation inhibits the &#8220;fight or flight&#8221; reaction, so it makes blood flow to the hands.</p>
<p>There is much more evidence that the mind can control supposedly &#8220;involuntary&#8221; bodily reactions, but for this post we want to describe Debbie&#8217;s experiences with preparing patients to deal with upcoming surgery. Like most clinicians, she uses methods that go far beyond the simple methods assessed in published studies.</p>
<p>In her words:</p>
<p>&#8220;As a therapist I had remarkable success in assisting some of my patients to prepare for surgery or other medical procedures.</p>
<p>In therapy sessions, I begin by having the patient talk about the surgery and what the aim or primary goal is particularly from their perspective. We explore any feelings or concerns that they have about the surgery. What is their relationship with the medical people including the surgeon? Have they had surgery in the past and how did it go? Were there any complications? Have there previously been any poor outcomes.</p>
<p>The potential benefits of preparing psychologically in advance of the surgery are explained. I cite examples from published literature and describe my own experiences with other patients to explain how beneficial preparation can be. If for example the patient does not trust the medical field or has had bad experiences, we work to come to some sort of peace with it, enough that this does not transfer to the present situation. If they have had bad outcomes from surgery we explore this together to see if there are differences in the present situation.</p>
<p>We talk about mentally shifting to a place where the patient can see the medical team as being there to help them achieve their objectives.</p>
<p>We discuss how getting to a place where they are trusting of the medical provider makes it possible for their body to cooperate with the surgeon and not fight against her/him. It is understandable that at some level the body will protest being cut into and it is best to get the surgeon and patient working together, helping the body to relax.</p>
<p>The patient  tries to find out as much as possible about the surgery and what the procedure consists of, including a description of the steps along the way.</p>
<p>The patient  learns some form of relaxation procedure and oftentimes  is provided an audio to practice at home. In the counseling sessions I use the same relaxation procedure and while the patient is relaxed begin to guide them in imagining the surgery and positive outcomes. I provide some of the &#8220;script&#8221; but also encourage them to offer input and improve it.</p>
<p>I re-emphasize that the surgeon is here to help the patient and cooperating with him/her is what is needed now. Usually they visualize the knife entering their body for a noble purpose and that the blood at the time moves away from the surgery site.</p>
<p>Surgical steps are reviewed and how particularly the patient, the surgeon and the patient&#8217;s body are cooperating. They visualize how the area of the body is being &#8220;corrected&#8221; and how wonderful it will be for the quality of their life and health afterwards.</p>
<p>They imagine the anesthesia wearing off in a pleasant manner. I suggest that, as the anesthesia wears off, they will soon want water and some food. We discuss their body eliminating in a normal way and the body vitals being such that they can soon go home.</p>
<p>Other images might include seeing loved ones arrive to take them home and how soon they see the anticipated surgical improvements. Any rehabilitation services can also be incorporated into the imagery exercise.</p>
<p>Typically, it is best  to have several weeks to prepare for the surgery but have seen benefit in just a few sessions.&#8221;</p>
<p>Notice that there are three main devices being used. They are relaxation, imagery and suggestion. This is a triad that can help get you through just about any difficult situation.</p>
<p>RELATED READINGS</p>
<p>For clinical techniques we recommend Stanley Fischer&#8217;s &#8220;Discovering the Power of Self Hypnosis : A New Approach for Enabling Change And Promoting Healing.&#8221; The book was published in 1991, so is likely to be out of print but you can probably get a good used one at Abebooks.com at a very low price.</p>
<p>For a very good review of research on the evidence that supports the efficacy of this kind of method for surgical preparation we recommend &#8220;Mind-Body Interventions for Surgery: Evidence and Exigency,&#8221;published in Advances in Mind-Body Medicine, volume 14, Number 3 in the Summer of 1998, Pages 165-234. You can probably get a copy at little or no cost from your library. Be sure to ask for an interlibrary loan. Reading the article will likely be a challenge unless you have background in scientific writing , including statistical methods.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Prepare for Your Later Life by Accumulating Skills and Habits of Resilience</title>
		<link>/2014/12/22/prepare-for-your-later-life-by-accumulating-skills-and-habits-of-resilience/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2014 17:41:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Benefits of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience and Health]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1801</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Why should we invest in improving our resilience? Usually it is because we want to: Avoid having painful, distressing reactions to potentialy jarring occurrences that come up in our lives, and instead to stay reasonably calm and cool in the &#8230; <a href="/2014/12/22/prepare-for-your-later-life-by-accumulating-skills-and-habits-of-resilience/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Why should we invest in improving our resilience? Usually it is because we want to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Avoid having painful, distressing reactions to potentialy jarring occurrences that come up in our lives, and instead to stay reasonably calm and cool in the face of such experiences.</li>
<li>Avoid ending up lastingly impaired by such experiences. That often quoted saying “Whatever doesn’t kill me makes me stronger” Is only true when permanent or long-term damage isn’t done. (Think of Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder.)</li>
<li>If we fail to avoid being impaired, minimize the damage by developing effective “work-arounds”, and thus maintain our quality of life.</li>
</ul>
<p>Researchers have provided us with many studies that show striking positive effects of resilience. A remarkable example that comes to mind is research showing that optimism predicts  <a title="better outcomes of surgery, including recovery from a coronary bypass" href="http://www.psy.miami.edu/faculty/ccarver/documents/10_CPR_Optimism.pdf">better outcomes of surgery, including recovery from a coronary bypass</a>.</p>
<p>Still, studies in real life situations with large samples of real people that trace the effects of resilience over fairly long periods of time are rare. The work of <a title="Lydia Manning" href="http://newoldage.blogs.nytimes.com/2014/09/12/tougher-than-they-look/" target="_blank">Lydia Manning</a> and her colleagues is one of the rare exceptions.<span id="more-1801"></span></p>
<p>This team assessed the impact of resilience on the lives of older people (ranging from their fifties to their late nineties). She and her colleagues gave a remarkably large sample of more than 10,000 older people a simple measure of resilience, then tracked them for two years.</p>
<p>People in their study who started out more resilient were less likely to lose functions that enable them to live independently. When you are elderly and dealing with stress, you are not just at risk of feeling uncomfortable; you are at risk of losing control of your life. Resilience makes it more likely that you will stand up to the stresses of life, or, failing that, at least find ways you can stay in control of your life.</p>
<p>Many of you may feel that research on old people’s ability to avoid needing help to do everyday tasks of life has little or nothing to do with you. Well, 100 percent of young people who don’t die young end up old. Even before they get old, people who are important to them may face the vulnerabilities of old age. So this research is important to most of us.</p>
<p>If we want to meet the challenges of elder life with a strong armamentarium of resilience skills and habits, the best thing is to learn those skills and develop those habits early on so they are ingrained in us and can be called on whether you are young or old.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F12%2F22%2Fprepare-for-your-later-life-by-accumulating-skills-and-habits-of-resilience%2F&amp;linkname=Prepare%20for%20Your%20Later%20Life%20by%20Accumulating%20Skills%20and%20Habits%20of%20Resilience" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lessons for the Old and the Young on Recovering from Nasty Challenges</title>
		<link>/2014/09/22/lessons-for-the-old-and-the-young-on-recovering-from-nasty-challenges/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2014 03:28:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Benefits of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience and Health]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1748</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Elderly people can have devastating consequences, including death, from injuries such as breaking bones. Broken hips are hard for any of us to deal with, but often can be fatal to elders. Recently research on the factors that predict recovery &#8230; <a href="/2014/09/22/lessons-for-the-old-and-the-young-on-recovering-from-nasty-challenges/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Elderly people can have devastating consequences, including death, from injuries such as breaking bones. Broken hips are hard for any of us to deal with, but often can be fatal to elders.</p>
<p>Recently research on the factors that predict recovery after falls for the elderly has shown that <a href="http://newoldage.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/11/15/predicting-a-falls-aftermath/?_php=true&amp;_type=blogs&amp;_r=0">those who were more fit before the fall were significantly more likely to recover</a>.</p>
<p>Our take on this is that elderly people who have a lifestyle that makes them more fit are more resilient in the face of mortal threats.</p>
<p>Many countries, including ours, have populations that are increasingly older. But if you take away from this recent finding that you should stay fit as you grow older, you are right, but you are, at the same time, missing the heart of the matter.</p>
<p>The main thing to take away is that the more you, whether old or yourng, cultivate your resilience, the more likely you are to come out well after any of life’s nasty challenges, and the more likely you are to recover a good life.</p>
<p>Nietszche said “Whatever does not kill me makes me stronger”.  Another, less dramatic and less poetic, way to phrase that is, if you have developed resilience skills, you are more likely to grow strong after nasty challenges instead of being taken down by them. And this is true no matter how old you are, or what kind of damage you are facing.</p>
<p>The take-home message is “start NOW to build your physical, and mental resilience”. It will help you through all the phases of your life.</p>
<p>This is YOUR LIFE we are talking about.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F09%2F22%2Flessons-for-the-old-and-the-young-on-recovering-from-nasty-challenges%2F&amp;linkname=Lessons%20for%20the%20Old%20and%20the%20Young%20on%20Recovering%20from%20Nasty%20Challenges" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Facing Situations That You May Not Be Able to Handle? Develop a Problem Solving Attitude.</title>
		<link>/2014/06/25/facing-situations-that-you-may-not-be-able-to-handle-develop-a-problem-solving-attitude/</link>
		<comments>/2014/06/25/facing-situations-that-you-may-not-be-able-to-handle-develop-a-problem-solving-attitude/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2014 18:30:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Benefits of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1667</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Having a “problem solving attitude” is an important influence on resilience. This attitude is a form of positivity, which is a well-known key to resilience. It is a facet of the first and most influential factor influencing resilience. It is &#8230; <a href="/2014/06/25/facing-situations-that-you-may-not-be-able-to-handle-develop-a-problem-solving-attitude/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Having a “problem solving attitude” is an important influence on resilience. This attitude is a form of positivity, which is a well-known key to resilience. It is a facet of the <a href="/2011/01/11/the-three-core-factors-that-can-make-you-more-resilient/">first and most influential factor influencing resilience</a>. It is linked to “positivity”, which is a key to resilience.</p>
<p>What, exactly is a “problem-solving attitude”? The best way to explain this is to describe what people with this attitude are likely to believe about life’s challenges.</p>
<p>People with this kind of attitude tend to react to mistakes by trying to figure out how to avoid them in the future.</p>
<p>You might say, “Isn’t that what everybody does?”</p>
<p><span id="more-1667"></span></p>
<p>No! It is very common for people to spend much more time looking for who is to blame for what happened, and, in particular, trying to convince themselves and others that nothing they did contributed to the bad outcome. That results in learning nothing about how to make things better.</p>
<p>Are there steps you can take to improve your problem solving attitude?</p>
<p>One thing you should do when faced with difficult situations is mentally take a step back and review the nature of the problem. Too often people jump into active attempts to solve a problem without first reviewing the details of the situation that are giving rise to the problem.</p>
<p>A good example is how people react when their computer or mobile device will not respond the way it should. It is all too common to become frustrated and angry, maybe muttering expletives while quickly trying out various solutions without really thinking through what is likely to work. Muttering expletives doesn’t repair electronic equipment.</p>
<p>It’s best to settle down and think through the nature of the problem and then select a few potential solutions to try out. Then try them out, being sure to keep track of what you are trying and of the results.</p>
<p>Don’t start telling yourself how bad it will be if you fail to come up with a quick solution. The problem is likely to be less consequential than it seems when you are immersed in it. As Nobel Prize winning psychologist, Daniel Kahneman said “Nothing in life is as important as you think it is, while you are thinking about it”.</p>
<p>Emphasize that this is a <em>problem</em> to be <em>solved</em> and there may well be many solutions. Do not fall into the trap of thinking the problem simply cannot be solved.</p>
<p>Think of the centuries in which people insisted that it was impossible for humans to fly. Then the Wright brothers built their flying machine and then, over the next several years developed it into a stable way of flying. After that, many more ways of flying came to light.</p>
<p>One thing you should train yourself <strong><em>not </em></strong>to do is focus on criticizing yourself for making mistakes. If you do that, it is likely to engulf you, leaving little or no mental space for thinking about how to make things better. Attacking yourself is a matter of changing the subject from how to solve the problem to a mental discussion of your worth. At that point, you stop problem solving.</p>
<p>Avoid being one of the many people who actually <em>insist on hopelessness</em>. The last thing you should do is adopt any resilience-draining approach of quickly deciding that nothing can be done to improve results. That is the path of hopelessness.</p>
<p>You don’t have to be a baseball fan to appreciate the following story:</p>
<p>In his book “The Mental ABC’s of Pitching: A Handbook for Performance Enhancement”, Major League pitching coach and sports psychologist, Harvey Dorfman, provided a clarifying example of how easy it may be to succeed if you just focus your mind on looking for solutions.</p>
<p>He describes an encounter with a pitcher, Steve Mura, who had spent six seasons in the Major Leagues and won 12 games for the 1983 Cardinals He was the starting pitcher for that night’s game.</p>
<p>Dorfman was chatting with him, and Mura shook his head silently. When asked what that was about, he said, “I can never win on this mound.” In the ensuing discussion, Dorfman told Mura, “There is a difference between, ‘I have not won and I cannot win’.” After all, there are many things we accomplish for the first time. Otherwise there would be no such thing as breaking one’s personal record.</p>
<p>Dorfman was already guiding Mura toward a problem solving approach by disabusing him of the illusion that past failures <strong><em>must</em></strong> continue forever. Can you see what a silly idea that is? To start with, how many things in life, whether good or bad, last forever?</p>
<p>When questioned further, Mura complained about the height and slope of the pitching mound. Dorfman asked him what kind of adjustments he could make to deal with that. Mura thought it over and came up with a strategy. He had never thought that way before. Instead he had spent his energy telling himself that he couldn’t win in that ballpark.</p>
<p>Mura pitched seven innings that night and gave up only two runs on hits. For those of you who don’t understand baseball, that is a very respectable performance.</p>
<p>Mura began in a state of pessimism and hopelessness. He wasn’t even applying the power of his mind to find solutions. As Dorfman pointed out, why should anyone think about solving the problem if failure is foreordained? And if they do not even begin problem solving, they obviously cannot persist in finding a way to succeed.</p>
<p>Once Mura shifted from pessimism and hopelessness to a problem-solving mode, it took only a few minutes to develop a plan of adjustments that led to success.</p>
<p>We are not saying that it will always be that easy, but you are much more likely to find solutions if you invest your energy in looking for them</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=&amp;linkname=Facing%20Situations%20That%20You%20May%20Not%20Be%20Able%20to%20Handle%3F%20Develop%20a%20Problem%20Solving%20Attitude." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2014/06/25/facing-situations-that-you-may-not-be-able-to-handle-develop-a-problem-solving-attitude/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Can We Make Ourselves Biologically Younger?</title>
		<link>/2013/10/17/can-we-make-ourselves-biologically-younger/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2013 05:47:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Benefits of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mindfulness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience and Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1516</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Some years ago we became aware of the important role of telomeres in aging, and the role of stress in speeding up the aging process. Telomeres are genetic components that are linked to biological aging. Usually, the older you are &#8230; <a href="/2013/10/17/can-we-make-ourselves-biologically-younger/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Some years ago we became aware of the important role of telomeres in aging, and the role of stress in speeding up the aging process. Telomeres are genetic components that are linked to biological aging. Usually, the older you are the shorter your telomeres become.</p>
<p>What did this have to do with resilience? Well, resilience controls stress, and it turns out that higher levels of stress result in increased shortening of telomeres. So your calendar age is not the only determinant of how old your cells are. Stress is a highly significant influence.</p>
<p>In fact, women who reported being highly stressed were biologically, as indexed by telomere length, about ten years older than those who did not report high stress.</p>
<p>In one of our early resilience workshops, one person in the group asked an obvious question that hadn’t occurred to us. “Is there anything that can enable us to <strong><em>lengthen</em></strong> our telomeres?&#8221; We paused, and had to say that we did not know.</p>
<p>Since that time, a good deal of research has shown that we can indeed lengthen our telomeres through lifestyle changes.</p>
<p>We were working on our usual exhaustive examination of the scientifically respectable evidence that people can lengthen their telomeres when we discovered the following interview of Dr. Dean Ornish, who recently completed a study on how the telomeres can be lengthened. We decided to re-post his video, which does a very good job of explaining what we need to do to lengthen our telomeres. We weren&#8217;t likely to improve, in a short post, on what he says in this interview. And it isn&#8217;t just a promotion of his own work; he talks about a wide range or research pointing in the same direction as his.</p>
<p><iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/QPpJU8Je-lE" frameborder="0" width="420" height="315"></iframe></p>
<p>It appears that telomeres can indeed be lengthened, and that well established healthy lifestyle changes can produce the lengthening.</p>
<p>Naturally attempts are being made to develop a kind of &#8220;Fountain of Youth&#8221; pill that can lengthen telomeres. We would recommend that such pills be viewed with great caution. It&#8217;s one thing to do things we already know are good for you and thus lengthen telomeres and quite another to take a new pill that needs lengthy testing.</p>
<p>As we have pointed out previously in this blog, the body is a highly complex, interactive ecosystem. Change one thing and many other unpredictable changes are likely to occur. The enzyme, telomerase stimulates growth of telomeres. But there is a lot of telomerase in certain malignant tumors. So who can say what kinds of side effects might result from artificial tampering?</p>
<p>On the other hand, sensible exercise, eating a healthy diet, learning to live peacefully with others, and calming ourselves through meditation have been around for centuries, and we know that their side effects improve lives</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F10%2F17%2Fcan-we-make-ourselves-biologically-younger%2F&amp;linkname=Can%20We%20Make%20Ourselves%20Biologically%20Younger%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Ways to Slow Down the Pace of Your Aging and Function Better Despite Your Biological Age</title>
		<link>/2013/01/23/ways-to-slow-down-the-pace-of-your-aging-and-function-better-despite-your-biological-age/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2013 04:45:48 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Benefits of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1302</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This may appear to be a preposterous claim, but there is good reason to believe that, through building your resilience, you can slow your body’s rate of cellular aging, and also that, regardless of your cellular age, you can match &#8230; <a href="/2013/01/23/ways-to-slow-down-the-pace-of-your-aging-and-function-better-despite-your-biological-age/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This may appear to be a preposterous claim, but there is good reason to believe that, through building your resilience, you can slow your body’s rate of cellular aging, and also that, regardless of your cellular age, you can match the functional level of young people if you have good resilience skills.</p>
<h3><strong>“Illusory Aging”</strong></h3>
<p>I frequently hear my friends complain about loss of memory, being tired, or lacking energy, which they attribute to aging. I am convinced that many of the symptoms they attribute to age are really due to a lack of exercise, or to making unreasonable demands on the brain in an era of information overload. Usually this kind of “aging” can be dealt with moderate exercise and easing up on the demands we make on our brains, e.g. quieting the mind through meditation. We could as well say it can be dealt with by reducing stress and improving our resilience skills.</p>
<h3><strong>Real Aging and What You Can Do About It.</strong></h3>
<p>Of course, there is also real aging, even down to the cellular level. For example, there are little end caps on chromosomes, called telomeres. Telomeres shorten each time a cell divides, and therefore they are an index of biological aging. There is clearly nothing illusory about that kind of aging.</p>
<p>In fact, in a <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC534658/?rendertype=abstract">study</a> by Elissa Epel and her colleagues, women who reported being highly stressed had telomere lengths that indicated ten more years of aging than the telomeres of less stressed women.</p>
<p><span id="more-1302"></span></p>
<p>Interestingly, the same tactics we use to deal with illusory aging appear to provide our best hope of slowing biological aging. There is <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/01/28/AR2008012801873.html">research</a> showing that the telomeres of people who exercise shorten more slowly those who exercise less.</p>
<p>The levels of exercise in this study were moderate, with the high end at about three hours of exercise per week. Don’t make the mistake of thinking that, no matter how lengthy and intense, exercise is healthy. Robert Sapolsky pointed out that salmon swim upstream, against the current, leaping over waterfalls and dams, in order to spawn. Their bodies undergo <a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=4_K7Bvxy0AIC&amp;pg=PA127&amp;lpg=PA127&amp;dq=robert+sapolsky+aging+salmon&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=C6vzS4xqeL&amp;sig=QBnjY5VjVGfuAjnng100Ans233M&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=wGT_UNKtHILsqwHxioCYCg&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CFsQ6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q=robert%20sapolsky%20aging%20salmon&amp;f=false">very rapid and severe aging</a> at that time, and they die.</p>
<p>It has been shown that removal of the adrenal glands, which secrete stress hormones, prevents this rapid aging. In addition, Sapolsky points out that well known effects of stress hormones correspond to symptoms of aging: fatigue, thinning muscles, adult-onset diabetes, hypertension, osteoporosis, reproductive decline, and immune suppression.</p>
<p>Decades ago, long before we knew anything about telomeres, <a href="http://www.abebooks.com/servlet/SearchResults?an=herbert+devries&amp;sts=t&amp;tn=vigor+regained">Herbert De Vries</a> did research showing that old, sedentary people could improve their physiological markers of aging by going on a gradually increasing program of exercise (e.g. walking with a very slow increase to jogging).</p>
<p>In contrast, he found that college students paid for being inactive began to show physiological signs of aging.</p>
<h3><strong>What to Do If You Have Already Declined Functionally.</strong></h3>
<p>Now what if you haven’t been able to prevent manifestations of aging. As a result, maybe you have become forgetful, or seen significant losses of ability that are usually linked with increased age. Is there anything you can do about that?</p>
<p>The answer is “Yes”.</p>
<p>A <a href="http://library.mpib-berlin.mpg.de/ft/ul/UL_Limits_2001.pdf">major long-term study</a> of people ranging from 70 to over 100 years old showed us how others have done that.</p>
<p>Here is the pattern of tactics that work:</p>
<p><strong>Selection</strong>: Realize that your capacity is diminished, and that you have to reduce your range of activities. You have to pick what you value the most and really want to maintain. A good example is the great violinist, Yehudi Menuhin, who continued his outstanding performances into advanced old age.</p>
<p><strong><em>How did he do that?</em></strong> He began by reducing his repertoire(selection), so he had less to maintain.</p>
<p><strong>Optimization</strong>: Search for the <strong><em>most effective ways</em></strong> for maintaining the quality of the activities you have chosen to retain. Menuhin focused his energy on the smaller repertoire of musical pieces he wanted to perform.</p>
<p><strong>Compensation</strong>: <strong><em>Put into practice the effective methods</em></strong> you find. Menuhin intensified his practice of the music he had chosen.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F01%2F23%2F1302%2F&amp;linkname=Ways%20to%20Slow%20Down%20the%20Pace%20of%20Your%20Aging%20and%20Function%20Better%20Despite%20Your%20Biological%20Age" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>When Life Becomes a Tsunami of Stress</title>
		<link>/2012/03/14/when-life-becomes-a-tsunami-of-stress/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2012 15:00:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Benefits of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Effective Communication]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Expressing Feelings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Physical Contact]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=971</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[One test of the usefulness of our program and techniques is whether we really practice what we preach. We are not perfect models of what we believe in, nor are we people of super-resilience. I think in an earlier post &#8230; <a href="/2012/03/14/when-life-becomes-a-tsunami-of-stress/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One test of the usefulness of our program and techniques is whether we really practice what we preach. We are not perfect models of what we believe in, nor are we people of super-resilience. I think in an earlier post I acknowledged that my life was far from handing me a cornucopia of resilience skills, and I think I am safe in saying that would also be true for Debbie.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, there were things in our early experiences that helped us develop a fighting spirit and a sense that we can improve by learning what we need to do and doggedly putting what we learned into practice.</p>
<p>For some months we have been dealing with extremely stressful situations. I cannot be explicit about them because that would violate the privacy of others, including others that we care deeply about. I think it’s okay if I say that it involves the approaching death of someone who has been important part of our lives. This is aggravated by dementia of a beloved member of our family, and intense pressure put on even the tiniest of fractures between members of the extended family.</p>
<p>So what has helped us to deal with these things?</p>
<p><span id="more-971"></span></p>
<p>We have both increased our use of deep relaxation. We listen to one of the short audio recordings we designed ourselves, narrated by Debbie. These take only 10-20 minutes.</p>
<p>Even fitting this into our pressured schedules can be hard, but it is well worth the effort. These sessions take us to a level of relaxation that drastically reduces our stress responses.</p>
<p>In spite of there being a lot of interference with sticking to exercise regimens, we both have continued to exercise. Exercise reduces stress reactions in many ways; it reduces stress enhancing bodily chemicals and increases natural bodily chemicals that calm and sooth us.</p>
<p>One of our ways of exercising is to hike in wooded areas which we are fortunate to have tucked away even in our metropolitan area. We usually take our dog, Luke, and his intense enjoyment of being off leash in a place full of surprises and fascinating odors, helps us to experience the joys of being in nature.</p>
<p>Speaking of our dog, he shows clear signs of feeling our distressing experiences very deeply. Dogs, and many other animals, are geniuses at sensing distress in members of their “pack”. So we decided to have what (I blush to admit this) we have dubbed “lovey-dovey time”, just before bed time. He quickly learned that when we say “It’s lovey-dovey time”, both of us are going to lie down beside him and massage and pet him for a while. He, who is normally a very rough and tumble dog, becomes soft and gentle during those sessions.</p>
<p>Research shows that when you pet an animal, the animal’s heart rate and blood pressure go down, and so does yours. Debbie and I both have marveled at how much better we feel during and after these sessions. We had read about it in research studies, but experiencing it is something else.</p>
<p>Debbie and I have an understanding that we’ve got each other’s backs, and that is a core purpose in our lives.</p>
<p>In our last post, we discussed the positive impact of emotional support at home. We have extended that beyond home.</p>
<ul>
<li>Every night we go through a debriefing between the two of us, thus augmenting each other’s individual perspective.</li>
<li>We have extended this theme of support to the extended family by planning coping strategies as a group, with everyone’s viewpoint getting a hearing.</li>
<li>We have steadily worked to create a store of past experiences of support and trust throughout the extended family, so we can speak more frankly with each other than would otherwise be possible.</li>
<li>Whenever possible we have been cooperative with family members who might have reason to oppose us.</li>
</ul>
<p>We still have to take hits; our phone rings over and over again, often making it impossible to relax at night. That is one of the costs incurred by being positive and constructive with all of the people who have a stake in this. Because we have developed our means of individual support and support of each other, we can afford these intrusions, even though they add to our stress load.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2012%2F03%2F14%2F971%2F&amp;linkname=When%20Life%20Becomes%20a%20Tsunami%20of%20Stress" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Encouraging Positive Attitudes Can Enhance Your Resilience</title>
		<link>/2010/12/15/encouraging-positive-attitudes-can-enhance-your-resilience/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2010 04:38:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Benefits of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience as Positive Psychology]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=472</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Highlights: Resilient actions and resilient attitudes are centrally important to becoming more resilient. In this post we want to call your attention to the value of optimism. Research on the influence of optimism and pessimism has tended to be focused on three &#8230; <a href="/2010/12/15/encouraging-positive-attitudes-can-enhance-your-resilience/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong><br />
</strong></p>
<h3><em>Highlights:</em></h3>
<p><em>Resilient actions and resilient attitudes are centrally important to becoming more resilient.</em></p>
<p><em>In this post we want to call your attention to the value of optimism.</em></p>
<p><em>Research on the influence of optimism and pessimism has tended to be focused on three things:</em></p>
<ul>
<li><em>Job and Athletic Performance.</em></li>
<li><em>Relationship Success.</em></li>
<li><em>Health.</em></li>
</ul>
<p><em>***************************************************************************</em></p>
<p>A major way to improve your resilience is to learn the kinds of self-soothing skills we have been discussing, and turning them into habits. Developing habits of self-soothing in distressing situations and of relaxing deeply to replenish yourself are pivotal to improving resilience.</p>
<p>Equally important is shifting how you think, your attitudes. Positive attitudes improve resilience.</p>
<h3>More resilient people:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Are optimistic, consider interpretations of life events that are positive.</li>
<li>See problems as solvable.</li>
<li>See their lives as making sense, as meaningful.</li>
<li>Feel that they have valuable connections to others.</li>
</ul>
<p>Resilient actions and resilient attitudes are centrally important to becoming more resilient.</p>
<p>In this post we want to call your attention to the value of optimism.</p>
<p>Research on the influence of optimism and pessimism has tended to be focused on three things:</p>
<ul>
<li>Job and Athletic Performance.</li>
<li>Relationship Success.</li>
<li>Health.</li>
</ul>
<h3>To provide some examples:</h3>
<h3><em>Job Success</em></h3>
<ul>
<li>Optimists tend to get higher overall job performance ratings from their supervisors.</li>
<li>In a study of optimistic versus pessimistic insurance agents, the optimists sold more, were given higher ratings by managers, and were less likely to quit their jobs.</li>
<li>Tests of optimism and pessimism given during orientation sessions for new production workers at a manufacturing facility predicted later supervisor performance ratings. Pessimism was a particularly strong predictor of poorer performance.</li>
</ul>
<p><span id="more-472"></span></p>
<h3><em>Athletic Performance</em><em> </em></h3>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"> </span></p>
<ul>
<li>Optimistic athletes tend to perform better than pessimists.</li>
<li>Optimistic athletes tend to sustain their performance better than pessimists when faced with adversity, e.g. being behind behind in a game or playing a tough competitor after you have not performed up to expectations in a previous event.</li>
</ul>
<h3><em>Level of Physical Health and Coping with Illness</em></h3>
<ul>
<li>Optimists tend be more healthy than pessimists.</li>
<li>Optimists recover more quickly from major surgery, return to work sooner, end up with a higher post-surgical quality of life, and are less likely to be re-hospitalized.</li>
<li>Optimists have a higher quality of life and better biological markers of recovery if they undergo chemotherapy.</li>
<li>Optimists have a lower risk of all causes of death, especially death due to heart disease.</li>
<li>If required to become a long-term caregiver for a loved one who is seriously ill, optimists stay healthier, and the person they are caring for does too.</li>
<li>Pessimists are more likely than optimists to die prematurely.</li>
</ul>
<h3><em>Mental Health</em></h3>
<ul>
<li>Optimists are less likely to be depressed.</li>
<li>Optimists tend to be less anxious.</li>
<li>Optimists are more likely to have high satisfaction with their lives.</li>
<li>Optimistic mothers are less likely to suffer from post-partum depression.</li>
<li>Optimists tend to have more energy than pessimists.</li>
</ul>
<h3><em>Success in Relationships</em></h3>
<ul>
<li>Optimists tend to be more satisfied with their primary relationship.</li>
<li>Optimists who discuss one of their conflicts see the discussion as more constructive and, later, feel the conflict was better resolved.</li>
<li>Optimistic women treated for breast cancer feel more supported and more physically attractive than pessimists.</li>
</ul>
<p>These bulleted points are not mere opinions. They are all based in scientific studies, many of them available on line. Yet some prominent writers deny the value of optimism. We will take a close look at their objections in the next post.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2010%2F12%2F15%2Fencouraging-positive-attitudes-can-enhance-your-resilience%2F&amp;linkname=Encouraging%20Positive%20Attitudes%20Can%20Enhance%20Your%20Resilience" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
