<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Happiness &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/happiness/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Hazards of a Life That is All Work and No Play.</title>
		<link>/2013/01/09/hazards-of-a-life-that-is-all-work-and-no-play/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Jan 2013 17:21:37 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Happiness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1296</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[For some time now, it has been obvious that Secretary of State, Hillary Clinton, was exhausted. She has coped with many extreme stresses for years. Recently she collapsed and suffered a concussion. Then she had a blood clot near her &#8230; <a href="/2013/01/09/hazards-of-a-life-that-is-all-work-and-no-play/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For some time now, it has been obvious that Secretary of State, Hillary Clinton, was exhausted. She has coped with many extreme stresses for years. Recently she collapsed and suffered a concussion. Then she had a blood clot near her brain. She has recovered, and we do not need to tell her she needs to lighten up her life. Even before her collapse she had made it clear that she would no longer be U.S. Secretary of State.</p>
<p>It is a shame that so many people work so hard that they damage themselves. I wonder how many other people out there are pushing themselves to such damaging levels?  Why do we not refuse to continue when stress has obviously reached those risky levels?</p>
<p>There are many good reasons to demand so much of ourselves.</p>
<p>Many people have to do it just to make ends meet.  Others may push themselves out of personal ambition. Many sacrifice their personal well-being on behalf of people they care about, ranging from friends and family to fellow citizens.</p>
<p>When we choose to make such sacrifices, it is important to be aware of the risks to our health, and even our lives.</p>
<p><span id="more-1296"></span></p>
<p>The stressful “all work and no play” way of living can be deadly. For example, cardiologist C. Noel Bairey Merz concluded, after reviewing the research literature on psychosocial stress and various endpoints of cardiovascular disease (CVD) that “…psychosocial stress contributes to CVD in multiple ways and may well be the decisive factor determining survival or death in the majority of cases.”</p>
<p>There is an important review of scientific research on the relationship between the length of our lives and such things as joy, cheerfulness, and happiness. When Drs. Ed Diener and Micaela Chan systematically <a href="http://internal.psychology.illinois.edu/~ediener/Documents/Diener-Chan_2011.pdf">reviewed</a> research on the relationship between health, longevity and a positive attitude toward your life, the astonishing results were that living a happy life predicts how long we live better than whether we have risky habits like smoking. And the differences in life span for people low versus high in sense of well-being are quite large.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, many people do not have viable options for avoiding living stressful and unhappy lives. Many have to work, often more than one job, while taking care of children or of parents who can no longer take care of themselves (or both).</p>
<p>Let’s face it, many people are trapped in situations that are likely to shorten their lives, and to make them less healthy on the way to their early death. What is to be done about that?</p>
<p>The approach we take for people trapped by circumstances has been to find strategies that preserve well-being, no matter how harsh life may be. Aaron Antonovsky even identified attitudes that helped  people in Nazi concentration camps to survive and do well after their torment came to an end. We must learn from them and have faith that there are pathways even out of the nastiest of circumstances.</p>
<p>Our regular readers will understand that we prefer changing circumstances. Stay away from stress if you can.  But when that option is unavailable, fall back to neutralizing the potentially deadly consequences.</p>
<p>Many of our previous posts describe well-established techniques for reducing the effects of stress. For example, you can simply listen to the audio we provided in <a href="/2010/12/06/a-key-step-in-resilience-training-is-learning-deep-relaxation/">this post</a>. Or you can use the mindfulness meditation technique we described <a href="/2011/03/02/basic-mindfulness-technique/">here</a>. These are excellent starting points, and are likely to surprise you with their power to help you through distressing situations.</p>
<p>Even a little time spent practicing these techniques can have dramatic effects on mental and bodily reactions to stress. All of us should have such techniques as a routine part of our lives.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F01%2F09%2Fhazards-of-a-life-that-is-all-work-and-no-play%2F&amp;linkname=Hazards%20of%20a%20Life%20That%20is%20All%20Work%20and%20No%20Play." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Resilience and Happiness</title>
		<link>/2011/03/11/resilience-and-happiness/</link>
		<comments>/2011/03/11/resilience-and-happiness/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2011 04:32:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Happiness]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=609</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[About a year ago, I stumbled on a series of short YouTube videos, by Shawn Achor, on how to become happier. He is a delightful lecturer and his topic could hardly be more important. Achor taught a course on positive &#8230; <a href="/2011/03/11/resilience-and-happiness/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>About a year ago, I stumbled on a series of short <a href="http://www.google.com/#q=shawn+achor+youtube&amp;hl=en&amp;prmd=ivnso&amp;source=univ&amp;tbs=vid:1&amp;tbo=u&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=bqB5TZbzH8WEqgHJ2IDeBQ&amp;ved=0CCoQqwQ&amp;bav=on.2,or.r_gc.r_pw.&amp;fp=172639ded0fa996d">YouTube videos</a>, by Shawn Achor, on how to become happier. He is a delightful lecturer and his topic could hardly be more important. Achor taught a course on positive psychology at Harvard and one seventh of Harvard undergraduates enrolled in the course. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Positive_psychology">Positive psychology</a> is an approach that places its main emphasis on guiding people, including those who are already functioning well, to function at better levels.</p>
<p>After seeing Achor’s videos, I went in search of more information about new research on how people can learn to be more happy.</p>
<p>Achor mentions that a professor named Tal Ben Shahar had developed the positive psychology course so I looked for his work. Shahar has written several guides to increasing happiness. One was a book called “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Happier-Learn-Secrets-Lasting-Fulfillment/dp/0071492399/ref=ntt_at_ep_dpi_1">Happier</a>” and another was a book called “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Even-Happier-Gratitude-Journal-Fulfillment/dp/0071638032/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1299817033&amp;sr=8-1">Even Happier</a>”. Recently, Shawn Achor published a very readable book “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Happiness-Advantage-Principles-Psychology-Performance/dp/0307591549">The Happiness Advantage</a>: The Seven Principles of Positive Psychology That Fuel Success and Performance at Work”. It is a pleasant read, and a nice overview of current research on how to become happier.</p>
<p>What was most striking for me in these books was the remarkable overlap between what makes people happy and what makes them resilient. The overlap is so extensive that it would be reasonable to wonder whether the principles of happiness and the principles of resilience are the same.</p>
<p>To illustrate in a concise way, let’s consider the procedures Achor offers in his final summary in the <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vQt_WNewOKs">third YouTube video</a>. You can find it in the last few minutes of that video. They are:</p>
<p>1.      Gratitudes: taking note each day of several things that went well that day, and that you are grateful for.</p>
<p>2.      Journaling: Spending three minutes each day writing about something that went well.</p>
<p>3.      Simplifying your life and avoiding multitasking.</p>
<p>4.      Focusing on your strengths and building from them.</p>
<p>5.      Exercise.</p>
<p>6.      Meditation, specifically mindfulness meditation.</p>
<p>Numbers 1, 2, 5, and 6 are important aspects of our approach to resilience training. The remaining two are present in our training, but haven’t been central training principles. It would not be unreasonable to include them as central.</p>
<p>There are also many aspects of resilience training that are not in this list. For example, mastering the skill of deep relaxation, or learning how to breathe in a way that helps you stay reasonably cool under pressure. So resilience training seems to have a wider range than happiness training. Though resilience training helps you to function effectively under threat and stress, it also enhances life satisfaction when your baseline is fairly good.</p>
<p>In any case, it seems that when you are doing resilience training, you are also doing happiness training.</p>
<p>A reasonable question would be the old “chicken and egg” one. Does happiness cause resilience or does resilience cause happiness? The truth is, we don’t know. For the scientifically minded, it is a complicated question, but for those who simply want a better life all that matters is that the resilience training can be expected to make them both more resilient <em>and</em> happier.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2011%2F03%2F11%2Fresilience-and-happiness%2F&amp;linkname=Resilience%20and%20Happiness" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2011/03/11/resilience-and-happiness/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
