<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Effective Communication &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/effective-communication/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Resilience Factor Three: Understanding and Expressing Yourself.</title>
		<link>/2013/07/22/resilience-factor-three-understanding-and-expressing-yourself/</link>
		<comments>/2013/07/22/resilience-factor-three-understanding-and-expressing-yourself/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2013 00:26:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effective Communication]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Expressing Feelings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Focusing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Understanding]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1423</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[For people who are new to this blog, we have been reviewing the three core factors that underlie resilience. Probably some of the original readers have forgotten those factors, so this review may be useful to them too. In the &#8230; <a href="/2013/07/22/resilience-factor-three-understanding-and-expressing-yourself/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For people who are new to this blog, we have been reviewing the three core factors that underlie resilience. Probably some of the original readers have forgotten those factors, so this review may be useful to them too.</p>
<p>In the previous two posts we described the first two factors. Here we deal with the third and final factor. This factor has to do with expressing or articulating your inner reactions to distressing situations.</p>
<p>James Pennebaker and his colleagues did a series of studies that linked expressiveness to improved physical and mental health. This work was summarized in Pennebaker’s book “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Opening-Up-Healing-Expressing-Emotions/dp/1572302380/ref=sr_1_2?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1374426455&amp;sr=1-2&amp;keywords=james+pennebaker">Opening Up: The Healing Power of Confiding in Others</a>”. Basically, they showed that clarifying and speaking of your feelings about things that distress you led to improved mental and even physical health.</p>
<p>It is easy to confuse the self-expression Pennebaker and his colleagues advocate with other actions that can even be damaging, so we will clarify the details of how to be expressive.</p>
<h4><strong>What You Need to Do to Improve Your Self-Understanding and To Express It.</strong></h4>
<p><span id="more-1423"></span></p>
<p>To articulate your reactions, the first step is to understand them. You can, most likely, improve your understanding of your own reactions by way of inner dialogue. But there are advantages to having someone else also understand you.</p>
<p>Effective communication often happens in psychotherapy, but it also can take place in serious conversations with caring friends and other people who are good listeners, patient, and willing to let you know when they don’t understand.</p>
<p>If you have the right kind of listener, you might also have a dialogue that improves both their and your understanding of how you feel and why you feel as you do. It requires you to be very clear about your feelings because it is very hard to explain them in a way that effectively communicates them to others.</p>
<p>Both self-understanding and self-expression are of remarkable value in helping you keep in check what might otherwise be a damaging stress reaction.</p>
<h4><strong>Journaling</strong></h4>
<p>Though there is a clear advantage to effectively sharing your deep feelings with supportive friends, such sharing is not always easy or even possible.</p>
<p>In such cases, <a href="http://homepage.psy.utexas.edu/homepage/faculty/pennebaker/home2000/WritingandHealth.html">writing down how you have reacted to a troubling situation</a>, even without an outside listener, can be helpful. Studies have shown that writing a journal that focuses on expressing how you feel about hurtful experiences diminishes their negative consequences.</p>
<p>The following video has the founder of this journaling method showing how it is done:<br />
<iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/XsHIV9PxAV4?rel=0" frameborder="0" width="640" height="360"></iframe></p>
<h4><strong>A Special Kind of Focusing</strong></h4>
<p>Another method of clarifying feelings is through a process called Focusing. Privately talking to yourself about how you feel can be worth a lot. However, you have to focus in a specific way, emphasizing how you feel, and paying attention to your body’s reactions as you go through this inner dialogue.</p>
<p>The special kind of <a href="/2011/05/13/relieve-distress-with-extra-ordinary-focusing/">focusing</a> developed by Eugene Gendlin is an outstanding way to learn from those bodily reactions. This special kind of focusing is not easy to explain, and we think that <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Power-Focusing-Practical-Emotional-Self-Healing/dp/157224044X/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1374042330&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=ann+cornell+weiser">Ann Cornell Weiser</a> has done the best job we have seen in explaining how to focus.</p>
<p>We often think that just keeping quiet about our feelings and ignoring them can make them irrelevant to our mental and physiological functions. James Lynch has shown clearly that emotions that cannot be formulated in our mind enough to be spoken or written tend to be expressed in harmful physiological reactions, for example, in elevated blood pressure.</p>
<p>Lynch’s work is not as well known as it should be. If his books are not available in your library, you could get them on <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Language-Heart-Bodys-Response-Dialogue/dp/046503795X/ref=sr_1_5?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1374042815&amp;sr=1-5&amp;keywords=James+Lynch">Amazon</a>, but as of this writing they are available on <a href="http://www.abebooks.com/servlet/SearchResults?an=James+Lynch&amp;sts=t&amp;tn=The+language+of+the+heart">Abebooks</a> for as little as $1.00 plus a few dollars in shipping fees.</p>
<p>He did extensive research on people who did not respond well to medicines in reducing dangerously high blood pressure. He concluded that they were often expressing their emotions by way of these elevations of blood pressure.</p>
<p>Learning to understand our reactions and express them in words instead of bodily reactions helps us be more resilient. This is not the same as “<a href="/2011/04/18/articulation-of-feelings-is-not-the-same-as-venting/">getting our anger out</a>”.  That is more likely to be damaging than helpful.</p>
<p>Learning to understand what you really feel about what is going in your life is healthy but take care that you express those feeling in situations that do not unnecessarily trigger hostile reactions in others.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F07%2F21%2Fresilience-factor-three-understanding-and-expressing-yourself%2F&amp;linkname=Resilience%20Factor%20Three%3A%20Understanding%20and%20Expressing%20Yourself." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2013/07/22/resilience-factor-three-understanding-and-expressing-yourself/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Don’t Let Anger Give You a Heart Attack.</title>
		<link>/2013/05/29/dont-let-anger-give-you-a-heart-attack/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2013 03:55:42 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effective Communication]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Expressing Feelings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Focusing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience and Health]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1382</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[What should we do with anger bottled up inside of us? A recent article in the Washington Post discussed a serious effect of one option, that of letting out the raw anger, even to the point of throwing things and &#8230; <a href="/2013/05/29/dont-let-anger-give-you-a-heart-attack/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What should we do with anger bottled up inside of us? A <a href="http://articles.washingtonpost.com/2013-05-20/national/39387984_1_heart-attack-elizabeth-mostofsky-risk">recent article in the Washington Post</a> discussed a serious effect of one option, that of letting out the raw anger, even to the point of throwing things and threatening to hurt other people.</p>
<p>A common theme for some mental health professionals has been that we should get the anger out. For these therapists, sessions can consist of banging a pillow (usually representing  parents who were taken as having failed the client), with a bat that has many of the properties of a nasty club, but is in fact safely padded.</p>
<p>The Washington Post article describes a study in which about 4000 people who had heart attacks were asked about their experiences of anger. Heart attacks were twice as likely to occur after an episode of anger. There was a tendency for the heart attacks to occur within two hours of the anger episode.</p>
<p>Patients were also asked to rate how intense their anger episode had been, and the more intense the anger episode, the more likely patients were to have a heart attack.</p>
<p>So we have therapists trying to help us get the anger out versus research showing that expressing anger can lead to a heart attack.  So what are we to do? Should we bottled up our anger or express it?</p>
<p><span id="more-1382"></span></p>
<p>The Washington Post article says that “Bottling up of emotions is thought to harm both mind and body, but a new study suggests that doing the opposite may be no better.” What I want to do here is to be sure readers don’t take the options as limited to either “bottling up” or “doing the <span style="text-decoration: underline;">opposite</span>”, blowing your stack.</p>
<p>There is a lot of research indicating that, even though <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Anger-Misunderstood-Emotion-Carol-Tavris/dp/0671675230/ref=sr_1_3?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1369798270&amp;sr=1-3&amp;keywords=carol+tavris">letting out raw anger</a> harms you, striving to get clear about, articulate, and express your emotions has positive effects on the mind and body, not to mention on social relationships.</p>
<p>This is very different from blowing your stack or “<a href="/2011/04/18/articulation-of-feelings-is-not-the-same-as-venting/">venting</a>”, which has long been known to be an ineffective and typically damaging way to deal with distressing experiences.</p>
<p>It is important to learn how to <a href="/2011/05/03/focusing-a-highly-effective-way-to-resolve-distress/">understand your feelings when distressed</a>, and to articulate them without unnecessarily alienating others, especially others who might be able to help you minimize any potential damage coming from your stress. “Blowing your stack” is almost certain to amplify the impact of stress.</p>
<p>With stress amplification, your response to stress increases the physiological responses that make heart attacks more likely. That kind of response also may alienate your potential support systems and thus make   you less resilient and more vulnerable. It’s amazing how many people follow this totally ineffective pattern of stress management.</p>
<p>Your anger is there to protect you. It helps you to push against obstacles that can block you from reaching your goals, including people who are trying to dominate you in order to reach their own goals.</p>
<p>If you use anger well, it will be a powerful source of energy to help you reach your goals.</p>
<p>If, instead, you amplify the impact of your stress, you become your own enemy, often your own worst enemy.</p>
<p>To deal with anger you should not act on it. Don’t let your brain’s motor system rule you. You should attend to the anger and find out what it means.</p>
<p>To do this, you have to <a title="open a mental space in which you can gain a deep understanding of why you are angry" href="/2011/05/03/focusing-a-highly-effective-way-to-resolve-distress/">open a mental space in which you can gain a deep understanding of why you are angry</a>.</p>
<p>That way you are more likely to move toward your sensible goals instead of undermining yourself.</p>
<p>You should take time to attend to your angry reactions, focusing first on what you feel in your body.  Visit with those bodily reactions until they can be expressed in words.</p>
<p>When you do that, you shift from unwise, primitive commands from the parts of your brain that lead to mindless action. Instead you pull together and synthesize thoughts with emotions and then take action.</p>
<p>That synthesis is most likely to be the creative source of actions that are both wise and effective.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F05%2F29%2Fdont-let-anger-give-you-a-heart-attack%2F&amp;linkname=Don%E2%80%99t%20Let%20Anger%20Give%20You%20a%20Heart%20Attack." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>When Life Becomes a Tsunami of Stress</title>
		<link>/2012/03/14/when-life-becomes-a-tsunami-of-stress/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2012 15:00:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Benefits of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Effective Communication]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Expressing Feelings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Physical Contact]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=971</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[One test of the usefulness of our program and techniques is whether we really practice what we preach. We are not perfect models of what we believe in, nor are we people of super-resilience. I think in an earlier post &#8230; <a href="/2012/03/14/when-life-becomes-a-tsunami-of-stress/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One test of the usefulness of our program and techniques is whether we really practice what we preach. We are not perfect models of what we believe in, nor are we people of super-resilience. I think in an earlier post I acknowledged that my life was far from handing me a cornucopia of resilience skills, and I think I am safe in saying that would also be true for Debbie.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, there were things in our early experiences that helped us develop a fighting spirit and a sense that we can improve by learning what we need to do and doggedly putting what we learned into practice.</p>
<p>For some months we have been dealing with extremely stressful situations. I cannot be explicit about them because that would violate the privacy of others, including others that we care deeply about. I think it’s okay if I say that it involves the approaching death of someone who has been important part of our lives. This is aggravated by dementia of a beloved member of our family, and intense pressure put on even the tiniest of fractures between members of the extended family.</p>
<p>So what has helped us to deal with these things?</p>
<p><span id="more-971"></span></p>
<p>We have both increased our use of deep relaxation. We listen to one of the short audio recordings we designed ourselves, narrated by Debbie. These take only 10-20 minutes.</p>
<p>Even fitting this into our pressured schedules can be hard, but it is well worth the effort. These sessions take us to a level of relaxation that drastically reduces our stress responses.</p>
<p>In spite of there being a lot of interference with sticking to exercise regimens, we both have continued to exercise. Exercise reduces stress reactions in many ways; it reduces stress enhancing bodily chemicals and increases natural bodily chemicals that calm and sooth us.</p>
<p>One of our ways of exercising is to hike in wooded areas which we are fortunate to have tucked away even in our metropolitan area. We usually take our dog, Luke, and his intense enjoyment of being off leash in a place full of surprises and fascinating odors, helps us to experience the joys of being in nature.</p>
<p>Speaking of our dog, he shows clear signs of feeling our distressing experiences very deeply. Dogs, and many other animals, are geniuses at sensing distress in members of their “pack”. So we decided to have what (I blush to admit this) we have dubbed “lovey-dovey time”, just before bed time. He quickly learned that when we say “It’s lovey-dovey time”, both of us are going to lie down beside him and massage and pet him for a while. He, who is normally a very rough and tumble dog, becomes soft and gentle during those sessions.</p>
<p>Research shows that when you pet an animal, the animal’s heart rate and blood pressure go down, and so does yours. Debbie and I both have marveled at how much better we feel during and after these sessions. We had read about it in research studies, but experiencing it is something else.</p>
<p>Debbie and I have an understanding that we’ve got each other’s backs, and that is a core purpose in our lives.</p>
<p>In our last post, we discussed the positive impact of emotional support at home. We have extended that beyond home.</p>
<ul>
<li>Every night we go through a debriefing between the two of us, thus augmenting each other’s individual perspective.</li>
<li>We have extended this theme of support to the extended family by planning coping strategies as a group, with everyone’s viewpoint getting a hearing.</li>
<li>We have steadily worked to create a store of past experiences of support and trust throughout the extended family, so we can speak more frankly with each other than would otherwise be possible.</li>
<li>Whenever possible we have been cooperative with family members who might have reason to oppose us.</li>
</ul>
<p>We still have to take hits; our phone rings over and over again, often making it impossible to relax at night. That is one of the costs incurred by being positive and constructive with all of the people who have a stake in this. Because we have developed our means of individual support and support of each other, we can afford these intrusions, even though they add to our stress load.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2012%2F03%2F14%2F971%2F&amp;linkname=When%20Life%20Becomes%20a%20Tsunami%20of%20Stress" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Love and Support You Get From Others Enhances Your Health and Well-Being.</title>
		<link>/2012/02/29/the-love-and-support-you-get-from-others-enhances-your-health-and-well-being/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 Feb 2012 15:19:31 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effective Communication]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=965</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[So far our posts have emphasized building your inner resilience. In particular, we have emphasized cultivating positive attitudes, practicing skills that help you minimize your stress reactions, and, learning to be compassionate with yourself. All of these are things you &#8230; <a href="/2012/02/29/the-love-and-support-you-get-from-others-enhances-your-health-and-well-being/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>So far our posts have emphasized building your inner resilience. In particular, we have emphasized cultivating positive attitudes, practicing skills that help you minimize your stress reactions, and, learning to be compassionate with yourself. All of these are things you can do by yourself.</p>
<p>But resilience is not all inside you; you are not an island. The people you are connected to are centrally important to your resilience. There is much scientific evidence that your health and well-being are strongly influenced by the people who are linked to you.</p>
<p>A recent example came to our attention and triggered this post. It showed clearly that better work performance and success depended on whether people had strong emotional support at home.</p>
<p><span id="more-965"></span></p>
<p>In a <a href="http://www.orlandosentinel.com/features/career/sfl-stressed-out-working-couples,0,7079625.story">recent study</a> by Wayne Hochwarter and his colleagues at Florida State University, emotional support at home was linked to:</p>
<ul>
<li>A 50 percent greater satisfaction with marriage.</li>
<li>A 33 percent greater likelihood of having better relationships with co-workers.</li>
<li>A 25 percent greater likelihood of being able to concentrate at work and a 25 percent lower chance of feeling fatigued at work and at home.</li>
<li>A 30 percent likelihood of less guilt associated with home/family neglect.</li>
<li>A 30 percent lower likelihood of being critical of others (spouse, children) at home.</li>
</ul>
<p>People who have emotional support are clearly at an advantage, and Dr. Hochwarter’s work gives is just one tiny bit of the large body of evidence for that.</p>
<p>There are also personal skills that help you make the most of the emotional support you have. You can help your supporters support you. Often the people who are available for support do not really know what you need. A good example of this from our experience is that women seeking support from their husbands may not want to be told what to do. More often they want somebody to listen to them and be on their side. Husbands tend to think that supporting their wives means telling them how they should handle the situation.</p>
<p>What is our “take home” message?</p>
<ul>
<li>Support from others is very important to many aspects of your well-being. Friends and family are also a major resilience resource.</li>
<li>If you are not getting the support you need, you may be able to coach potential supporters on how to do better.</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2012%2F02%2F29%2Fthe-love-and-support-you-get-from-others-enhances-your-health-and-well-being%2F&amp;linkname=The%20Love%20and%20Support%20You%20Get%20From%20Others%20Enhances%20Your%20Health%20and%20Well-Being." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Articulation of Feelings Is Not the Same as Venting</title>
		<link>/2011/04/18/articulation-of-feelings-is-not-the-same-as-venting/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2011 03:40:33 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effective Communication]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Expressing Feelings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Understanding]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=709</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In the last post, I pointed out the importance of clarifying and expressing your feelings of distress. Understanding how you feel about a distressing situation and expressing it in a safe context can make you feel better and stay healthier.

For years many in the mental health field have encouraged people to blow off steam, let out their anger, and get things off their chest. It was a model that implied that, when we are upset, we are like a boiler that is overheated, and that will blow up if it does not release some of the pressure. But humans are much more complex than boilers. <a href="/2011/04/18/articulation-of-feelings-is-not-the-same-as-venting/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the last post, I pointed out the importance of clarifying and expressing your feelings of distress. Understanding how you feel about a distressing situation and expressing it in a safe context can make you feel better and stay healthier.</p>
<p>For years many in the mental health field have encouraged people to blow off steam, let out their anger, and get things off their chest. It was a model that implied that, when we are upset, we are like a boiler that is overheated, and that will blow up if it does not release some of the pressure. But humans are much more complex than boilers.</p>
<p>This way of handling distress, which is called “venting”, is <strong><em>not</em></strong> likely to make you feel better or become healthier.</p>
<p>Carol Tavris and Elliot Aronson gave a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Mistakes-Were-Made-But-Not/dp/0156033909/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;s=books&amp;qid=1303097019&amp;sr=1-1">nice, concise summary of the effects of venting:</a></p>
<p>“…when people vent they often feel worse, pump up their blood pressure, and make themselves even angrier. Venting is especially likely to backfire if a person commits an aggressive act against another person directly…”.</p>
<p>There are commonly social ramifications of venting. Venting or dumping strong negative feelings on other people is likely to lead to reactions on their part that will create more stress. People have a way of making a person who is venting and dumping on them pay a price for doing so. And so the original stress gets amplified instead of being brought under control.</p>
<p>More careful therapists were likely to have people “get their anger out” by having them do things like yelling and screaming at pillows or beating on them with bats wrapped in foam rubber. This avoids antagonizing others and thereby amplifying stress.</p>
<p>However, if you don’t have a deep inner connection to your words and actions, these methods are not likely to resolve the issues. This pounding and yelling is probably, at best, a way to get a bit of exercise.</p>
<p>Fully articulating feelings tends to produce healthy outcomes, e.g. <a href="../2011/04/13/control-distress-by-understanding-and-expressing-yourself/">fewer physical symptoms</a>, <a href="http://homepage.psy.utexas.edu/homepage/faculty/pennebaker/reprints/Kiecolt.pdf">fewer visits to health care facilities, and improved immunity</a>. This articulating, unlike venting, involves a serious look at what has you upset and how you feel about it. You should come away from the experience with a sense of greater self-understanding and of relief.</p>
<p>The following are some clues that you are engaging in unproductive venting:</p>
<ul>
<li>When you vent, you do not      feel a sense of progressing toward recovery; you can go over and over the      problem without moving forward at all.</li>
<li>Your inner tension is      likely to improve little if at all, and often will rise.</li>
<li>You don’t get a feeling of      deepening your understanding of yourself and why you are reacting as you      are.</li>
<li>You don’t get a glimmer of      how you might proceed to improve the situation or live well in spite of      it.</li>
<li>Commonly the focus is on      others, on how awful and wicked they are.</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2011%2F04%2F18%2Farticulation-of-feelings-is-not-the-same-as-venting%2F&amp;linkname=Articulation%20of%20Feelings%20Is%20Not%20the%20Same%20as%20Venting" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Control Distress By Understanding and Expressing Yourself</title>
		<link>/2011/04/13/control-distress-by-understanding-and-expressing-yourself/</link>
		<comments>/2011/04/13/control-distress-by-understanding-and-expressing-yourself/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2011 15:40:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effective Communication]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Expressing Feelings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Understanding]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=639</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In this post, I want to discuss the third factor we identified in our research on personal resilience. It involves two things: Attending to and clarifying your feelings about distressing experiences. Expressing those clarified feelings in a safe way that &#8230; <a href="/2011/04/13/control-distress-by-understanding-and-expressing-yourself/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this post, I want to discuss the third factor we <a href="../../../../../2011/01/11/the-three-core-factors-that-can-make-you-more-resilient/">identified in our research on personal resilience</a>. It involves two things:</p>
<ul>
<li>Attending to and clarifying      your feelings about distressing experiences.</li>
<li>Expressing those clarified      feelings in a safe way that enables you to feel clearer and better about      them.</li>
</ul>
<p>As with the other two factors, this one has been the object of much research. <a href="http://homepage.psy.utexas.edu/homepage/faculty/pennebaker/Reprints/index.htm">James Pennebaker</a> was the researcher who first identified it as important. He and his  co-workers found that women who reported having been sexually abused  also reported, later in life, a markedly elevated number of symptoms of  ill health. However, if they had opportunities to <strong><em>express</em></strong> their feelings about the experience, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Opening-Up-Healing-Expressing-Emotions/dp/1572302380/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1302704279&amp;sr=1-1">the symptoms were markedly diminished</a>.</p>
<p>There is good research that supports the idea that expressing feelings reduces bodily responses to stress. For example, <a href="http://ist-socrates.berkeley.edu/%7Eucbpl/docs/51-Hiding%20Feelings97.pdf">Robert Levenson</a> found that people who participated in an experiment in which they were  required to watch a gruesome video of the amputation of a human limb had  stronger physiological reactions to the experience if they were also  asked to <strong><em>hide</em></strong> those reactions. (The video was gruesome enough that even those told to conceal their reactions were not fully able to comply.)</p>
<p>This  and similar research indicates that it is a healthy thing to spend the  time and effort to understand your feelings and to find a way to  articulate them.</p>
<p>A very good method is to talk to a well-trusted  friend. Of course, that kind of friend is often not available. Be  careful about expressing your private reactions to people who are not  solidly on your side. Instead of helping, it can make things worse,  amplify stress, and turn a small problem into a big one.</p>
<p>Fortunately, research shows us that <strong><em><a href="http://homepage.psy.utexas.edu/HomePage/Faculty/Pennebaker/Reprints/P1997.pdf">journaling privately to articulate how you feel about bad experiences also works</a></em></strong>. If you are in doubt about the supportiveness of potential listeners, it might be wise to use journaling.</p>
<p>In either case, focus on how you <strong><em>feel</em></strong> about the distressing situation. Do not worry about your style,  grammar, etc. Clarifying what you feel is the crux of the matter.</p>
<p>Later we will have more to say about how to <strong><em>listen to yourself</em></strong> enough to clarify your feelings about bad situations.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2011%2F04%2F13%2Fcontrol-distress-by-understanding-and-expressing-yourself%2F&amp;linkname=Control%20Distress%20By%20Understanding%20and%20Expressing%20Yourself" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2011/04/13/control-distress-by-understanding-and-expressing-yourself/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
