<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>Comments on: Focusing: A Highly Effective Way to Resolve Distress</title>
	<atom:link href="/2011/05/03/focusing-a-highly-effective-way-to-resolve-distress/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/2011/05/03/focusing-a-highly-effective-way-to-resolve-distress/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2016 16:41:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>By: Jerry Sheridan</title>
		<link>/2011/05/03/focusing-a-highly-effective-way-to-resolve-distress/?#comment-618</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2011 04:47:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=722#comment-618</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Oops! I didn&#039;t get it right. I very much want  to encourage those who need to learn how to deal with painful experiences to comment so they can get help from people who know what is likely to work.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Oops! I didn&#8217;t get it right. I very much want  to encourage those who need to learn how to deal with painful experiences to comment so they can get help from people who know what is likely to work.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>By: Jerry Sheridan</title>
		<link>/2011/05/03/focusing-a-highly-effective-way-to-resolve-distress/?#comment-617</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2011 04:42:52 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=722#comment-617</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Reading these two comments next to each other is a delight. This is the kind of thing I hoped for when I decided to do this blog. It&#039;s not all about my telling people what to do. It&#039;s about building a community of people who know a lot about the topics that come up, and, just as important, of people who just want to know how to deal with distress.

I hope you will continue to comment and others will join into a community of people who want to learn how to be more resilient and to help others to do the same.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Reading these two comments next to each other is a delight. This is the kind of thing I hoped for when I decided to do this blog. It&#8217;s not all about my telling people what to do. It&#8217;s about building a community of people who know a lot about the topics that come up, and, just as important, of people who just want to know how to deal with distress.</p>
<p>I hope you will continue to comment and others will join into a community of people who want to learn how to be more resilient and to help others to do the same.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>By: Elmar Kruithoff</title>
		<link>/2011/05/03/focusing-a-highly-effective-way-to-resolve-distress/?#comment-614</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Elmar Kruithoff]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2011 15:41:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=722#comment-614</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yes, this is also my experience: Focusing goes beyond feelings; it is not about feelings at all, but about inviting and working with a bodily felt sense. Gendlin writes, that Focusing enables one &quot;to live from a deeper place than just your thoughts and feelings&quot; (p.4 in his book &quot;Focusing&quot;). And this level of experiencing, felt sensing, is only accessible when one is (again and again) able to be self-in-presence, a term introduced by Ann Weiser Cornell and Barbara McGavin. And the qualities of presence are not only empathy, listening, patience - but a combination with strength and power. Otherwise one would not reach the level of felt sensing but become stuck in feeling the same feelings over and over again]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yes, this is also my experience: Focusing goes beyond feelings; it is not about feelings at all, but about inviting and working with a bodily felt sense. Gendlin writes, that Focusing enables one &#8220;to live from a deeper place than just your thoughts and feelings&#8221; (p.4 in his book &#8220;Focusing&#8221;). And this level of experiencing, felt sensing, is only accessible when one is (again and again) able to be self-in-presence, a term introduced by Ann Weiser Cornell and Barbara McGavin. And the qualities of presence are not only empathy, listening, patience &#8211; but a combination with strength and power. Otherwise one would not reach the level of felt sensing but become stuck in feeling the same feelings over and over again</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>By: Cheryl</title>
		<link>/2011/05/03/focusing-a-highly-effective-way-to-resolve-distress/?#comment-522</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cheryl]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2011 07:46:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=722#comment-522</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Agreed.  I think this is a healthy way as long as you understand too that you have power over your feelings and do not have to succumb to them.   You can allow yourself to experience them, understand them and to move beyond them as well.  Moving beyond what you have experienced does not mean you are dismissing it&#039;s significance in your life.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Agreed.  I think this is a healthy way as long as you understand too that you have power over your feelings and do not have to succumb to them.   You can allow yourself to experience them, understand them and to move beyond them as well.  Moving beyond what you have experienced does not mean you are dismissing it&#8217;s significance in your life.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
</channel>
</rss>
