<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Stress &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/stress/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The Green Space Solution</title>
		<link>/2015/07/28/the-green-space-solution/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2015 17:27:31 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stress]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stressful Environments]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1949</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[People who are being damaged by stress are often in situations they see as unchangeable. Frequently they try meditation, take a Yoga class or go to lectures on dealing with stress. All of these can help, but let’s take another &#8230; <a href="/2015/07/28/the-green-space-solution/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>People who are being damaged by stress are often in situations they see as unchangeable. Frequently they try meditation, take a Yoga class or go to lectures on dealing with stress. All of these can help, but let’s take another look at the possibility of changing the stressful environments that are triggering stress reactions.</p>
<p>If we think of these situations as a whole, it is very understandable why they seem unchangeable. If your job is the problem, it may also pay well or have other benefits that are hard to replace. Similarly, when the main source of stress is a marriage, you may have to face risks of damage to children, being thrown into a much more difficult financial situation, or getting trapped in a life of loneliness.</p>
<p>So the idea that exiting your situation is hopeless makes sense.</p>
<p>However, all of this fails to consider the potential of small changes. If you can’t get out of your situation, small changes in it may be a good alternative.</p>
<p><span id="more-1949"></span><br />
We have never found a better concise account of the power of small changes than the following quotation from Susan and Larry Terkel’s book “Small Change”:</p>
<p>“Small change adds up. This is worth repeating: small change adds up. Empty your small change in a jar every day, and watch the total add up over time. Make small changes in your daily habits – such as your meals or snacks, your relationships, your work, or your leisure- and watch those changes gradually accumulate into a much healthier, happier, and more satisfying life.”</p>
<p>“An angle of only one degree is difficult to draw on a piece of paper. It is too small. If a flight from New York to Los Angeles is off course by just one degree, the plane will arrive closer to Tijuana, Mexico, than Los Angeles.”<br />
“Small changes can get us back on course as easily as the can lead us off course”.</p>
<p>We discussed small change in several earlier posts, e.g. here and here. The concept came back to mind recently when Gretchen Reynolds published an article in the New York Times on the benefits of being in “green space”, the outdoors where the view includes trees and plants.</p>
<p>It is easy to discard the idea of adding time in green space to your life. It seems to be a minor benefit.</p>
<p>However, there is an abundance of research confirming that the experience of green space, even something as minimal as seeing that space through a window, is linked to a wide variety of positive effects. These effects include such things as buffering against the negative health impact of stressful life events, reducing stress hormones, reducing brooding over what is wrong with ourselves and our lives, relieving depression, reducing anxiety, etc.</p>
<p>Ms. Reynolds article was mainly about research in which a randomly selected half of volunteers were asked to take a stroll in a green space and the other half walked the same length on an urban path near a busy highway.</p>
<p>The researchers found that the group that walked in green space showed a reduction in obsessive rumination about themselves and their lives, but those who walked in the urban environment did not.</p>
<p>The investigators also measured activity in a brain area, the subgenual gyrus, which previous research implicated in sadness, the onset of depressive episodes and other mental disorders. Walking in green space reduced activity in the subgenual gyrus. Walking in the urban environment did not.</p>
<p>If something as simple as a walk in a “green” park can enhance your ability to deal with life’s challenges, there are probably many other aspects of your life situation that can be changed and give your resilience a valuable edge in the effort to live well.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2015%2F07%2F28%2Fthe-green-space-solution%2F&amp;linkname=The%20Green%20Space%20Solution" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Don’t Let Overwhelming Distress Take You Down.</title>
		<link>/2011/12/14/dont-let-overwhelming-distress-take-you-down/</link>
		<comments>/2011/12/14/dont-let-overwhelming-distress-take-you-down/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2011 18:30:51 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stress]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=883</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[When one distressing thing happens after another, it’s natural to be overwhelmed. Though it is natural, that doesn’t mean it is inevitable. There are a few things you can do to keep these stressful things from piling up, but many, &#8230; <a href="/2011/12/14/dont-let-overwhelming-distress-take-you-down/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When one distressing thing happens after another, it’s natural to be overwhelmed. Though it is natural, that doesn’t mean it is inevitable. There are a few things you can do to keep these stressful things from piling up, but many, even most of them are out of your control. However, you CAN have control over your reactions to them. In this post we outline ways to reign in your reactions to stress and avoid becoming overwhelmed. We include links that provide more detail about</p>
<p>Here are the steps to take:</p>
<p><span id="more-883"></span></p>
<h3>Before the stress becomes overwhelming.</h3>
<p>If you are not already overwhelmed, you should prepare by learning some basic skills to neutralize distress.</p>
<ol>
<li>Breath Control: Learn how      to give yourself immediate relief by coaching yourself in the use of <a href="../../../../../2011/06/02/tactical-breathing-can-stop-stress-on-the-spot/">tactical      breathing</a>. Breath control is a central tool we have to minimize how      our bodies respond to stress.
<ol>
<li>Practice breathing all       the way down to your abdomen. If your belly doesn’t move out as you       breathe in, you are not getting full breaths.</li>
<li>Besides breathing deeply,       train yourself to extend the exhalation phase of the breathing cycle. An       easy way to do this is by mentally saying the word “relax” in any extended       way “reeeeelaaaax” as you breathe out. That way you get more effective       breathing and also, by using the word “relax”, suggest to your mind that       it shift to a relaxed state.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Self-Soothing: Train      yourself to do <a href="../../../../../2010/11/04/natural-stress-defeaters/#more-389">what      soothes and calms you</a> and start it at the first signs of stress. Look      at the link and identify some for you to practice for calming and      self-soothing. When something riles you, think of it as an <strong><em>opportunity</em></strong> to practice resilience skills.</li>
<li>Listen to soothing,      relaxing audios (which is a method we, ourselves, routinely use when the      going gets tough).  There is a <a href="../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2010/12/Tense-Relax.mp3">free      audio</a> on this blog that works well, but use whatever works for you.</li>
<li><a href="../../../../../2011/01/06/from-pessimism-to-optimismthree-basic-techniques/">Self-Talk</a>:      Remind yourself that you have survived other harsh situations, and so you have      reason to believe you can handle this as well.
<ol>
<li>Talk to yourself in       calming ways. Imagine how an ideal parent who loves you would talk to you       and talk to yourself that way.</li>
<li>Have compassion for yourself;       it only makes things worse to criticize yourself when under stress. You       need someone on your side, and you should definitely be on your own side.</li>
<li>Don’t know how to be       caring and support yourself?  Well,       try “acting”; maybe you aren’t ready for Broadway, but you can probably       manage this. The more you do it, the more natural it will become.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Social Support: If you are      overwhelmed or close to it, <a href="../../../../../?s=neurotic+stupidity">your mind is probably      overloaded</a>, so you need outside help. Look for people who can help you      to stay in control when you are becoming overwhelmed. Call on them when      you are distressed, <a href="../../../../../2011/04/13/control-distress-by-understanding-and-expressing-yourself/">talk      things out</a>, and ask for help when you need it.
<ol>
<li>If you haven’t       established a base of supporters, start right now to develop one. Be       generous in giving others support so they feel okay investing their       energy in supporting you.</li>
<li>Encourage and teach your       supporters to have a clear sense of how to meet your needs. Supporters       need to be <strong><em>told</em></strong> what kind of support you need. Many people end up       disappointed with the support they get, but they haven’t really <strong><em>asked</em></strong> for what they need.</li>
<li>When you are distressed,       it is often tempting to direct your anger and frustration toward people       who would like to support you. Do not discourage your supporters. If       possible, be <em>their</em> cheerleader       and their coach. You will probably get a good return on your investment       if you do that.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Use Your Imagination: If      you don’t get the needed support from others, imagine yourself in      supportive situations
<ol>
<li>Picture and ponder scenes       in which you have felt good and at peace. “Ponder” means that you stay       with these imaginings for a while, long enough to let them have an effect       on both your thoughts and your feelings.</li>
<li>Imagine yourself with a       person, real or imaginary, who really cares about you and backs you up.</li>
<li>If you can’t imagine, or       feel uncomfortable imagining a supportive <em>person</em>, try imagining a caring pet who loves you unconditionally.</li>
<li>If you can’t imagine a       supportive animal, imagine yourself sitting in a park resting your back       against a tree. Take in the feeling that the earth supports you and the       tree has your back.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Exercise: Take a brisk      walk; it can <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Calm-Energy-People-Regulate-Exercise/dp/0195163397/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1323470751&amp;sr=1-1">calm      and energize you</a>. A brisk walk is enough; you do not have to prepare      for a marathon. Years ago Dr. Herbert DeVries did a study showing that a      15 minute brisk walk resulted in greater relaxation than valium. If  you can devote more time and energy to      the exercise, you will probably get more relief up to a point. You      probably already know the routine cautions about checking with a physician      before you start a new exercise program. This is just in case there are medical      reasons to limit exertion. Most of us can do modest amounts of exercise      without any significant risks of nasty side effects, but it’s risky to      make big changes in our level of exertion without consulting with someone      who knows our true physical state.</li>
</ol>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2011%2F12%2F14%2Fdon%25E2%2580%2599t-let-overwhelming-distress-take-you-down%2F&amp;linkname=Don%E2%80%99t%20Let%20Overwhelming%20Distress%20Take%20You%20Down." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2011/12/14/dont-let-overwhelming-distress-take-you-down/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
