<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>How Hard Is It To Change Resilience? &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/how-hard-is-it-to-change-resilience/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>More Resilience Training Can Produce Richer, More Powerful Results.</title>
		<link>/2014/08/04/many-resilience-techniques-can-be-brief-and-easy-but-more-training-can-produce-richer-more-powerful-results/</link>
		<comments>/2014/08/04/many-resilience-techniques-can-be-brief-and-easy-but-more-training-can-produce-richer-more-powerful-results/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2014 18:55:57 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[How Hard Is It To Change Resilience?]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1709</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[We have often pointed out, maybe even emphasized, how easy it is to learn techniques that are helpful in resisting and recovering from stress. The techniques are not only easy, but are typically pleasant and comforting. Most resilience training methods &#8230; <a href="/2014/08/04/many-resilience-techniques-can-be-brief-and-easy-but-more-training-can-produce-richer-more-powerful-results/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We have often pointed out, maybe even emphasized, how <em>easy</em> it is to learn techniques that are helpful in resisting and recovering from stress.</p>
<p>The techniques are not only easy, but are typically pleasant and comforting. Most resilience training methods make you feel somewhere in the range of good to very good.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, too many people practice for a while, but then get embedded in the demands of ordinary life and never get to see how rich the benefits might be if they continued over the long term.</p>
<p>Take <a href="/2010/12/06/a-key-step-in-resilience-training-is-learning-deep-relaxation/">deep relaxation</a> as an example. A large majority of people who try basic methods of deep relaxation find the states they induce both useful and pleasant.</p>
<p>They should consider persisting at least a little longer. For some methods of relaxation and calming, there is evidence that practice can continue to improve, even over many years.</p>
<p>A striking example is the work of a Japanese researcher, Tomio Hirai. He studied changes in brain waves that take place when people practice Zen Meditation. (It is called “Zazen” and is essentially identical to the currently popular “Mindfulness Meditation”).</p>
<p><span id="more-1709"></span></p>
<p>Zazen involves sitting in a stable posture and attending to your breathing. The goal is to do that and nothing else.</p>
<p>Beginners count their inhalations and exhalations from one to ten; then they go back to one and start over again. If you try this for a while you will find yourself counting numbers like “42”, indicating that your mind has wandered without your noticing it. When this happens you just calmly go back to one.</p>
<p>As time goes on, brain wave patterns shift from fast to slow (an indication of calm, deep relaxation, the antithesis of a stress response, a “relaxation response”).</p>
<p>Hirai found that even after decades of practice meditators <a href="http://is.muni.cz/www/178816/EEG_and_Zazen.pdf">are still improving</a>.</p>
<p>But their commitment to meditation is not just to deal with life’s frustrations. As part of a Buddhist tradition, it is done to achieve some form of “enlightenment”, a profound and highly beneficial readjustment of their perceptions of themselves and of the world.</p>
<p>Zen masters recognize and accept that many people who practice Zazen, do so in order to function better in their ordinary lives. The term “<a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=KczYq22WAeYC&amp;pg=PA49&amp;lpg=PA49&amp;dq=bompu+zen&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=igVZJ2sn_3&amp;sig=7PRrXKcW1ep0fUHZCShYKcRc_cc&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=3rfdU_POGKLT8AGjvoCgCg&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CFIQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=bompu%20zen&amp;f=false">Bompu Zen</a>” is used for this more basic approach.</p>
<p>What resilience training normally aims to achieve is at the level of Bompu Zen. This does not meant that it is <em>merely</em> bompu Zen. We, for example, include the most effective techniques from a wide variety of traditions and other sources, as long as their effectiveness is robust enough to be empirically confirmed.</p>
<p>It appears that “the sky is the limit” when it comes to how far you can go with your training. Whether you reach for the sky depends on your ultimate goals. It depends on whether you seek a radically new perspective on the world and your life or just want to deal more effectively with life’s familiar demands, which is, incidentally, the humble goal we have chosen for this blog.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F08%2F04%2Fmany-resilience-techniques-can-be-brief-and-easy-but-more-training-can-produce-richer-more-powerful-results%2F&amp;linkname=Many%20Resilience%20Techniques%20Can%20Be%20%20Brief%20and%20Easy%2C%20but%20More%20Training%20Can%20Produce%20Richer%2C%20More%20Powerful%20Results." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2014/08/04/many-resilience-techniques-can-be-brief-and-easy-but-more-training-can-produce-richer-more-powerful-results/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>How Much Training Does It Take to Develop a Resilience Skill?</title>
		<link>/2014/07/15/how-much-training-does-it-take-to-develop-a-resilience-skill/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2014 20:03:43 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[How Hard Is It To Change Resilience?]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1685</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Our core purpose at OnResilience is to explain how and why you should train to be more resilient. We want to help people learn techniques that can help them get through difficult situations and come out able to at least &#8230; <a href="/2014/07/15/how-much-training-does-it-take-to-develop-a-resilience-skill/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Our core purpose at OnResilience is to explain how and why you should train to be more resilient. We want to help people learn techniques that can help them get through difficult situations and come out able to at least stay in the game, and maybe also having learned things that make them more effective in handling difficulties to come.</p>
<p>Debbie and I both know from published research, our own personal experiences, and our work as trainers and therapists that the techniques we teach will help most people to deal more effectively with painful, threatening situations .</p>
<p>A fortunate few can get benefits from just a few training sessions. But most people need more help, and, especially, more practice than that. However, it is safe to say that no one who neglects practice will reach their potential even if they are in the above-mentioned “fortunate few”.</p>
<p>Why do so many people fail to practice resilience-inducing procedures?</p>
<p>A possible reason is that people in technically advanced parts of the world have become accustomed to treatments that require little effort. Most of us have gotten prescriptions that quickly relieved us of distressing diseases, and we may tend now to expect a quick, almost effortless resolution to any of our problems. The old Alka-Seltzer line, “Relief is just a swallow away”, says it all.</p>
<p>That “take a pill” model is usually not a good one for making changes in the way the mind, or, if you prefer, the brain, influences the body. Nor does it work particularly well if we need to maneuver our way through complicated situations, such as a troubled marriage. In these situations, many factors influence what happens, and these factors may include some that can be influenced by chemicals, but we are far from having pills, injections, or surgical procedures that do much to turn complex situations from bad to good.</p>
<p>For the most part, neither can listening to a lecture or two, or practicing mind-body techniques a few times.</p>
<p>To get the most out of resilience training you need “practice, practice, and practice”.</p>
<p>But many, many people just do not see any room in their available <em>time</em> to fit practice in.</p>
<p><span id="more-1685"></span></p>
<p>Both Debbie and I have “been there and done that”.  We understand how hard it can be to find the time and energy to practice.</p>
<p>So, granting that we have to practice in order to see what resilience techniques can really do to make our lives better, <strong><em>how much</em></strong> practice is required?</p>
<p>Malcolm Gladwell in his best-selling book, “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Outliers-Story-Success-Malcolm-Gladwell/dp/0316017930/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1405436934&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=gladwell+outliers">Outliers</a>” concluded that mastering a skill requires practicing 10,000 times. Fortunately, in the video below, the speaker makes a case for 20 practice sessions as enough to reach the modest goals most of us set for ourselves.</p>
<p>Gladwell has been a brilliant commentator on life, but this encouraging video should help those of you who cannot fit that much practice into the stream of your life. It deals with people who, like most of us, are not aiming for goals that would make us world champions, but, rather for goals that make our lives better and, perhaps goals that make us stand out as notably good at what we are trying to do.</p>
<p>Watch the video for encouraging information on what you can gain from fairly modest effort.</p>
<p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/5MgBikgcWnY" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Magic of Small Changes</title>
		<link>/2013/08/27/the-magic-of-small-changes/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2013 03:06:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[How Hard Is It To Change Resilience?]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1470</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[There is an unusual poem by award-winning poet, Mona van Duyn, which illustrates some key aspects of resilience. Please read the poem. I know that many people do not like poetry, and see the core of it as rhyming. This &#8230; <a href="/2013/08/27/the-magic-of-small-changes/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There is an unusual poem by award-winning poet, Mona van Duyn, which illustrates some key aspects of resilience. Please read <a href="http://www.poets.org/viewmedia.php/prmMID/15674">the poem</a>. I know that many people do not like poetry, and see the core of it as rhyming.</p>
<p>This poem could be called a “prose poem”, and it is quite readable and lacks rhyme. And it’s over the top gloominess is even funny in spots.</p>
<p>The poem is called “Letters from a Father”. The letters come from an elderly father and are written to his daughter.</p>
<p>So please give it a chance so you can make sense of our comments on it.</p>
<p>Here is a synopsis that will allow you to understand how our linking it to resilience makes sense.</p>
<p>An elderly father speaks for both himself and his elderly wife. They seem both to have given up on life, and see themselves as on the threshold of death.</p>
<p>The daughter has sent them a bird feeder and feed, and the letters focus on how she is wasting her money on parents who won’t live long enough to enjoy the results.</p>
<p>Slowly the letters begin to reflect the parent’s re-engagement with life, as seen by the father’s diminished focus on death and increasing enjoyment of the birds, as well as pride in how well they are doing in getting interesting birds to visit.</p>
<p>Basically, that’s it.</p>
<p>Here are our comments on how this poem relates to resilience, and, in particular, how simple, small changes can move us from negativity and despair to positivity. Such changes can help us to shift from a morbid view of life to engrossment in the beauty of even a simple part of our lives.</p>
<p><span id="more-1470"></span></p>
<p>Small changes can result in major shifts in how resilient we are and in how we appreciate and enjoy our lives. Here is a valuable quotation from a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Small-Change-Little-Things-Difference/dp/1585423599/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1377485594&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=Terkel+%22small+change%22">book by Susan and Larry Terkel entitled “Small Change”</a>.</p>
<p>“Small change adds up. This is worth repeating: small change adds up. Empty your small change in a jar every day, and watch the total add up over time. Make small changes in your daily habits – such as your meals or snacks, your relationships, your work, or your leisure- and watch those changes gradually accumulate into a much healthier, happier, and more satisfying life.”</p>
<p>“An angle of only one degree is difficult to draw on a piece of paper. It is too small. If a flight from New York to Los Angeles is off course by just one degree, the plane will arrive closer to Tijuana, Mexico, than Los Angeles.”</p>
<p>“Small changes can get us back on course as easily as the can lead us off course”</p>
<p>For more about “small change”, click <a href="/2011/01/20/small-changes-can-result-in-big-improvements-in-resilience/">here.</a></p>
<p>We know very well how easy it is to give up on learning how to live a fulsome life. Life can be so densely hard that we may come to believe that nothing short of a miracle could make things better.</p>
<p>The pain of life can make us oblivious to the value of gifts (maybe we should say “blessings”) that fall in our laps. And this devaluation of the good things that come our way can lead us to pass up the opportunities for happiness that are offered to us for free.</p>
<p>In this poem, two elderly people who are in despair are drawn back to the joy that remains for them. And, in this case, all it took was a bird feeder and some seeds.</p>
<p>The Poem illustrates not only the value of small changes, but also the importance of other people in our resilience. The daughter played an essential role.</p>
<p>Resilience is not just inside us. There is a great deal of research that shows that we live better and healthier lives if we get support from others.</p>
<p>So the pathway from vulnerability to resilience includes not only shifts within us, but also shifts in our selection of the people who provide our life’s context. Our family and friends are more than the people we care about; they are also important sources of the support we need to get successfully to a healthy, satisfying life.”</p>
<p>Take an appreciative look at those people, and maybe even let them know how important they are to you.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F08%2F27%2Fthe-magic-of-small-changes%2F&amp;linkname=The%20magic%20of%20small%20changes" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Does Secure Attachment to Others Lead to High Resilience?</title>
		<link>/2013/02/21/does-secure-attachment-to-others-lead-to-high-resilience/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2013 04:15:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[How Hard Is It To Change Resilience?]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1321</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[There is interesting research showing that how securely we attach to our caregivers as young children plays an important role in our resilience as adults. Children who develop a secure attachment to their mother (or other caregiver) tend, as adults, &#8230; <a href="/2013/02/21/does-secure-attachment-to-others-lead-to-high-resilience/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There is interesting research showing that how securely we attach to our caregivers as young children plays an important role in our resilience as adults. Children who develop a secure attachment to their mother (or other caregiver) tend, as adults, to be resilient in the face of challenges.</p>
<p>Does this mean that your level of resilience became a settled matter when you were little, and nothing can be done about it now? We don’t think so.</p>
<p><span id="more-1321"></span></p>
<p>Attachment style is developed in very early childhood, and has been extensively studied. Usually there are deemed to be three basic styles, Secure, Anxious-Ambivalent, and Avoidant. This attachment style developed in early childhood appears to stay with us throughout our lives.</p>
<p>Those who are “Secure”, apparently had a good fit between their inborn temperament and parental responses that enabled them to build inner resources. These inner resources enable them to connect well with others, and to feel confident in potentially scary, unfamiliar environments. Both the Anxious-Ambivalent and the Avoidant people are less effective in dealing with such environments.</p>
<p>Avoidant people appear to be comfortable without close relationships, and avoid dependency on others. This is viewed as a defense, and can, under enough distress, break down.</p>
<p>Avoidant people may seem to be secure unless the environment is too challenging, and under those circumstances, they can seem more like those who are Anxious-Ambivalent.</p>
<p>Anxious-Ambivalent people long for emotionally close relationships, but tend to feel uncomfortable with them. It is hard for them to trust or depend on others.</p>
<p>For our purposes here, we can look at those who are just “Secure” or “Non-Secure”.</p>
<p>Mario Mikulincer and Victor Florian have <a href="http://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=hWe5-aSgZmcC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA143&amp;dq=mikulincer+florian&amp;ots=zjtx_xOZK5&amp;sig=KVc2PtHo1ap0q86eXi5AyA9k3SU#v=onepage&amp;q=mikulincer%20florian&amp;f=false (">summarized the research on how Secures and Non-Secures react to a wide range of demanding circumstances</a>, and have consistently shown that Secures are more resilient than Non-Secures.</p>
<p>Their review includes studies of reactions to significant life challenges. Very consistently they indicate that Secures handle such challenges better than Non-Secures. Here are examples:</p>
<ul>
<li>In the military training, Anxious Ambivalents perceived more threat, felt a greater sense of personal inadequacy and helplessness in dealing with the training.</li>
<li>When facing the threat of death, Secures had less fear.</li>
<li>In time of war, when threatened with missile attacks, Secures sought more support from others and had fewer symptoms of post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD).</li>
<li>Prisoners of War who were Secures had fewer symptoms of PTSD than Non Secures.</li>
<li>Secures handled loss of significant others better than Non-Secures.</li>
<li>In experiments testing reactions to personal failure, Secures handled the failures better.</li>
<li>Women facing the challenges of new <strong>motherhood </strong>who were secure handled them better than non-secures.</li>
<li>Mothers with handicapped children dealt with the extra challenges better if they were Secures.</li>
<li>People coping with chronic pain who are secure react much more effectively than those who are insecure.</li>
</ul>
<p>So, here is more evidence that resilience helps us deal with life’s challenges. But, if attachment style is determined when we are no more than toddlers, doesn’t it seem we are either blessed or doomed by early experiences to be resilient or not?</p>
<p>One interesting fact in the work of Mikulincer and Florian provides considerable room for hope. In Israel, during the first Persian Gulf War, some people had to deal with Scuds missile attacks. They had to face the possibility of instant death, and had no personal control over the source of that threat.</p>
<p>Yet the less resilient people reacted the same way as those who were resilient. Why? Presumably because public service messages consistently told them to check on each other during and after the attacks. With these instructions, anxious ambivalent and avoidant people reacted by reaching out to others, just as secure people would likely have done without the instructions.</p>
<p>So mere instructions from the government were able to override the knee jerk reactions of insecures to either hem and haw (anxious-ambivalents) or deal with the threats solely on their own (avoidant).</p>
<p>We can reasonably expect that real resilience training can be even more effective than mere instructions.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F02%2F21%2Fdoes-secure-attachment-to-others-lead-to-high-resilience%2F&amp;linkname=Does%20Secure%20Attachment%20to%20Others%20Lead%20to%20High%20Resilience%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Self-Help Programs Must Acknowledge the Elephant in the Room.</title>
		<link>/2012/09/26/self-help-programs-must-acknowledge-the-elephant-in-the-room/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2012 17:03:33 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[How Hard Is It To Change Resilience?]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1157</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The often unmentioned elephant in the room for those of us who are promoting self-help is “How do we effectively help people to actually DO what we know will help them?” And to be frank, “How do we get ourselves &#8230; <a href="/2012/09/26/self-help-programs-must-acknowledge-the-elephant-in-the-room/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The often unmentioned elephant in the room for those of us who are promoting self-help is “How do we effectively help people to actually DO what we know will help them?” And to be frank, “How do we get <strong><em>ourselves</em></strong> to do what we know will lead to a better life?”</p>
<p>Harvard happiness guru, <a title="Shawn Achor" href="http://goodthinkinc.com/experts/shawn-achor/">Shawn Achor,</a> emphasizes that we need to make sure we have arranged to minimize the effort it takes to carry through on our decisions. We need to minimize the “activation energy’ required to get going.</p>
<p><span id="more-1157"></span></p>
<p>Achor uses his own failed effort to learn how to play the guitar to explain the use of activation energy. He kept his guitar in the closet, but never got around to taking it out to practice. He even timed how long it took to get the guitar out and sit down to practice. It was only 21 seconds!</p>
<p>So, he set things up so the guitar was no longer in the closet. He put it right where he couldn’t avoid contact with it. Result? He now plays the guitar.</p>
<p>Debbie and I have done a similar, though reversed, version of this. We usually eat a pretty low fat diet. With that kind of diet, it’s not unusual to get hungry before bedtime. We decided to include nuts in our diet. But once before we had tried an Atkins-like diet, and used peanuts as our snack. We decided to drop that diet, but kept on eating the peanuts. I, she, and our dog, Sam, all gained weight.</p>
<p>So now we put the nuts on a shelf in the basement. When we decide to eat them, we take a small container (designed to hold spices) downstairs and fill it. I think it probably takes less than a minute to get the nuts, but I don’t think we have ever gone back for a refill.</p>
<p>It strikes me as a quirk of the mind that manipulating such small expenditures of energy can have so much influence on what we do. One answer to the self-improvement’s elephant-in-the-room issue may lie in understanding these “quirks”. We will have more to say about this in our next post.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2012%2F09%2F26%2Fself-help-programs-must-acknowledge-the-elephant-in-the-room%2F&amp;linkname=Self-Help%20Programs%20Must%20Acknowledge%20the%20Elephant%20in%20the%20Room." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Does Our DNA Have Final Say Over Our Reactions to Stress?</title>
		<link>/2012/01/17/does-our-dna-have-final-say-over-our-reactions-to-stress/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2012 22:43:37 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[How Hard Is It To Change Resilience?]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=916</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[When people ask whether resilience is genetic, I tend to suspect they are asking whether they can reasonably hope to improve how they act to stress. I worry that they will give up without a fight because they believe they &#8230; <a href="/2012/01/17/does-our-dna-have-final-say-over-our-reactions-to-stress/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When people ask whether resilience is genetic, I tend to suspect they are asking whether they can reasonably hope to improve how they act to stress. I worry that they will give up without a fight because they believe they are forever closed in a prison of misery by the chemical code of their genes.</p>
<p>Is the way we react inborn? Is it unchangeable? <span id="more-916"></span></p>
<p>This video by <a href="http://blog.ted.com/2008/06/24/dean_ornish/">Dr. Dean Ornish</a> answers these questions well and concisely. His emphasis on factors that influence gene <strong><em>expression</em></strong> is right on target. Gene expression is strongly influenced by lifestyle and skills of managing stress. There is a whole field, called “<a href="http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1952313,00.html">epigenetics</a>” devoted to the ways in which DNA is “expressed” by various triggers, many of which are environmental.</p>
<p><object width="526" height="374"><param name="movie" value="http://video.ted.com/assets/player/swf/EmbedPlayer.swf"></param><param name="allowFullScreen" value="true" /><param name="allowScriptAccess" value="always"/><param name="wmode" value="transparent"></param><param name="bgColor" value="#ffffff"></param><param name="flashvars" value="vu=http://video.ted.com/talk/stream/2008/Blank/DeanOrnish_2008-320k.mp4&#038;su=http://images.ted.com/images/ted/tedindex/embed-posters/DeanOrnish-2008.embed_thumbnail.jpg&#038;vw=512&#038;vh=288&#038;ap=0&#038;ti=252&#038;lang=&#038;introDuration=15330&#038;adDuration=4000&#038;postAdDuration=830&#038;adKeys=talk=dean_ornish_says_your_genes_are_not_your_fate;year=2008;theme=might_you_live_a_great_deal_longer;theme=medicine_without_borders;event=TED2008;tag=Science;tag=aging;tag=genetics;tag=health;tag=health+care;tag=medicine;tag=short+talk;&#038;preAdTag=tconf.ted/embed;tile=1;sz=512x288;" /><embed src="http://video.ted.com/assets/player/swf/EmbedPlayer.swf" pluginspace="http://www.macromedia.com/go/getflashplayer" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" wmode="transparent" bgColor="#ffffff" width="526" height="374" allowFullScreen="true" allowScriptAccess="always" flashvars="vu=http://video.ted.com/talk/stream/2008/Blank/DeanOrnish_2008-320k.mp4&#038;su=http://images.ted.com/images/ted/tedindex/embed-posters/DeanOrnish-2008.embed_thumbnail.jpg&#038;vw=512&#038;vh=288&#038;ap=0&#038;ti=252&#038;lang=&#038;introDuration=15330&#038;adDuration=4000&#038;postAdDuration=830&#038;adKeys=talk=dean_ornish_says_your_genes_are_not_your_fate;year=2008;theme=might_you_live_a_great_deal_longer;theme=medicine_without_borders;event=TED2008;tag=Science;tag=aging;tag=genetics;tag=health;tag=health+care;tag=medicine;tag=short+talk;&#038;preAdTag=tconf.ted/embed;tile=1;sz=512x288;"></embed></object></p>
<p>Here is what I understand about genes and resilience from years, really decades, of studying both resilience and the biological bases of behavior.</p>
<p>It seems obvious to me that part of our reaction to stress is influenced by genetic factors. Decades ago I was asked to present my research at a conference organized by the U.S. Veterans Administration. I don’t really remember what I presented, but I clearly remember what a man from Arkansas, Oddist Murphree presented on the genetics of vulnerability.</p>
<p>Murphree had interbred tense and anxious dogs. Generations of these dog’s offspring were <strong><em>extremely</em></strong> tense and anxious. (He wasn’t just a mad scientist. He wanted to find ways to help people who suffer from anxiety and tension by using nervous dogs as research models for nervous humans.)</p>
<p>I recall his showing a slide of a dog so tense that, even when his usual caretaker pushed down on his nose, his hind legs went upward, as if he were made of wood.</p>
<p>Murphree’s research was enough to make me strongly inclined to believe that there is an important genetic component that determines how we react, or over-react to stress.</p>
<p>Most people think that, if something is genetic, it cannot be changed. Actually whether the gene gets turned on or not is influenced by many factors, as <a href="http://blog.ted.com/2008/06/24/dean_ornish/">Dr. Ornish</a> points out.</p>
<p>Being “hard-wired” does not mean that a trait cannot be modified. Commonly we are born with a general template of what we might be, but our environment and what we do with it has to fill in the details of that template.</p>
<p>Bird song provides a good example of a modifiable genetic template. A given species of bird has a commonly shared set of songs that they sing. But the young ones sing the equivalent of human “baby talk”. The rest is fleshed out by the songs they hear in their environment. So birds of the same species from different parts of the world may have different “accents”.</p>
<p>Thus our genetic code can provide us a beginning template that provides a platform for developing a final pattern that is well adapted to the specifics or our environment.</p>
<p>Furthermore, it is well known that our brains tend to follow a pattern of “use it or lose it”. If we do not use brain circuits, they tend to deteriorate and stop functioning. Neuroscientists have shown, for example that, at birth, kittens have cells in their visual cortex that react to useful aspects of their visual environment. If the kittens are kept from seeing that environment, those cells quit functioning. Neuroscientists now place emphasis on “neuroplasticity”, the ability of our brains to change in response to environments or other factors.</p>
<p>We can play the DNA hand we have been dealt poorly or <a href="../../../../../2011/07/05/resilience-is-more-than-bouncing-back-from-stress/">play it well</a>. We can thrive and succeed in spite of what our DNA stipulates. Doing the best with the DNA we inherit is a central point of resilience training. Even when DNA and environment conspire to make things difficult, many people find ways to do well.</p>
<p>So I give genes their due, but, I also know that we can learn to respond effectively and do well despite our vulnerability. Not to be super-human, but to respond effectively and do well. That’s what resilience training is all about.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2012%2F01%2F17%2Fdoes-our-dna-have-final-say-over-our-reactions-to-stress%2F&amp;linkname=Does%20Our%20DNA%20Have%20Final%20Say%20Over%20Our%20Reactions%20to%20Stress%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Small Changes Can Result in Big Improvements in Resilience</title>
		<link>/2011/01/20/small-changes-can-result-in-big-improvements-in-resilience/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2011 04:03:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[How Hard Is It To Change Resilience?]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=549</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[It’s not uncommon for colleagues to express doubt that we can actually influence people to do the work involved in improving their resilience. They opine that people will not be willing to work that hard. In an earlier post we &#8230; <a href="/2011/01/20/small-changes-can-result-in-big-improvements-in-resilience/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It’s not uncommon for colleagues to express doubt that we can actually influence people to do the work involved in improving their resilience. They opine that people will not be willing to work that hard.</p>
<p>In an earlier post we pointed out that internalizing a resilient approach to life, which does take serious effort, is not essential to increasing resilience. In that post we explained how “props” can augment your functioning, enabling you to respond in a more resilient way than you could on your own. Props can be as simple as listening to a relaxation audio when you feel the need.</p>
<p>Also, in another earlier post, we listed many easy, pleasant ways you can sooth yourself and get relief from distress using ways that are already familiar to you, for example, cuddling with a pet or lover, listening to music, or getting a massage. Not exactly hard work.</p>
<p>In this post we will cover another factor that makes building resilience easier- the importance of small changes. No one has done a better job of explaining that importance than Larry and Susan Terkel, in their book, “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Small-Change-Little-Things-Difference/dp/1585423599">Small Change* It’s the Little Things in Life That Make a <strong>BIG</strong> Difference</a>!” Here are some important quotes from that book:</p>
<ul>
<li>“Small change adds up.      This is worth repeating: small change adds up. Empty your small change in      a jar every day, and watch the total add up over time. Make small changes      in your daily habits &#8211; such as your meals or snacks, your relationships,      your work, or your leisure- and watch those changes gradually accumulate      into a much healthier, happier, and more satisfying life.”</li>
<li>“An angle of only one      degree is difficult to draw on a piece of paper. It is too small. If a      flight from New York to Los Angeles is off course by just one degree, the      plane will arrive closer to Tijuana, Mexico, than Los Angeles.”</li>
<li>“Small changes can get us      back on course as easily as the can lead us off course.”</li>
</ul>
<p>Additionally, at the very beginning of working toward improvement, small changes in effort produce disproportionately large results.  For example, if you have long been sedentary and you begin a modest program of walking several times a week, your fitness will improve much more dramatically than it would if you were starting from a high level of fitness. A Silver Medal winning athlete who is determined to go for the gold will have to expend huge effort to make the needed changes.</p>
<p>This pattern of big, easy change in the beginning and smaller, effortful change at the end is so common that is has been applied in many different scientific fields and is known as The Growth Curve.</p>
<p>In helping people to improve their resilience, we always suggest that they try from one to, at most, three changes at any one time. It’s just fine if the changes you choose to try are small ones.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2011%2F01%2F20%2Fsmall-changes-can-result-in-big-improvements-in-resilience%2F&amp;linkname=Small%20Changes%20Can%20Result%20in%20Big%20Improvements%20in%20Resilience" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Building Personal Resilience: How Hard Is It?</title>
		<link>/2010/12/08/building-personal-resilience-how-hard-is-it/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2010 15:08:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[How Hard Is It To Change Resilience?]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=467</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Highlights: When the exercise came to an end, I realized that it had produced far more than merely “taking the edge off the anxiety”. I was downright serene. Somehow, my entire perspective had shifted. ********************************************************** We strongly advocate devoting a &#8230; <a href="/2010/12/08/building-personal-resilience-how-hard-is-it/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2><em>Highlights:</em></h2>
<p><em>When the exercise came to an end, I realized that it had produced far more than merely “taking the edge off the anxiety”. I was downright serene. Somehow, my entire perspective had shifted.</em></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">**********************************************************</p>
<p>We strongly advocate devoting a good deal of time and energy to building your resilience, so you may be surprised to learn that we also believe that:</p>
<ul>
<li>You can <em>improve</em> it with very little effort. You can make significant improvements in your resilience by practicing a few minutes per day.</li>
<li>You can even use resilience-enhancing “prosthetic procedures” or “props” that require little or no practice, though their usefulness gets greater with use.</li>
</ul>
<p>Props function in a way that is similar to the way eyeglasses or canes do. Virtually anyone can use them, and they help you function better even without changing any limitations you may have.</p>
<p>The recording we linked to the previous post is a good example of a resilience prop. It can be helpful whether you are highly resilient at your core or not.</p>
<p>An experience Jerry had illustrates the power of these recordings:</p>
<p>&#8220;I was a full time professor for several decades. Contrary to a prevalent illusion, the days when academe provided a nice, relaxing job are long gone. I loved many aspects of my work, but in too many ways it was a “rat race”. I had started grammar school a year early, finished undergraduate school in less than four years, working nights the whole time, finished my doctoral program very quickly and then, after I became a professor, almost always had an extra job. My nickname in my Department was &#8216;The Busy Professor&#8217;.</p>
<p>I always had a dream of getting out of the rat race early just as I had started early. Our university began giving early retirement incentives, but I was not old enough to be eligible. Luckily another incentive was provided just as I reached an age that allowed me to grab it. I actually succeeded in getting out early!</p>
<p>Then, a month or two after my retirement, my bowels started producing copious amounts of blood.</p>
<p>I catastrophized. Just when I thought I was home safe, it appeared it all might well be taken away from me. I became intensely anxious and, even though I had worked in the areas of stress and resilience for many years, I was taken over by this anxiety.</p>
<p><span id="more-467"></span></p>
<p>Usually when something hits me hard like this, it takes a few days for me to remember that I know a lot about how to get a grip on it. Then I develop a resilience plan and start implementing it.</p>
<p>The plan I came up with included something to pull me out of the acute anxiety pretty quickly. I knew that a deep relaxation recording was very likely to at least take the edge off the anxiety.</p>
<p>I stretched out in a reasonably quiet comfortable spot, closed my eyes, and just passively listened. Soon I was unaware of the outside world.</p>
<p>When the exercise came to an end, it had produced far more than merely taking the edge off the anxiety. I was downright serene. Somehow, my entire perspective had shifted.</p>
<p>Later, the anxiety came back in a milder form, but I kept returning to the recording as I went through the days waiting for my colonoscopy.</p>
<p>The GI doctor found a suspicious polyp, so I had to wait another week or so for the results. I continued using the tape and was able to exert considerable control over the anxiety. Finally I learned that the polyp was not malignant. I have not had another one since.</p>
<p>Given how effective mere listening to a tape proved to be, why do we still think you should invest more effort to improve your inner, core resilience? For one thing, the extra effort can make you <em>basically</em> more resilient. As a result, you will tend to be consistently calmer, less reactive, happier, healthier and more effective. And there is more, which you will see in subsequent posts.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2010%2F12%2F08%2Fbuilding-personal-resilience-how-hard-is-it%2F&amp;linkname=Building%20Personal%20Resilience%3A%20How%20Hard%20Is%20It%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
