<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Self-Understanding &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/self-understanding/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Clearing the Mind through Meditation</title>
		<link>/2015/04/14/clearing-the-mind-through-meditation/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 Apr 2015 16:22:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Understanding]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1874</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In this post we want to discuss mental changes that occur while and after meditation. The type of meditation you do is a factor in determining what happens, but there are many commonalities shared by various types of meditation. Relaxation &#8230; <a href="/2015/04/14/clearing-the-mind-through-meditation/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this post we want to discuss mental changes that occur while and after meditation.</p>
<p>The type of meditation you do is a factor in determining what happens, but there are many commonalities shared by various types of meditation. Relaxation of mind and body are very basic ones. We discussed this relaxation of mind and body in our previous post, and we followed Herbert Benson’s lead in dubbing it “the relaxation response”.</p>
<p>Since Benson is a cardiologist, it should not be a surprise that he focused on physiological reactions relevant to how the heart and blood vessels react. Obviously these changes are important for all of us. But there are also important changes in the way our <strong><em>minds</em></strong> function when we meditate. And these changes impact how we view the world and how we feel and behave.</p>
<p>A very valuable change has to do with getting control of the constant chattering that goes on in our minds.</p>
<p>Limiting the chatter/background noise is essential to developing a mind clear enough to be able to make our perception of reality clear. In Yoga it is seen as a form of enlightenment and in the more scientific framework of Information Theory it is a matter of reducing our mental “noise” level enough to tell whether an input contains something meaningful, a “signal”, or is merely noise.</p>
<p>We see the ancient views from Yoga and the modern views from information theory as expressing basically the same concepts, though within different frameworks.</p>
<p>One of the classic accounts of meditation and its consequences is in the Yoga Sutras of Patanjali. The first line of the Yoga Sutras says that “Even-mindedness is Yoga”.  In this view, the mind can be likened to a pond that responds with waves when something is dropped into it. If the pond is calm, without waves, even dropping a small pebble into it will result in easily noted waves.</p>
<p>In the middle of a storm, the impact of that same pebble may be impossible to detect.</p>
<p>With meditation, our minds have increased clarity and a wider awareness than they had prior to meditating. This clarity and extensiveness of awareness goes beyond mere facts. After meditation, things you have passed by many times with little reaction may suddenly reveal their beauty and trigger a sense of awe in you.  So meditation also clarifies a more emotional aspect of what we experience.</p>
<p>Until the 1960s, Western science paid little attention to claims that healthy changes could result from meditation. Such claims were generally ignored or seen as hokum. In the early 1960s this easy dismissal was called into question, and research began to be published that confirmed some of the claims.</p>
<p>Interesting early work by a psychiatrist, <a href="http://www.cuke.com/Cucumber%20Project/interviews/deikman.html">Arthur Deikman</a>, made a start in recognizing that our perceptions of many aspects of reality and our reactions to that reality are intensified and improved by meditation. He did a small study in which he got various colleagues to meditate on an ordinary blue vase. He simply asked the colleagues to sit in a room and keep their attention on the vase, putting aside distractions that came to mind.</p>
<p>Participants reported a wide range of reactions. Here is an illustration from an <a href="http://www.deikman.com/experimental.html">article written by Deikman</a> describing a shift in perception of the vase that occurred quite generally:</p>
<p><em>   Sooner or later they experienced a shift to a deeper and more intense blue. &#8220;More vivid&#8221;   was a phrase they used frequently. Ss experienced the vase as becoming brighter while everything in their visual field became quite dark and indistinct. The adjective &#8220;luminous&#8221; was often applied to the vase, as if it were a source of light. For example, subject B, Session #6, &#8220;The vase was a hell of a lot bluer this time than it has been before . . . it was darker and more luminous at the same time.&#8221;</em></p>
<p>(When Deikman wrote this article, the term “Subject” or “S” was in general use when referring to volunteer participants in psychological experiments.)</p>
<p>If you do a search in Google Scholar for research on meditation today, you will find many confirmations of beneficial effects of meditation.</p>
<p>We will continue discussing changes due to meditation in our next post.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2015%2F04%2F14%2Fclearing-the-mind-through-meditation%2F&amp;linkname=Clearing%20the%20Mind%20through%20Meditation" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Resilience Factor Three: Understanding and Expressing Yourself.</title>
		<link>/2013/07/22/resilience-factor-three-understanding-and-expressing-yourself/</link>
		<comments>/2013/07/22/resilience-factor-three-understanding-and-expressing-yourself/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2013 00:26:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effective Communication]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Expressing Feelings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Focusing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Understanding]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1423</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[For people who are new to this blog, we have been reviewing the three core factors that underlie resilience. Probably some of the original readers have forgotten those factors, so this review may be useful to them too. In the &#8230; <a href="/2013/07/22/resilience-factor-three-understanding-and-expressing-yourself/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For people who are new to this blog, we have been reviewing the three core factors that underlie resilience. Probably some of the original readers have forgotten those factors, so this review may be useful to them too.</p>
<p>In the previous two posts we described the first two factors. Here we deal with the third and final factor. This factor has to do with expressing or articulating your inner reactions to distressing situations.</p>
<p>James Pennebaker and his colleagues did a series of studies that linked expressiveness to improved physical and mental health. This work was summarized in Pennebaker’s book “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Opening-Up-Healing-Expressing-Emotions/dp/1572302380/ref=sr_1_2?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1374426455&amp;sr=1-2&amp;keywords=james+pennebaker">Opening Up: The Healing Power of Confiding in Others</a>”. Basically, they showed that clarifying and speaking of your feelings about things that distress you led to improved mental and even physical health.</p>
<p>It is easy to confuse the self-expression Pennebaker and his colleagues advocate with other actions that can even be damaging, so we will clarify the details of how to be expressive.</p>
<h4><strong>What You Need to Do to Improve Your Self-Understanding and To Express It.</strong></h4>
<p><span id="more-1423"></span></p>
<p>To articulate your reactions, the first step is to understand them. You can, most likely, improve your understanding of your own reactions by way of inner dialogue. But there are advantages to having someone else also understand you.</p>
<p>Effective communication often happens in psychotherapy, but it also can take place in serious conversations with caring friends and other people who are good listeners, patient, and willing to let you know when they don’t understand.</p>
<p>If you have the right kind of listener, you might also have a dialogue that improves both their and your understanding of how you feel and why you feel as you do. It requires you to be very clear about your feelings because it is very hard to explain them in a way that effectively communicates them to others.</p>
<p>Both self-understanding and self-expression are of remarkable value in helping you keep in check what might otherwise be a damaging stress reaction.</p>
<h4><strong>Journaling</strong></h4>
<p>Though there is a clear advantage to effectively sharing your deep feelings with supportive friends, such sharing is not always easy or even possible.</p>
<p>In such cases, <a href="http://homepage.psy.utexas.edu/homepage/faculty/pennebaker/home2000/WritingandHealth.html">writing down how you have reacted to a troubling situation</a>, even without an outside listener, can be helpful. Studies have shown that writing a journal that focuses on expressing how you feel about hurtful experiences diminishes their negative consequences.</p>
<p>The following video has the founder of this journaling method showing how it is done:<br />
<iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/XsHIV9PxAV4?rel=0" frameborder="0" width="640" height="360"></iframe></p>
<h4><strong>A Special Kind of Focusing</strong></h4>
<p>Another method of clarifying feelings is through a process called Focusing. Privately talking to yourself about how you feel can be worth a lot. However, you have to focus in a specific way, emphasizing how you feel, and paying attention to your body’s reactions as you go through this inner dialogue.</p>
<p>The special kind of <a href="/2011/05/13/relieve-distress-with-extra-ordinary-focusing/">focusing</a> developed by Eugene Gendlin is an outstanding way to learn from those bodily reactions. This special kind of focusing is not easy to explain, and we think that <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Power-Focusing-Practical-Emotional-Self-Healing/dp/157224044X/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1374042330&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=ann+cornell+weiser">Ann Cornell Weiser</a> has done the best job we have seen in explaining how to focus.</p>
<p>We often think that just keeping quiet about our feelings and ignoring them can make them irrelevant to our mental and physiological functions. James Lynch has shown clearly that emotions that cannot be formulated in our mind enough to be spoken or written tend to be expressed in harmful physiological reactions, for example, in elevated blood pressure.</p>
<p>Lynch’s work is not as well known as it should be. If his books are not available in your library, you could get them on <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Language-Heart-Bodys-Response-Dialogue/dp/046503795X/ref=sr_1_5?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1374042815&amp;sr=1-5&amp;keywords=James+Lynch">Amazon</a>, but as of this writing they are available on <a href="http://www.abebooks.com/servlet/SearchResults?an=James+Lynch&amp;sts=t&amp;tn=The+language+of+the+heart">Abebooks</a> for as little as $1.00 plus a few dollars in shipping fees.</p>
<p>He did extensive research on people who did not respond well to medicines in reducing dangerously high blood pressure. He concluded that they were often expressing their emotions by way of these elevations of blood pressure.</p>
<p>Learning to understand our reactions and express them in words instead of bodily reactions helps us be more resilient. This is not the same as “<a href="/2011/04/18/articulation-of-feelings-is-not-the-same-as-venting/">getting our anger out</a>”.  That is more likely to be damaging than helpful.</p>
<p>Learning to understand what you really feel about what is going in your life is healthy but take care that you express those feeling in situations that do not unnecessarily trigger hostile reactions in others.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F07%2F21%2Fresilience-factor-three-understanding-and-expressing-yourself%2F&amp;linkname=Resilience%20Factor%20Three%3A%20Understanding%20and%20Expressing%20Yourself." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2013/07/22/resilience-factor-three-understanding-and-expressing-yourself/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Overthinking No More.</title>
		<link>/2013/05/13/overthinking-no-more/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2013 15:46:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Compassion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Understanding]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1370</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I don’t remember where I first ran into the concept of overthinking, but it appealed to me. Both Debbie and I understand the limitations of the parts of the brain that underlie thinking. We also are aware of the often &#8230; <a href="/2013/05/13/overthinking-no-more/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><!--[if gte mso 9]><xml>
<o:OfficeDocumentSettings>
<o:AllowPNG/>
</o:OfficeDocumentSettings>
</xml><![endif]--></p>
<p><!--[if gte mso 9]><xml>
<w:WordDocument>
<w:View>Normal</w:View>
<w:Zoom>0</w:Zoom>
<w:TrackMoves/>
<w:TrackFormatting/>
<w:PunctuationKerning/>
<w:ValidateAgainstSchemas/>
<w:SaveIfXMLInvalid>false</w:SaveIfXMLInvalid>
<w:IgnoreMixedContent>false</w:IgnoreMixedContent>
<w:AlwaysShowPlaceholderText>false</w:AlwaysShowPlaceholderText>
<w:DoNotPromoteQF/>
<w:LidThemeOther>EN-US</w:LidThemeOther>
<w:LidThemeAsian>X-NONE</w:LidThemeAsian>
<w:LidThemeComplexScript>X-NONE</w:LidThemeComplexScript>
<w:Compatibility>
<w:BreakWrappedTables/>
<w:SnapToGridInCell/>
<w:WrapTextWithPunct/>
<w:UseAsianBreakRules/>
<w:DontGrowAutofit/>
<w:SplitPgBreakAndParaMark/>
<w:EnableOpenTypeKerning/>
<w:DontFlipMirrorIndents/>
<w:OverrideTableStyleHps/>
</w:Compatibility>
<m:mathPr>
<m:mathFont m:val="Cambria Math"/>
<m:brkBin m:val="before"/>
<m:brkBinSub m:val="&#45;-"/>
<m:smallFrac m:val="off"/>
<m:dispDef/>
<m:lMargin m:val="0"/>
<m:rMargin m:val="0"/>
<m:defJc m:val="centerGroup"/>
<m:wrapIndent m:val="1440"/>
<m:intLim m:val="subSup"/>
<m:naryLim m:val="undOvr"/>
</m:mathPr></w:WordDocument>
</xml><![endif]--><!--[if gte mso 9]><xml>
<w:LatentStyles DefLockedState="false" DefUnhideWhenUsed="true"
DefSemiHidden="true" DefQFormat="false" DefPriority="99"
LatentStyleCount="267">
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="0" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Normal"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="heading 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 7"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 8"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 9"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 7"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 8"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 9"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="35" QFormat="true" Name="caption"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="10" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Title"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="1" Name="Default Paragraph Font"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="11" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Subtitle"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="22" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Strong"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="20" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Emphasis"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="59" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Table Grid"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Placeholder Text"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="1" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="No Spacing"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Revision"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="34" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="List Paragraph"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="29" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Quote"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="30" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Intense Quote"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="19" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Subtle Emphasis"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="21" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Intense Emphasis"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="31" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Subtle Reference"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="32" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Intense Reference"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="33" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Book Title"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="37" Name="Bibliography"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" QFormat="true" Name="TOC Heading"/>
</w:LatentStyles>
</xml><![endif]--><!--[if gte mso 10]>


<style>
 /* Style Definitions */
 table.MsoNormalTable
	{mso-style-name:"Table Normal";
	mso-tstyle-rowband-size:0;
	mso-tstyle-colband-size:0;
	mso-style-noshow:yes;
	mso-style-priority:99;
	mso-style-parent:"";
	mso-padding-alt:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;
	mso-para-margin:0in;
	mso-para-margin-bottom:.0001pt;
	mso-pagination:widow-orphan;
	font-size:10.0pt;
	font-family:"Calibri","sans-serif";}
</style>

<![endif]--></p>
<p>I don’t remember where I first ran into the concept of overthinking, but it appealed to me. Both Debbie and I understand the limitations of the parts of the brain that underlie thinking. We also are aware of the often unrecognized strengths of the “emotional brain”, which is commonly regarded as a giving birth to mere “fluff”.</p>
<p>Emotion is certainly not “fluff”.<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Descartes-Error-Emotion-Reason-Human/dp/014303622X/ref=sr_1_3?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1368458741&amp;sr=1-3&amp;keywords=antonio+damasio"> Antonio and Hannah Da Massio</a> have shown that we need cooperation between the emotional brain and the thinking brain in order to deal with the real world. They showed that people with brain injuries that left both their thinking and their emotional brains intact, but blocked them from cooperating with each other resulted in smart people with extremely poor judgment.</p>
<p>These people could do very well on IQ tests, and even give intelligent answers to questions like “How many giraffes are there in the United States” that require creative and complicated thinking strategies.</p>
<p>So, when I ran into several articles about overthinking, I already knew that placing too much emphasis on thinking and too little on feeling and emotions would lead to poor outcomes. So the word “overthinking” grabbed my attention.</p>
<p>The go-to book on overthinking is one called “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Women-Who-Think-Too-Much/dp/0805075259/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1368459003&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=women+who+think+too+muchhttp://">Women Who Think Too Much</a>” by Prof. Susan Noel-Hoeksema. (Why just women? She pointed out that women are more likely than men to overthink. That is true, but actually, the few available research <a href="http://www.refocuser.com/2009/08/9-ways-to-stop-overthinking-everything/">sources</a> indicate a small, though statistically significant difference. So the book is also useful for guys).</p>
<p>As I began working my way through the book, I was impressed, and I recommended it to Debbie.</p>
<p>But, eventually I saw that reading the book is like taking a ride on a roller coaster, with the excitement and fun of learning alternating with pages of tedium. (This was my experience, not necessarily the objective truth.)</p>
<p>The best thing about the book is that it is full of methods for reducing overthinking.</p>
<p>So, here is my take:</p>
<p><span id="more-1370"></span></p>
<p>What is overthinking? Professor Noel-Hoeksema describes it as “going over and over your negative thoughts and feelings, kneading them like dough. She applies the term the “yeast effect”.  “Just as yeasty bread dough will double in size after it’s been kneaded, our negative thoughts expand, grow, and begin to take up all the space around them in our minds.”</p>
<p>We have always emphasized the damaging effects of stress amplification in limiting resilience. That last thing you should do when times are harsh is to alienate your supporters, tear yourself down, exaggerate your hopelessness… You get the idea- when you are in a distressing situation, you need someone who is on your side, but also smart about what helps and what hurts.</p>
<p>Clearly it doesn’t sound like a good thing to overthink. Research has linked it to depression. “When sadness is amplified instead of managed, it can take you down paths to hopelessness, self-hate, and immobility.”</p>
<p>It also increases anxiety, which can lead to a nasty physiological and psychological avalanche, ending in chronic arousal that “wears down the body” and eventually makes it hard for you to deal with even mildly challenging situations. All we can say is “Amen”.</p>
<p>So what can you do about overthinking? Here is a mix of examples from her book and some others that we think are also useful:</p>
<ul>
<li>Look for interpretations of distressing events that are not as damning as the ones that first come to mind.  Could nasty, critical comments about you be wrong, even silly and more about the critic than about you?</li>
<li>You should accept and attend to your negative feelings. But don’t be ruled by them. This is possibly the most important thing you can learn about scary feelings; you can have them and just keep going with what you judge to be in your best interest.</li>
<li>Don’t wait for someone else to rescue you; get going on ways to take care of yourself. Focus on what you can do for yourself, and if someone else helps, be thankful for their caring, but realize that it is the delicious frosting on the cake.</li>
<li>Brainstorm for possible ways to change your situation. The first few solutions you come up with are probably a tiny fraction of what you can discover if you unleash your creativity.</li>
<li>Start with something small. Small change adds up.</li>
<li>Don’t let uncertainly stop you from acting. Move forward even though you are uncertain about whether your solution will work. Doing <strong><em>something</em></strong> at the very least gives you dignity.</li>
<li>When you are having catastrophic thoughts about yourself, ask if these thoughts are merely echoing the unsupportive words of others who spoke without looking out for your interests.</li>
<li>Focus on your <strong><em>feelings</em></strong>, attend to what you are feeling in your body. This is usually the best source of what you really need to know in order to find an answer that can help you.</li>
<li>Don’t forget to exercise, even if it is for only a few minutes per day. Exercise improves
<ul>
<li>Stress-related aspects of your physiology.</li>
<li>The positivity and clarity of your thoughts.</li>
<li>Your level of calmness.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F05%2F13%2Foverthinking-no-more%2F&amp;linkname=Overthinking%20No%20More." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sleeplessness: Should You Medicate of Meditate?</title>
		<link>/2011/11/15/sleeplessness-should-you-medicate-of-meditate/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2011 16:28:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Perfectionism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Self-Criticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mindfulness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Understanding]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Women's Resilience]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=858</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I think it is safe to say that a large majority of us gravely underestimate the powers of our minds and overestimate the powers of medicine. Whether your problem is sleeplessness, pain or some other potentially overwhelming challenge, your mind, &#8230; <a href="/2011/11/15/sleeplessness-should-you-medicate-of-meditate/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think it is safe to say that a large majority of us gravely underestimate the powers of our minds and overestimate the powers of medicine. Whether your problem is sleeplessness, pain or some other potentially overwhelming challenge, your mind, especially if you train and develop its powers, can work wonders in corralling and controlling your problem.</p>
<p>Fortunately the title of this post implies a false dichotomy. Why not meditate AND medicate? Why not do what you can to control your problem by training your mind and then minimize the use of medical interventions.</p>
<p>Why should you take the trouble to train your mind? Well, the human body is a complex ecosystem. Every attempt to control such a system by tampering with its inner workings triggers an avalanche of unpredictable results. Our body’s complexity makes it subject to what has been called “<a href="http://www.imho.com/grae/chaos/chaos.html">the butterfly effect</a>”.  The butterfly effect refers to the fact that the tiny effect of a butterfly flapping its wings in China may change the weather in, say, Los Angeles. (Click the link above for a more detailed explanation.)</p>
<p>This effect implies that complex systems can be heavily influenced by tiny variations in factors that scientists would usually see as negligible. The butterfly effect clarifies why all medicines have “side effects”, and also why It is wise to minimize the risks of putting alien substances into our bodies.</p>
<p>In light of this, I had a strong reaction to a recent article in the New York Times <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/06/fashion/mothers-and-sleep-medication.html?_r=2&amp;src=rechp">referring to sleep medications as “mother’s little helper”.</a></p>
<p>There are useful non-medical ways to deal with sleeplessness and they can powerfully improve the effects of medical treatment while minimizing the risks entailed in taking medication. For example most of the sleepless mothers described in the New York Times article could not sleep because they were obsessively ruminating over tasks that needed to be done.</p>
<p>Meditation can help reduce such rumination. While meditating you deal with mental distractions by gently and compassionately returning your mind to the object on which you are meditating.</p>
<p>Think of it in terms of deeply ingrained stimulus-response bonds; the thought is the stimulus and it demands that you respond. One illustrative example from the Times article is a mother who said “There’s always the worry another e-mail has come in” (stimulus). &#8220;It’s hard to resist getting up and checking your emai&#8221;l (response).</p>
<p>But when you meditate, you learn over and over not to do things like taking that last peek; instead you train your mind to go back to your chosen object of meditation. This breaks the stimulus-response bond. Think of it, there are probably thousands of thoughts that create in you an urge to take action, but your meditation breaks the bond between thought and action.  It reduces the linkage to the point where the response becomes optional instead of compulsive. That will make you calmer.</p>
<p>Earlier we posted <a href="../../../../../2011/03/02/basic-mindfulness-technique/">a traditional way of doing mindfulness meditation</a>, and also an <a href="../../../../../2010/12/06/a-key-step-in-resilience-training-is-learning-deep-relaxation/">audio</a> that can have a similar effect. Nether of these aids take up much of your time. You should consider trying one or both of them.</p>
<p>This is only one small way of changing how your mind works. We will be discussing many more in later posts.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2011%2F11%2F15%2Fsleeplessness-should-you-medicate-of-meditate%2F&amp;linkname=Sleeplessness%3A%20Should%20You%20Medicate%20of%20Meditate%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Articulation of Feelings Is Not the Same as Venting</title>
		<link>/2011/04/18/articulation-of-feelings-is-not-the-same-as-venting/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2011 03:40:33 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effective Communication]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Expressing Feelings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Understanding]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=709</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In the last post, I pointed out the importance of clarifying and expressing your feelings of distress. Understanding how you feel about a distressing situation and expressing it in a safe context can make you feel better and stay healthier.

For years many in the mental health field have encouraged people to blow off steam, let out their anger, and get things off their chest. It was a model that implied that, when we are upset, we are like a boiler that is overheated, and that will blow up if it does not release some of the pressure. But humans are much more complex than boilers. <a href="/2011/04/18/articulation-of-feelings-is-not-the-same-as-venting/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the last post, I pointed out the importance of clarifying and expressing your feelings of distress. Understanding how you feel about a distressing situation and expressing it in a safe context can make you feel better and stay healthier.</p>
<p>For years many in the mental health field have encouraged people to blow off steam, let out their anger, and get things off their chest. It was a model that implied that, when we are upset, we are like a boiler that is overheated, and that will blow up if it does not release some of the pressure. But humans are much more complex than boilers.</p>
<p>This way of handling distress, which is called “venting”, is <strong><em>not</em></strong> likely to make you feel better or become healthier.</p>
<p>Carol Tavris and Elliot Aronson gave a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Mistakes-Were-Made-But-Not/dp/0156033909/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;s=books&amp;qid=1303097019&amp;sr=1-1">nice, concise summary of the effects of venting:</a></p>
<p>“…when people vent they often feel worse, pump up their blood pressure, and make themselves even angrier. Venting is especially likely to backfire if a person commits an aggressive act against another person directly…”.</p>
<p>There are commonly social ramifications of venting. Venting or dumping strong negative feelings on other people is likely to lead to reactions on their part that will create more stress. People have a way of making a person who is venting and dumping on them pay a price for doing so. And so the original stress gets amplified instead of being brought under control.</p>
<p>More careful therapists were likely to have people “get their anger out” by having them do things like yelling and screaming at pillows or beating on them with bats wrapped in foam rubber. This avoids antagonizing others and thereby amplifying stress.</p>
<p>However, if you don’t have a deep inner connection to your words and actions, these methods are not likely to resolve the issues. This pounding and yelling is probably, at best, a way to get a bit of exercise.</p>
<p>Fully articulating feelings tends to produce healthy outcomes, e.g. <a href="../2011/04/13/control-distress-by-understanding-and-expressing-yourself/">fewer physical symptoms</a>, <a href="http://homepage.psy.utexas.edu/homepage/faculty/pennebaker/reprints/Kiecolt.pdf">fewer visits to health care facilities, and improved immunity</a>. This articulating, unlike venting, involves a serious look at what has you upset and how you feel about it. You should come away from the experience with a sense of greater self-understanding and of relief.</p>
<p>The following are some clues that you are engaging in unproductive venting:</p>
<ul>
<li>When you vent, you do not      feel a sense of progressing toward recovery; you can go over and over the      problem without moving forward at all.</li>
<li>Your inner tension is      likely to improve little if at all, and often will rise.</li>
<li>You don’t get a feeling of      deepening your understanding of yourself and why you are reacting as you      are.</li>
<li>You don’t get a glimmer of      how you might proceed to improve the situation or live well in spite of      it.</li>
<li>Commonly the focus is on      others, on how awful and wicked they are.</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2011%2F04%2F18%2Farticulation-of-feelings-is-not-the-same-as-venting%2F&amp;linkname=Articulation%20of%20Feelings%20Is%20Not%20the%20Same%20as%20Venting" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Control Distress By Understanding and Expressing Yourself</title>
		<link>/2011/04/13/control-distress-by-understanding-and-expressing-yourself/</link>
		<comments>/2011/04/13/control-distress-by-understanding-and-expressing-yourself/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2011 15:40:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effective Communication]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Expressing Feelings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Understanding]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=639</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In this post, I want to discuss the third factor we identified in our research on personal resilience. It involves two things: Attending to and clarifying your feelings about distressing experiences. Expressing those clarified feelings in a safe way that &#8230; <a href="/2011/04/13/control-distress-by-understanding-and-expressing-yourself/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this post, I want to discuss the third factor we <a href="../../../../../2011/01/11/the-three-core-factors-that-can-make-you-more-resilient/">identified in our research on personal resilience</a>. It involves two things:</p>
<ul>
<li>Attending to and clarifying      your feelings about distressing experiences.</li>
<li>Expressing those clarified      feelings in a safe way that enables you to feel clearer and better about      them.</li>
</ul>
<p>As with the other two factors, this one has been the object of much research. <a href="http://homepage.psy.utexas.edu/homepage/faculty/pennebaker/Reprints/index.htm">James Pennebaker</a> was the researcher who first identified it as important. He and his  co-workers found that women who reported having been sexually abused  also reported, later in life, a markedly elevated number of symptoms of  ill health. However, if they had opportunities to <strong><em>express</em></strong> their feelings about the experience, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Opening-Up-Healing-Expressing-Emotions/dp/1572302380/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1302704279&amp;sr=1-1">the symptoms were markedly diminished</a>.</p>
<p>There is good research that supports the idea that expressing feelings reduces bodily responses to stress. For example, <a href="http://ist-socrates.berkeley.edu/%7Eucbpl/docs/51-Hiding%20Feelings97.pdf">Robert Levenson</a> found that people who participated in an experiment in which they were  required to watch a gruesome video of the amputation of a human limb had  stronger physiological reactions to the experience if they were also  asked to <strong><em>hide</em></strong> those reactions. (The video was gruesome enough that even those told to conceal their reactions were not fully able to comply.)</p>
<p>This  and similar research indicates that it is a healthy thing to spend the  time and effort to understand your feelings and to find a way to  articulate them.</p>
<p>A very good method is to talk to a well-trusted  friend. Of course, that kind of friend is often not available. Be  careful about expressing your private reactions to people who are not  solidly on your side. Instead of helping, it can make things worse,  amplify stress, and turn a small problem into a big one.</p>
<p>Fortunately, research shows us that <strong><em><a href="http://homepage.psy.utexas.edu/HomePage/Faculty/Pennebaker/Reprints/P1997.pdf">journaling privately to articulate how you feel about bad experiences also works</a></em></strong>. If you are in doubt about the supportiveness of potential listeners, it might be wise to use journaling.</p>
<p>In either case, focus on how you <strong><em>feel</em></strong> about the distressing situation. Do not worry about your style,  grammar, etc. Clarifying what you feel is the crux of the matter.</p>
<p>Later we will have more to say about how to <strong><em>listen to yourself</em></strong> enough to clarify your feelings about bad situations.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2011%2F04%2F13%2Fcontrol-distress-by-understanding-and-expressing-yourself%2F&amp;linkname=Control%20Distress%20By%20Understanding%20and%20Expressing%20Yourself" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2011/04/13/control-distress-by-understanding-and-expressing-yourself/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
