<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Effective Resilience Training &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/effective-resilience-training/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Surgical Preparation: Specific Details.</title>
		<link>/2016/09/14/surgical-preparation-specific-details/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Benefits of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2131</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Recently we have been writing posts about preparing patients for surgery. Benefits can be mental, but our focus has been on learning mind-focused ways to improve patient&#8217;s physical reactions during and after surgery. We found that many published studies indicate &#8230; <a href="/2016/09/14/surgical-preparation-specific-details/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Recently we have been writing posts about preparing patients for surgery. Benefits can be mental, but our focus has been on learning mind-focused ways to improve patient&#8217;s physical reactions during and after surgery.</p>
<p>We found that many published studies indicate that outcomes are significantly improved in patients who were given presurgical training. For example, patients lose remarkably less blood if they are taught how to move the blood away from the spine during the surgery and then have it return to the spine to facilitate healing after surgery.</p>
<p>At this point, many readers may be thinking that there is no way for the mind to move blood around in the body. Patients who are being trained tend to feel that way too.</p>
<p>An important step is to explain how that can happen. Scientifically designed studies are normally kept very simple, but in clinical practice the methods may be more complex. A common method used in research is pointing out that our minds often trigger movement of blood. Remind the trainee that most people blush when they are embarrassed. We also move blood to our genitals by having erotic fantasies. You can direct your blood to your hands by relaxing, suggesting that your blood is flowing down your arm into your hands, and picturing the suggested flow. This is not at all remarkable, the &#8220;fight or flight&#8221; reaction includes moving blood away from the periphery of your body. Relaxation inhibits the &#8220;fight or flight&#8221; reaction, so it makes blood flow to the hands.</p>
<p>There is much more evidence that the mind can control supposedly &#8220;involuntary&#8221; bodily reactions, but for this post we want to describe Debbie&#8217;s experiences with preparing patients to deal with upcoming surgery. Like most clinicians, she uses methods that go far beyond the simple methods assessed in published studies.</p>
<p>In her words:</p>
<p>&#8220;As a therapist I had remarkable success in assisting some of my patients to prepare for surgery or other medical procedures.</p>
<p>In therapy sessions, I begin by having the patient talk about the surgery and what the aim or primary goal is particularly from their perspective. We explore any feelings or concerns that they have about the surgery. What is their relationship with the medical people including the surgeon? Have they had surgery in the past and how did it go? Were there any complications? Have there previously been any poor outcomes.</p>
<p>The potential benefits of preparing psychologically in advance of the surgery are explained. I cite examples from published literature and describe my own experiences with other patients to explain how beneficial preparation can be. If for example the patient does not trust the medical field or has had bad experiences, we work to come to some sort of peace with it, enough that this does not transfer to the present situation. If they have had bad outcomes from surgery we explore this together to see if there are differences in the present situation.</p>
<p>We talk about mentally shifting to a place where the patient can see the medical team as being there to help them achieve their objectives.</p>
<p>We discuss how getting to a place where they are trusting of the medical provider makes it possible for their body to cooperate with the surgeon and not fight against her/him. It is understandable that at some level the body will protest being cut into and it is best to get the surgeon and patient working together, helping the body to relax.</p>
<p>The patient  tries to find out as much as possible about the surgery and what the procedure consists of, including a description of the steps along the way.</p>
<p>The patient  learns some form of relaxation procedure and oftentimes  is provided an audio to practice at home. In the counseling sessions I use the same relaxation procedure and while the patient is relaxed begin to guide them in imagining the surgery and positive outcomes. I provide some of the &#8220;script&#8221; but also encourage them to offer input and improve it.</p>
<p>I re-emphasize that the surgeon is here to help the patient and cooperating with him/her is what is needed now. Usually they visualize the knife entering their body for a noble purpose and that the blood at the time moves away from the surgery site.</p>
<p>Surgical steps are reviewed and how particularly the patient, the surgeon and the patient&#8217;s body are cooperating. They visualize how the area of the body is being &#8220;corrected&#8221; and how wonderful it will be for the quality of their life and health afterwards.</p>
<p>They imagine the anesthesia wearing off in a pleasant manner. I suggest that, as the anesthesia wears off, they will soon want water and some food. We discuss their body eliminating in a normal way and the body vitals being such that they can soon go home.</p>
<p>Other images might include seeing loved ones arrive to take them home and how soon they see the anticipated surgical improvements. Any rehabilitation services can also be incorporated into the imagery exercise.</p>
<p>Typically, it is best  to have several weeks to prepare for the surgery but have seen benefit in just a few sessions.&#8221;</p>
<p>Notice that there are three main devices being used. They are relaxation, imagery and suggestion. This is a triad that can help get you through just about any difficult situation.</p>
<p>RELATED READINGS</p>
<p>For clinical techniques we recommend Stanley Fischer&#8217;s &#8220;Discovering the Power of Self Hypnosis : A New Approach for Enabling Change And Promoting Healing.&#8221; The book was published in 1991, so is likely to be out of print but you can probably get a good used one at Abebooks.com at a very low price.</p>
<p>For a very good review of research on the evidence that supports the efficacy of this kind of method for surgical preparation we recommend &#8220;Mind-Body Interventions for Surgery: Evidence and Exigency,&#8221;published in Advances in Mind-Body Medicine, volume 14, Number 3 in the Summer of 1998, Pages 165-234. You can probably get a copy at little or no cost from your library. Be sure to ask for an interlibrary loan. Reading the article will likely be a challenge unless you have background in scientific writing , including statistical methods.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to Develop Habits that Increase Resilience</title>
		<link>/2015/10/08/how-to-develop-habits-that-increase-resilience/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2015 16:34:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Habits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mental contrasting]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1989</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Ultimately, resilience training should result in new habits that make you more resistant to stress. We have pointed out a number of times that listening to a lecture or reading an article on coping with stress is not likely to &#8230; <a href="/2015/10/08/how-to-develop-habits-that-increase-resilience/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ultimately, resilience training should result in new habits that make you more resistant to stress.</p>
<p>We have pointed out a number of times that listening to a lecture or reading an article on coping with stress is not likely to be enough to result in more resilient habits. You may get useful information, maybe even inspiration, both of which can be valuable, but that is not enough to produce new habits.</p>
<p>Usually we recommend “practice, practice, practice”. We also described “<a href="/2014/12/07/mental-contrasting-an-important-technique-for-reaching-your-goals/">mental contrasting</a>”, a method that asks you to imagine yourself as you are now, and to alternate that with imagining yourself after you have developed a new resilience habit. This differs from a widely used method of simply imagining yourself as having achieved the desired goal. The latter method has proven to be ineffective.</p>
<p>Research shows that mental contrasting improves results. For example, see Amit Amin’s paper here. Details of how to practice mental contrasting were published in the Harvard Business Review<a href="https://hbr.org/2011/02/nine-things-successful-people"> here</a>.</p>
<p>We now have the concept of the habit loop, which can act as a guide on how to develop new habits. This model of habit change contrasts with a long familiar approach of just giving yourself rewards when you engage in the behavior you want to make habitual. Instead, it focuses heavily on turning attention to the cues or triggers that elicit the behavior.<span id="more-1989"></span> </p>
<p>The power of cues is striking. We had a friend (now deceased) who never smoked in front of his parents. For a long time, he could not quit smoking. But when he visited his parents, often for long periods, he told us that he never felt an urge to smoke. The cue or cues were missing, so the urge never appeared.</p>
<p>It is important to look for the cues that trigger your behaviors because, by manipulating the cues you can control habits.</p>
<p>It is also important to develop cues to trigger habits you are trying to develop. Shawn Achor provided a very good illustration of effectively developing <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Happiness-Advantage-Principles-Psychology-Performance/dp/0307591549/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1444256134&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=the+happiness+advantage">a cue to trigger practicing on his guitar.</a></p>
<p>Achor wanted to learn to play the guitar. At first he put the guitar in a closet. He could get it out in a matter of seconds. Yet, after some time he noted that he had not practiced guitar at all! So he took it out of the closet and placed it in the living room. Then, the guitar acted as a cue for him to practice, and soon he had developed a well-cued habit.</p>
<p>Several writers who wanted to develop a steady habit of exercising have put exercise clothing next to the bed. The clothing triggers a response of dressing for the workout and then doing it.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2015%2F10%2F07%2Fhow-to-develop-habits-that-increase-resilience%2F&amp;linkname=How%20to%20Develop%20Habits%20that%20Increase%20Resilience" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mental Contrasting: An Important Technique for Reaching Your Goals.</title>
		<link>/2014/12/07/mental-contrasting-an-important-technique-for-reaching-your-goals/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2014 22:02:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Habits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mental contrasting]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1785</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In this post we hope to show you the value of a technique called “mental contrasting”. We want to explain that concept, to cite evidence that mental contrasting really helps people change their habits to healthier and more productive ones, &#8230; <a href="/2014/12/07/mental-contrasting-an-important-technique-for-reaching-your-goals/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this post we hope to show you the value of a technique called “mental contrasting”. We want to explain that concept, to cite evidence that mental contrasting really helps people change their habits to healthier and more productive ones, and to tell you what you need to know in order to use it yourself.</p>
<p><span id="more-1785"></span></p>
<p>In an<a title="earlier post" href="/2010/12/06/getting-yourself-to-act-on-what-you-learn-about-building-resilience/"> earlier post </a>we discussed Gabrielle Oettingen’s method of “mental contrasting” as a way to keep yourself practicing resilience skills. If you want to build these skills and turn them into habits you have to practice. But it is hard to change habits, and we all have trouble getting ourselves to persist in habit-changing practices until we reach our goals.</p>
<p>Mental contrasting has a very credible basis to claim that it is an important technique to help us persist in needed practices.</p>
<p>An article written by Oettingen <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/10/26/opinion/sunday/the-problem-with-positive-thinking.html?_r=0">appeared in the October 24<sup>th</sup> New York Times</a>, and has been in our “to do” folder ever since. This week, we had a good opportunity to digest its content.</p>
<p>If you find a better summary of mental contrasting and its uses, please let us know. This one is excellent. It identifies research done on mental contrasting, showing that it helps “college students wanting a date, hip-replacement patients hoping to get back on their feet, graduate students looking for a job, (and) schoolchildren wishing to get good grades.” In addition, the study we cited earlier was on helping women lose weight. It helps.</p>
<p>So it’s clear that this is a technique that is both effective and widely applicable. It has helped people reach a variety of goals; in addition, the studies were done in both the United States and Germany. So the methods work in a variety of contexts.</p>
<p>The final test is: Do they work for you?</p>
<p>Would you like to try it for one of your goals? Here is Oettingen’s description of how to do that:</p>
<p>“…Think of a wish. For a few minutes, imagine the wish coming true, letting your mind wander and drift where it will. Then shift gears. Spend a few more minutes imagining the obstacles that stand in the way of realizing your wish.”</p>
<p>It’s as simple as that. If you try it, let us know how it works for you. We will share the results with a lot of other people.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F12%2F05%2Fmental-contrasting-an-important-technique-for-reaching-your-goals%2F&amp;linkname=Mental%20Contrasting%3A%20An%20Important%20Technique%20for%20Reaching%20Your%20Goals." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>More Resilience Training Can Produce Richer, More Powerful Results.</title>
		<link>/2014/08/04/many-resilience-techniques-can-be-brief-and-easy-but-more-training-can-produce-richer-more-powerful-results/</link>
		<comments>/2014/08/04/many-resilience-techniques-can-be-brief-and-easy-but-more-training-can-produce-richer-more-powerful-results/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2014 18:55:57 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[How Hard Is It To Change Resilience?]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1709</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[We have often pointed out, maybe even emphasized, how easy it is to learn techniques that are helpful in resisting and recovering from stress. The techniques are not only easy, but are typically pleasant and comforting. Most resilience training methods &#8230; <a href="/2014/08/04/many-resilience-techniques-can-be-brief-and-easy-but-more-training-can-produce-richer-more-powerful-results/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We have often pointed out, maybe even emphasized, how <em>easy</em> it is to learn techniques that are helpful in resisting and recovering from stress.</p>
<p>The techniques are not only easy, but are typically pleasant and comforting. Most resilience training methods make you feel somewhere in the range of good to very good.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, too many people practice for a while, but then get embedded in the demands of ordinary life and never get to see how rich the benefits might be if they continued over the long term.</p>
<p>Take <a href="/2010/12/06/a-key-step-in-resilience-training-is-learning-deep-relaxation/">deep relaxation</a> as an example. A large majority of people who try basic methods of deep relaxation find the states they induce both useful and pleasant.</p>
<p>They should consider persisting at least a little longer. For some methods of relaxation and calming, there is evidence that practice can continue to improve, even over many years.</p>
<p>A striking example is the work of a Japanese researcher, Tomio Hirai. He studied changes in brain waves that take place when people practice Zen Meditation. (It is called “Zazen” and is essentially identical to the currently popular “Mindfulness Meditation”).</p>
<p><span id="more-1709"></span></p>
<p>Zazen involves sitting in a stable posture and attending to your breathing. The goal is to do that and nothing else.</p>
<p>Beginners count their inhalations and exhalations from one to ten; then they go back to one and start over again. If you try this for a while you will find yourself counting numbers like “42”, indicating that your mind has wandered without your noticing it. When this happens you just calmly go back to one.</p>
<p>As time goes on, brain wave patterns shift from fast to slow (an indication of calm, deep relaxation, the antithesis of a stress response, a “relaxation response”).</p>
<p>Hirai found that even after decades of practice meditators <a href="http://is.muni.cz/www/178816/EEG_and_Zazen.pdf">are still improving</a>.</p>
<p>But their commitment to meditation is not just to deal with life’s frustrations. As part of a Buddhist tradition, it is done to achieve some form of “enlightenment”, a profound and highly beneficial readjustment of their perceptions of themselves and of the world.</p>
<p>Zen masters recognize and accept that many people who practice Zazen, do so in order to function better in their ordinary lives. The term “<a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=KczYq22WAeYC&amp;pg=PA49&amp;lpg=PA49&amp;dq=bompu+zen&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=igVZJ2sn_3&amp;sig=7PRrXKcW1ep0fUHZCShYKcRc_cc&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=3rfdU_POGKLT8AGjvoCgCg&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CFIQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=bompu%20zen&amp;f=false">Bompu Zen</a>” is used for this more basic approach.</p>
<p>What resilience training normally aims to achieve is at the level of Bompu Zen. This does not meant that it is <em>merely</em> bompu Zen. We, for example, include the most effective techniques from a wide variety of traditions and other sources, as long as their effectiveness is robust enough to be empirically confirmed.</p>
<p>It appears that “the sky is the limit” when it comes to how far you can go with your training. Whether you reach for the sky depends on your ultimate goals. It depends on whether you seek a radically new perspective on the world and your life or just want to deal more effectively with life’s familiar demands, which is, incidentally, the humble goal we have chosen for this blog.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F08%2F04%2Fmany-resilience-techniques-can-be-brief-and-easy-but-more-training-can-produce-richer-more-powerful-results%2F&amp;linkname=Many%20Resilience%20Techniques%20Can%20Be%20%20Brief%20and%20Easy%2C%20but%20More%20Training%20Can%20Produce%20Richer%2C%20More%20Powerful%20Results." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2014/08/04/many-resilience-techniques-can-be-brief-and-easy-but-more-training-can-produce-richer-more-powerful-results/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Stop Doing Things That Make You More Vulnerable and Less Resilient</title>
		<link>/2014/04/30/stop-doing-things-that-make-you-more-vulnerable-and-less-resilient/</link>
		<comments>/2014/04/30/stop-doing-things-that-make-you-more-vulnerable-and-less-resilient/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2014 16:58:24 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1641</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Are you doing things that impair your resilience? Here are some things that can reduce resilience. Don’t develop skills that enable you to sooth, calm, and comfort yourself. (Many, if not most, of our posts on this blog explain what &#8230; <a href="/2014/04/30/stop-doing-things-that-make-you-more-vulnerable-and-less-resilient/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Are you doing things that <strong><em>impair</em></strong> your resilience? Here are some things that can reduce resilience.</p>
<ol start="1">
<li>Don’t develop skills that enable you to sooth, calm, and comfort yourself. (Many, if not most, of <a href="/category/self-soothing/">our posts</a> on this blog explain what those skills are and how to develop them.) The basic ones are very easy to learn.</li>
<li>Don’t fail to apply your resilience skills when they are needed. (You know, “too busy”, “too tired”, “I’ll do this tomorrow”). Here are <a href="/2010/12/06/getting-yourself-to-act-on-what-you-learn-about-building-resilience/">some methods</a> that can help you to get past those excuses and really use the resilience skills that you have.</li>
<li>Don’t underestimate the importance of other people to increasing your resilience (not to mention your health and your success!). For example, be aware of what you may lose by directing your anger and frustration toward supporters. Dumping your distress on supportive others may tempt them to give up or even direct spite at you. For your own sake, you should guide and encourage them. Let them know how they can help, and even give them pep talks.</li>
<li>Don’t do things that increase your distress. For example, inwardly talking to yourself in ways that pump up your anger at people you see as having treated you unfairly. Or selling yourself on the idea that things that distress you make you a helpless victim, who lacks any control over her/his reactions.</li>
<li>Don’t numb your distressed feelings with alcohol or other drugs without even trying to find ways to control your own reactions with skills instead of chemicals.</li>
<li>Don’t allow your routine life to become chaotic without developing at least a few predictable routines. Simplifying your life makes it easier to cope with potentially distressing situations that inevitably come by.</li>
</ol>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>In Contrast, Here Is How Resilient People See It and Do It.</p>
<ul>
<li>I frequently take good care of, calm, and comfort myself.</li>
<li>My typical reaction to a bad situation is to think and do things that make me feel calmer and better.</li>
<li>I know some things I can do to make me feel better when I am upset, and I usually do those things when I am under stress.</li>
<li>I have many predictable routines in my life that give me comfort.</li>
<li>I know that people who try to help me through hard times need some encouragement, and I do my best to give it to them.</li>
<li>I often get to enjoy myself.</li>
<li>I have learned enough about self-calming and self-soothing to recover from challenges by the time I face the difficulties of the next day.</li>
</ul>
<p>To use an already overused saying “Rome wasn’t built in a day”. If things have gotten out of control for you, you will have to take toddler steps toward shifting to a more resilient way of living. Why not work toward developing skills and routines that help make your life less stressful and more successful?</p>
<p>And for heaven’s sake don’t lead with your chin and do things that turn up the intensity of your stress.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F04%2F30%2Fstop-doing-things-that-make-you-more-vulnerable-and-less-resilient%2F&amp;linkname=Stop%20Doing%20Things%20That%20Make%20You%20More%20Vulnerable%20and%20Less%20Resilient" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2014/04/30/stop-doing-things-that-make-you-more-vulnerable-and-less-resilient/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Sweet Talk versus Resilience Training.</title>
		<link>/2013/12/05/listening-to-sweet-talk-versus-resilience-training/</link>
		<comments>/2013/12/05/listening-to-sweet-talk-versus-resilience-training/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2013 04:06:54 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1551</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Debbie and I often discuss our concerns about the quality of research on resilience. But we are even more troubled by guidance from sources that make no distinction between advice based on well-established facts and advice that is based on &#8230; <a href="/2013/12/05/listening-to-sweet-talk-versus-resilience-training/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Debbie and I often discuss our concerns about the quality of research on resilience. But we are even more troubled by guidance from sources that make no distinction between advice based on well-established facts and advice that is based on mere opinion, advice that is merely “sweet talk”.</p>
<p>What is sweet talk? It’s hard to give it an air-tight definition, but you can recognize it if:</p>
<ul>
<li>It briefly makes you feel hopeful, but is soon forgotten.</li>
<li>It doesn’t give you a “recipe” for how you can implement its ideas or suggestions.</li>
<li>It is short on evidence that it will work. It may be empty claims, opinions (or even rehashes of other peoples’s opinions) that are only loosely based on evidence.</li>
<li>It doesn’t show you specific ways you can apply its suggestions to your own life.</li>
<li>It gives you little or no guidance about how to develop skills that make you more resilient.</li>
</ul>
<p><span id="more-1551"></span></p>
<p>Basically “sweet talk” creates the illusion that change is easy. It is almost entirely focused on gains while omitting a discussion of costs (that is, the planning and work you need to do to become more resilient).</p>
<p>Often, we find lists that tell you to do things like “be positive” or “be confident”.  The changes are desirable, but also can be hard to make. Often missing is an explanation of what you can do to make those changes.</p>
<p>Sweet talk feels good to hear, but may not be well-rooted in reality or have much effect on your resilience and your life.</p>
<p>The truth is that life is challenging. Life calls upon us to use and develop the gifts that we start with or that fall in our laps by luck. It also tempts us to avoid the effort needed to do what we must do to cultivate our full potential.</p>
<p>Admittedly, sweet talk sometimes helps. Sweet talk can be like the match that lights the fuse that sets off a powerful reaction. The energy and abilities are already there, but some sweet talk may help to activate them.</p>
<p>Sweet talk can give you the illusion that you have learned how to better your life without showing you how to do that.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F12%2F05%2Flistening-to-sweet-talk-versus-resilience-training%2F&amp;linkname=Listening%20to%20Sweet%20Talk%20versus%20Resilience%20Training." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2013/12/05/listening-to-sweet-talk-versus-resilience-training/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to Teach Your Worrier Brain to Function Like A Warrior Brain</title>
		<link>/2013/04/25/how-to-teach-your-worrier-brain-to-function-like-a-warrior-brain/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2013 19:17:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Genes and Resilience]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1359</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Our last two posts focused on research showing that there are two variants of a gene that result in your having either a “worrier brain” or a “warrior brain”. However, the research also shows that a “worrier” can function like &#8230; <a href="/2013/04/25/how-to-teach-your-worrier-brain-to-function-like-a-warrior-brain/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Our last two posts focused on research showing that there are two variants of a gene that result in your having either a “worrier brain” or a “warrior brain”. However, the research also shows that a “worrier” can function like a “warrior” with the right kind of training. Extensively exposing worriers to simulations of the stressors they need to face enabled many of them to deal with stress as effectively as warriors.</p>
<p>This “<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exposure_therapy">exposure training</a>” has been used widely by psychotherapists, and its efficacy is well established.</p>
<p>A second approach that improves performance under stress is “reappraisal”. An excellent example of reappraisal is teaching people about the helpful effects of our bodily stress responses. For example, blood glucose can be increased due to stress, and that can help when facing challenges like taking tests. Again, this is not new to psychotherapists; commonly they point out that what a person is experiencing as fear or anxiety can also be seen as “excitement”. This kind of shift in perspective has been shown to work.</p>
<p>In this post we want to point out some other things that both of us feel are particularly useful in dealing with stress.</p>
<p><span id="more-1359"></span></p>
<p>Debbie and I agreed to identify which methods we would add to the two described in the previous two posts. Debbie’s list was the best, so here is a summary of it.</p>
<ul>
<li>Exercise: Just about everyone these days knows about the body’s natural opiates that counter stress and even reduce pain. Exercise also produces <a href="/2012/05/09/physical-exercise-is-a-surefire-way-to-de-stress/">other, less well known, chemical changes</a> that are calming. Debbie also points out that exercise helps to shift our thoughts toward the positive.</li>
<li>Challenging negative thoughts, which commonly do you no good, and finding more useful, positive thoughts.</li>
<li>Practice being in the present moment rather than always anticipating and maybe even overthinking about possible bad things in the future.</li>
<li>Shift to a more positive frame by keeping a daily log of things that went well, and try to notice for a particular time period (e.g. a day), the things you like about other people.</li>
<li>One of the weaknesses of self-help is that most of us find it hard to do what we know is in our best interests. Debbie suggests “<a href="/2012/10/17/finding-a-path-to-a-more-resilient-life-the-devil-is-in-the-details/">Mental Contrasting</a>”, which has been shown to help people follow through on their good intentions. Mentally contrasting a future you want with present reality energizes us and encourages us to commit to the actions that will get us to our goal.</li>
</ul>
<p>The only thing I want to add to that list is controlled regulation of breathing. Details of how to do that are in <a href="/2011/12/14/dont-let-overwhelming-distress-take-you-down/">this post</a> and <a href="/2011/06/14/a-plain-vanilla-application-of-tactical-breathing-to-increase-resilience/">this one</a>.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F04%2F25%2Fhow-to-teach-your-worrier-brain-to-function-like-a-warrior-brain%2F&amp;linkname=How%20to%20Teach%20Your%20Worrier%20Brain%20to%20Function%20Like%20A%20Warrior%20Brain" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Genetic Variants That Can Determine Whether We Have a “Worrier Brain” or A “Warrior Brain” and What We Can Do About Them.</title>
		<link>/2013/03/19/genetic-variants-that-can-determine-whether-we-have-a-worrier-brain-or-a-warrior-brain-and-what-we-can-do-about-them/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2013 15:16:31 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Genes and Resilience]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1338</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This post is based on an article I recently found in the New York Times. It makes several important claims: There are two variants of a specific gene that influence how quickly we recover from stressful experiences. We get one &#8230; <a href="/2013/03/19/genetic-variants-that-can-determine-whether-we-have-a-worrier-brain-or-a-warrior-brain-and-what-we-can-do-about-them/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This post is based on an <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/10/magazine/why-can-some-kids-handle-pressure-while-others-fall-apart.html?pagewanted=all&amp;_r=0">article</a> I recently found in the New York Times. It makes several important claims:</p>
<ol start="1">
<li>There are two variants of a specific gene that influence how quickly we recover from stressful experiences.</li>
<li>We get one from our mother and the other from our father.</li>
<li>The pattern of these genes we inherit determines whether we will be “worriers” or “warriors”.</li>
<li>Worriers are people who have to struggle with stressful experiences and warriors are people for whom stress reactions quickly pass by.</li>
<li>Whether we have the genetic pattern that gives us a warrior brain or a worrier brain, there is at least one simple technique that can make us deal efficiently with stress.</li>
</ol>
<p><span id="more-1338"></span></p>
<p>First, I want to acknowledge that I am skeptical about much of the brain-mind research that has come to be widely accepted. I don’t want to get into that because it is way too technical. But I often ask, “What good does it do for people dealing with a stress problem to learn that they were genetically doomed to have trouble with stressors, e.g.to be a worrier?”</p>
<p>Today, Debbie had an opening in her usually busy schedule, and called to chat.  I was trying to write this post, and I posed this question to her. She paused briefly, and then said “It helps people to understand why they have to struggle with things that other people handle with apparent ease.” Good answer.</p>
<p>So here is my condensed description of the genetic issue. Dopamine is a brain chemical that is released in the lower part of the frontal lobes of our brain. The sooner it is cleared out, the sooner we recover from the stress. This is because that lower frontal part of the brain can control the parts of the brain that produce responses that are “raw emotions”.</p>
<p>We all have a gene that determines how fast we clear Dopamine out of that part of our brain, and, as we said above, one variant leads to quicker, actually something like 40 times quicker, cleanup of the dopamine “mess”.</p>
<p>For people whose brains cleanup that mess slowly, their brains and minds are likely to be overwhelmed by the surge.</p>
<p>The following is an important part of this study: the effects of the slow acting system have been demonstrated in a real-life stressful situation. Young people in Taiwan take a test that has a major influence on the trajectory of their lives. Those with the slow acting system score on average 8 percent lower than those with the fast-acting system.</p>
<p>However, people with the slow acting gene can handle extreme stress as long as they are well-trained. Even some Navy Seals have worrier genes.</p>
<p>This concept that training can trump genetic effects (or lifelong bad habits) is right at the core of our belief in the value of resilience training.</p>
<p>What kind of training do people with worrier brains need to function as well as those with warrior brains?</p>
<ul>
<li>Exposure to stress challenges. Worriers need to be taxed without being overwhelmed, and then have time for recovery. “Training, preparation, and repetition defuse the worrier’s curse”.</li>
<li>Labeling of stress can determine reactions to it. If worriers see their feelings of stress as something that can improve their performance, their performance improves. They learn to view the feelings we usually call “stress” as “excitement”.</li>
</ul>
<p>We plan to deal with the effects of such labeling or “reappraisal” in a future post.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=&amp;linkname=" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Some Ways to Manage Your Mind and Therefore to Manage Your Body</title>
		<link>/2012/11/14/some-ways-to-manage-your-mind-and-therefore-to-manage-your-body/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Nov 2012 17:59:31 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1278</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I want to discuss life changing lessons I have learned from people who taught me how to train the mind in a way that produces improvements I and others want and maybe even desperately need. The first of these people &#8230; <a href="/2012/11/14/some-ways-to-manage-your-mind-and-therefore-to-manage-your-body/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I want to discuss life changing lessons I have learned from people who taught me how to train the mind in a way that produces improvements I and others want and maybe even desperately need.</p>
<p>The first of these people is Theodore Xenophon Barber, known by people who were connected to him as “Ted”.</p>
<p>Ted was famous for publishing many papers, I think in the hundreds of them, which are widely viewed as somehow refuting hypnosis. His studies repeatedly showed that people who were asked to pretend that they were hypnotized could perform what were generally regarded as remarkable feats <strong><em>due to</em></strong> hypnosis, even though they were merely told to act <strong><em>as if</em></strong> they were hypnotized.</p>
<p>For example, a demonstration of the powers of hypnosis was (and probably still is) to show that a small woman could, under hypnosis, carry the weight of a heavy guy who sat on her stomach when her head was on one chair and her feet on another. This was a common feat of stage hypnosis.</p>
<p>Ted showed that small people who were only told to pretend they were hypnotized could also do this kind of feat.</p>
<p>This is a good lesson about how much we underestimate our capabilities. I think we could honestly say that there is an “epidemic of self-underestimation”.</p>
<p>If you attempt to do this at home, it might or might not work. We DO massively underestimate our abilities, but we also have to activate them in the right way. For example, the person bearing the weight has to have her (or his) upper body arranged so that the shoulders, not the head are on one of the chairs.</p>
<p>We do not want to give more details that might encourage people to try this on their own. That is not a good idea. We only want to illustrate that there is a bit of finesse required for it to work. The results are remarkable, even taking the “finesse” into account.  The need to finesse the details illustrates the important point that, to use your mind effectively, you need training in the details. In this case, without being adequately trained, you might end up with a neck injury.</p>
<p>I suppose you can see why Ted was seen as a person who had refuted hypnosis. He was saying that most of us ordinary people can do what are regarded as extraordinary feats due to hypnosis.</p>
<p><span id="more-1278"></span></p>
<p>When I first met Ted, I had already read a many of his books and papers; that is why I worked to arrange for him to give some lectures and training for the faculty and students at our Department of Psychology. Since I was the faculty member who had arranged for him to come, I was charged with picking him up at the airport.</p>
<p>On the way into town, he asked me what kind of work I do.</p>
<p>I said, “I am teaching people how to use mental imagery to help them maneuver through life”.  He responded, “Oh, you are also using hypnosis.”  I responded, “No, I just use things like guided imagery”.</p>
<p>We went through several rounds of this, and he finally said, “You will understand why I am calling what you do “hypnosis” after you attend my workshop.”</p>
<p>He was right. I now see that we are all hypnotized all of the time. All of us live in a “cultural trance” that is affirmed and strengthened by others in our culture.</p>
<p>His research had not refuted hypnosis; it had shown that what has been labeled “hypnosis” is an ordinary way that we all guide our minds, whether effectively or ineffectively. Many people guide their minds to make their lives miserable and ruin their health. That same mental power could as well make them happy and healthy.</p>
<p>In Ted’s training session he gave several demonstrations. For example, he asked us to rest an elbow on the desk in front of us (It was a college classroom), and then guided us into imagining that we had received an anesthetic injection. He asked to think and imagine with him as he suggested, step by step, what would happen if we had actually been anesthetized. The large majority of people in the audience experienced what he suggested.</p>
<p>We can call this “hypnosis”, but it is a natural ability we all have and use all the time. We can suggest to ourselves that “Life sucks”, that we are “useless”, or what have you. On the other hand we can think and imagine in ways that guide us to feeling that life is good and that we can make it better and better.</p>
<p>I think I first got a sense of what Ted’s research had taught him when I took him to lunch before we went to the University. At one point the waitress asked if we wanted anything else. He answered her with a look and tone that struck me as that of an enthusiastic child and said “Can I have some more milk?”</p>
<p>He had taught himself to get real joy out of simple things in life.</p>
<p>Later, in the training workshop, he talked about working with people who wanted to quit smoking. At first he did something that is common in our “cultural trance”, being negative and punitive.</p>
<p>He had his clients think and imagine the horrible consequences of smoking. He described taking a man step by step through imagining that he had a cough that didn’t go away, that he went to a doctor who, after some tests, told him he had lung cancer. He had him imagine the subsequent steps all the way to the client’s being in a coffin lowered into his grave as his young daughter sobbed and  said, “Daddy, if only you had quit smoking!”.</p>
<p>Well, that did not work.</p>
<p>Then he described what DID work. He suggested that people who were having trouble giving up cigarettes were depressed and did not know how to savor simple pleasures in life. Then he had them imagine and think about enjoying various aspects of life. One of them was the pleasure of drinking a beverage that they really liked.</p>
<p>Hearing him mention the example of enjoying a beverage, I thought of the way he asked for “more milk”. Then I knew he was telling us how he had learned to live an exuberant life.</p>
<p>Later, I will tell you some details of what Ted had discovered about effective ways to guide the mind in ways that work for you.</p>
<p>(<em>Edited by Debbie S. Sheridan)</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2012%2F11%2F14%2Fsome-ways-to-manage-your-mind-and-therefore-to-manage-your-body%2F&amp;linkname=Some%20Ways%20to%20Manage%20Your%20Mind%20and%20Therefore%20to%20Manage%20Your%20Body" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Here we go again! Is positivity really bad for you?</title>
		<link>/2012/08/23/here-we-go-again-is-positivity-really-bad-for-you/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 23 Aug 2012 03:08:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Harvard Grant Study]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1120</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In today’s post we will discuss a recent article, , “The Power of Negative Thinking”, published in the New York Times on August 4th. It would be reasonable to expect that anything that appears in the NYT is well-vetted, but &#8230; <a href="/2012/08/23/here-we-go-again-is-positivity-really-bad-for-you/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In today’s post we will discuss a recent article, , “The Power of Negative Thinking”, published in the New York Times on August 4th.</p>
<p>It would be reasonable to expect that anything that appears in the NYT is well-vetted, but you shouldn’t count on that. We read it regularly, and it often publishes articles that help us to think of timely new posts. Sometimes, though, they publish articles that just are not up to snuff.</p>
<p>The article, by Oliver Burkeman, begins by describing an event in which several people, apparently guided by the motivational speaker, Tony Robbins, attempted to walk barefoot over hot, burning coals. Twenty one of them had to be treated for burns. No big surprise for us.</p>
<p>Burkeman points out that physics tells us that “with quick, light steps, you’ll usually be fine”.  He goes on from that “lesson in physics” to turn the event into evidence against positivity.<span id="more-1120"></span></p>
<p>Well, there is overwhelming evidence that positivity helps us to flourish in life. With positivity we recover more quickly from surgery, perform better at work and in sports, are more successful in relationships, live longer, etc.</p>
<p>One would think that the “flagship” of newspapers in this country would require of its authors an awareness of at least a lot of this evidence, but apparently it does not. If you want to challenge the idea that positivity is good for people, why not include the body of serious research that supports this idea?</p>
<p>So, our first point is that this article shows no evidence of the author’s having reviewed the vetted, published literature on positivity and its outcomes.</p>
<p>Mr. Burkeman cites an article by Gabriele Oettingen, who is a real scientist, showing that people who were experimentally water-deprived and asked to picture a refreshing glass of water experienced a marked decline of energy levels compared to those who engaged in negative or neutral fantasies.</p>
<p>Anyone who has kept up with Dr. Oettingen’s research will understand that most of her work shows how effective positive imagining is when we contrast our future selves with and without taking constructive action designed for improvement. We routinely suggest this method to people who attend our workshops.</p>
<p>The body of Oettingen’s work demonstrates the effectiveness of positivity, not its ineffectiveness. It also points out important <span style="text-decoration: underline;">nuances</span> about how we can gain from positivity. So a second point is that the article has taken work out of context in a way that conceals the work&#8217;s overall significance. The nuances of positivity are missing.</p>
<p>Also the article lacks clarity about the definition of positivity. Living in a fantasy world is not the same as cultivating a life of positivity. It has long been known that mere fantasy is not likely to lead to success. George Vaillant in his <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Adaptation-Life-George-E-Vaillant/dp/0674004140">book on the Harvard Grant Study</a>, provides compelling evidence of that. Things like substituting fantasy for taking action to improve our lives and living in denial of the downside of our choices are not what research on positivity represents. Denial and fantasy have long been viewed as <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Defence_mechanism#Level_1_-_Pathological">immature or even pathological defense mechanism</a>, i.e. ways of fending off urges that are in conflict with our sense of self. Vaillant’s work shows that fantasy and denial are maladaptive.</p>
<p>Space limitations do not permit a more thorough analysis of the misconceptions in Burkeman’s article, but one, last point is that the author seems to assume that the cultivation of positivity entails the absence of negativity. Anyone who has read our last few posts will know that current evidence indicates that the needed ratio of positivity to negativity is around 3 positives to 1 negative, not 3 versus zero negatives.</p>
<p>Burkeman also cites Barbara Enrenreich’s grand rejection of positivity as authoritative. We have dealt with that in a <a href="/2010/12/18/is-optimism-really-toxic-5/">previous post</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
