<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Why Resilience? &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/why-resilience/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Recovery and Adaptation</title>
		<link>/2013/09/25/recovery-and-adaptation/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2013 19:47:51 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience and Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Why Resilience?]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1490</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I think it would be hard for anyone who spent even a few years probing deeply into research on stress to deny that it can really damage a person, both psychologically and physically. Reactions to stress are not just “in &#8230; <a href="/2013/09/25/recovery-and-adaptation/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think it would be hard for anyone who spent even a few years probing deeply into research on stress to deny that it can really damage a person, both psychologically and physically. Reactions to stress are not just “in your head”. They are palpable.</p>
<p>Stress is far more important to health than most people think. And the more stress there is in a person’s life, the more likely it is that she or he will become ill.</p>
<p>But the load of stress people can handle without getting sick varies a lot from one person to another. What are the differences between people who are stress resistant and those who are highly vulnerable to stress? And is there some way to guide the more vulnerable people to become more stress resistant?</p>
<p>Once you shift to these questions, you are moving from an emphasis on stress to an emphasis on resilience. We made that shift several decades ago. Our approach has been to identify how resilient people deal with stress, and then to ask how more vulnerable people might learn to use those patterns of resilience.</p>
<p><span id="more-1490"></span></p>
<p>It is important to realize that stress responses are <strong><em>adaptive. </em></strong>So it is not a good idea to just try to stamp out or run away from those responses.</p>
<p>Here is an example of the adaptiveness of the stress response. You have probably heard of the “fight or flight” response. When you have that pattern of responses, your heart pounds rapidly and the little blood vessels in the outer parts of your body constrict.</p>
<p>Since your blood pressure depends on the volume of blood being pumped and the amount of resistance coming from the downstream blood vessels, your blood pressure shoots up under stress. That increases the likelihood of cardiovascular diseases such as heart attack and stroke.</p>
<p>However, the fight or flight responses also help you if you have to fight or flee. Blood flow shifts away from your intestines to your muscles, so you are better equipped for fleeing or fighting. It also shifts away from your skin and coagulates more easily, so you will lose less blood if you are wounded.</p>
<p>So whether stress responses are good or bad depends on the circumstances.</p>
<p>Also, it may be good for you to deliberately stress yourself in order to become more resilient.</p>
<p>To illustrate, it is generally believed, on the basis of much research,  both by experts and by almost everybody else, that exercise is good for you. Yet exercise is stressful, and the physiological response to exercise is identical to the fight or flight response.</p>
<p>To be healthy, exercise has to stay within a range that allows us to recover fully and promptly.</p>
<p>With regular exercise we adapt to stress. We experience a “training effect” that changes our physiology in ways that enable us to exert ourselves more and more, and yet recover without harming ourselves. Basically, exercise increases our <strong><em>resilience</em></strong>.</p>
<p>A bonus is that, once we get that training effect from physical exercise, we can even handle psychological stress more comfortably.</p>
<p>Some people are just gifted with an ability to put out more work (or take more hits) than others, and still not be permanently or seriously damaged. But virtually all of us can build up resistance to stress by gradually increasing our stress level while holding back enough that we can still recover efficiently.</p>
<p>In the older research literature on the stress of work, it was pretty clear that people were working themselves to death. In the United States our idea of a full work-week has long been 40 hours. And at least part of the weekends are commonly time off or at least paid extra “overtime” salaries. (That appears to be changing as the rift between the well off and ordinary middle class and laboring people grows).</p>
<p>In many European countries, the work week is even shorter than that.  So now instead of hearing that work kills us, we often find studies concluding that <a href="http://www.medpagetoday.com/PrimaryCare/PreventiveCare/1980"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">retirement</span> kills us</a>.</p>
<p>It was Aaron Antonovky’s book “Health, Stress, and Coping” that helped clarify for us the importance of adaptation to and prompt recovery from stress. He spoke of “Stress resistance resources”; those resources underlie our ability to adapt to greater levels of stress. They are the primary source of resilience.</p>
<p>A great deal of research on resilience has centered on psychological patterns that make us more resilient. But Antonovsky saw that as only one category of factors that make us more resilient. For example, he included cultural or communal patterns that foster healthy, happy, successful, and resilient lives.</p>
<p>He did his research in Israel, a part of the world that included people who had been deprived of even the most basic resources that might help them adapt. These were survivors of Nazi concentration camps.  Of course they had a life before the camps, and had been able to develop inner resilience.</p>
<p>By tracking down the factors that differentiated people who came out of those camps and went on to do well, often exceptionally well, he concluded that some people have resources that lead them to be resilient even when those resources are taken from them.</p>
<p>He went on to say that researchers should turn their attention away from stress and toward resilience. He came to believe that we should be looking into what keeps us well (“Salutogenisis”) instead of what makes us ill (“Pathogenesis”).</p>
<p>He maintained that stress is so common that all of us are stressed enough to get sick from it.</p>
<p>That means we should focus on the science of resilience, which is what we have done.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F09%2F25%2F1490%2F&amp;linkname=Recovery%20and%20Adaptation" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Resilience Is More than Bouncing Back From Stress</title>
		<link>/2011/07/05/resilience-is-more-than-bouncing-back-from-stress/</link>
		<comments>/2011/07/05/resilience-is-more-than-bouncing-back-from-stress/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2011 06:06:12 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Why Resilience?]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=800</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In this post I want to take a closer look at what resilience is and who can gain from training to increase it. People often tell me that I should explain resilience as the ability to “bounce back” from stress. &#8230; <a href="/2011/07/05/resilience-is-more-than-bouncing-back-from-stress/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this post I want to take a closer look at what resilience is and who can gain from training to increase it.</p>
<p>People often tell me that I should explain resilience as the ability to “bounce back” from stress. I hate that view of resilience. It always reminds me of those inflated dummies that are designed to come right back to an upright position after they are punched, setting themselves up to be punched again. That is not resilience. It is mindlessness, literally in this case.</p>
<p>A much better description of resilience is “playing a poor hand well”. There is a pretty good <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Playing-Poor-Hand-Well-Professional/dp/0393702324" target="_self">book by that title</a>, and I commend the author for the book and the title.</p>
<p>But even that title fails to get it quite right. Resilience is having the ability to play <em>any</em> hand well. If you were dealt a poor hand, resilience is the set of abilities that enable you to perform above expectations. If you were dealt a good hand, it is the set of abilities that enable you to make the most of it. In other words, resilience enables you to deal with stress efficiently and effectively, to recover from stress more quickly and more completely. But, stress aside, it enables you to perform at your best level, whether in your work, in sports, or in relationships.</p>
<p>So it is not easy to target precisely who needs resilience training because the audience is really just about everybody. Maybe the best way to pinpoint who is a good match for training and who is not is to break people down into:</p>
<ul>
<li>Those who need help in developing      their skills for dealing with stress and living up to their potential in      life and also know they need help.</li>
<li>Those who need help in      developing those skills and do not know it.</li>
</ul>
<p>A final word.</p>
<p>Years ago I used to lend a large set of my data on stress and resilience for use in an advanced statistics class, where the students were learning to find the meanings hidden in masses of data. The instructor always invited me to sit in on a long session in which each student reported on their findings. In one of those classes a student who was a real standout in statistics reported that she had detected a very large factor in the data, for which she had struggled to give an adequate name. She decided to call it “Good Life”.</p>
<p>It was the factor that made the largest contribution to resilience. After many more years of study, we identified that factor as “resilient attitudes and skills”. I often think that “Good Life” gives an excellent sense of what developing resilient attitudes and skills might provide.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2011%2F07%2F05%2Fresilience-is-more-than-bouncing-back-from-stress%2F&amp;linkname=Resilience%20Is%20More%20than%20Bouncing%20Back%20From%20Stress" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2011/07/05/resilience-is-more-than-bouncing-back-from-stress/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why a Blog On Resilience?</title>
		<link>/2010/11/04/why-a-blog-on-resilience/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2010 03:33:38 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Why Resilience?]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=380</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[“Antonovsky’s studies led him to conclude that: there is enough stress in this world to make any and all of us get sick. looking at variations in stress was not a smart approach for anyone interested in predicting who would &#8230; <a href="/2010/11/04/why-a-blog-on-resilience/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>“<em>Antonovsky’s studies led him to conclude that:</em></p>
<ul>
<li><em>there is enough stress in this world to make any and all of us get sick. </em></li>
<li><em>looking at variations in stress was not a smart approach for anyone interested in predicting who would break down or in making human life better.”</em></li>
</ul>
<p><em>“…if the stress is locked in, unlikely to change, and pervasive, it would be best to focus on strategies for controlling its impact, not on how stressed we are.”</em></p>
<p>Paradoxically, this generally optimistic blog was born of despair. For many years I worked, as a research-oriented professor studying stress. Like most stress researchers, I focused on the health consequences of living with a lot of stress.</p>
<p>It was the work of Aaron Antonovsky that steered me in a new direction. He was an American-Israeli medical sociologist who studied the qualities that determined who survived Hitler’s concentration camps and which survivors ended up healthier than others.</p>
<p>Antonovsky found that, at the center of this distinction was a set of attitudes he called “the sense of coherence”. People with a high sense of coherence managed to find something they could believe in and commit to even in this most toxic of environments.</p>
<p>Eventually Antonovsky’s studies led him to conclude that:</p>
<ul>
<li>there is enough stress in this world to make any and all of us get sick.</li>
<li>looking at variations in stress was not a smart approach for anyone interested in predicting who would break down or in making human life better.</li>
</ul>
<p><span id="more-380"></span></p>
<p>For me, it took a while for that lesson to sink in. But I came eventually to see that, if the stress is locked in, unlikely to change, and pervasive, it would be best to focus on strategies for controlling its impact, not on how stressed we are.</p>
<p><em>I shifted my research emphasis to identifying the core characteristics that make some people resilient and others vulnerable.</em></p>
<p>After more than two decades of research, I was able to show that there are three core characteristics that determine how resilient people are. In later posts, we will detail them, but for now the most important thing so say is that having seen the nature of those characteristics, it was clear that psychologists already had ways of teaching people how to become more resilient.</p>
<p>My wife, Debbie,  and I decided to write a book on how to change resilience. As the book neared completion, I kept finding new research that I wanted to include in the book. Debbie began to emphasize to me that I could not go on indefinitely adding things to the manuscript. This blog was our solution. Here we can be brief accounts of what is in the book and also show how new research relates to our work.</p>
<p>Hopefully, a final advantage of the blog, will be that enough readers will comment on posts so that we can improve our thinking about resilience through dialogue and learn how readers are improving their own resilience.</p>
<p>So here it is! Please join us.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2010%2F11%2F04%2Fwhy-a-blog-on-resilience%2F&amp;linkname=Why%20a%20Blog%20On%20Resilience%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why Building Resilience Is Better Than Controlling Stress.</title>
		<link>/2010/11/04/why-building-resilience-is-better-than-controlling-stress/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2010 03:32:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Why Resilience?]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=376</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[“People who do well in life don’t do so by arranging for it to be stress free or even close to that. If your source of stress is something you can change, you should change it. But, even after removing &#8230; <a href="/2010/11/04/why-building-resilience-is-better-than-controlling-stress/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>“People who do well in life don’t do so by arranging for it to be stress free or even close to that. If your source of stress is something you can change, you should change it. But, even after removing things like that, a lot of stress will remain.” </em></p>
<p>High resilience is the main key to living well in this stressful world.</p>
<p>Resilience is a set of attitudes, skills, and habits that make us, when challenged by stress, react less and recover more quickly and completely. There is good evidence that it can make us healthier and enable us to be more successful and happier.</p>
<p>For years the dominant idea has been that stress can make us sick, which is absolutely true. Almost daily there is more and better research attesting to the role of stress in health, illness, quality of life, and success in life. This evidence tells us that we really need to find ways to limit the impact of stress. How do we do that?</p>
<p>If you think back on magazine articles you’ve read, lectures you’ve heard, or advice you’ve gotten from friends, it’s likely they have all emphasized reducing your stress. But if you look closely at what has stressed you, you will find that most of it has been either entirely or largely out of your control.</p>
<p>You can’t just decide not to get laid off, not to have your “life” partner fall in love with someone else, or not to go through the holiday season.</p>
<p><span id="more-376"></span></p>
<p>To illustrate the point further, let’s take a look at the Holmes-Rahe Scale, a short paper and pencil test that put stress control on the map. It has appeared over and over in articles on how to deal with stress. It lists a number of “life events” that increase your stress load. Add up your score on this test, and you have a reliable predictor of future problems with your health.</p>
<p>The trouble is that a large proportion of the stressful events listed on this test are out of your control. The first items are “Death of a spouse”, then “Divorce”, “Marital separation”, “Jail term”, “Death of a close family member”, and so on.</p>
<p>Most human environments are fundamentally stressful. Stress comes close to being part of “the human condition”.</p>
<p>People who do well in life don’t do so by arranging for it to be stress free or even close to that. If your source of stress is something you can change, you should change it. But, even after removing things like that, a lot of stress will remain.</p>
<p>High resilience is the main key to living well in this stressful world. Some fortunate people are naturally resilient. They have the right genes and were taught early in life to approach stress effectively.</p>
<p>They are the lucky ones. Most of us have to work to develop habitual ways of handling life’s challenges that protect us from damage. How?</p>
<p>That is where resilience training comes in.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
