<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Self-Soothing &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/self-soothing/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The Powers of the Mind 1</title>
		<link>/2016/06/01/the-powers-of-the-mind-1/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2016 18:53:11 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Meditation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2082</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[There is a graph that has stayed alive in Jerry&#8217;s mind for decades. It was in a study designed to see what happens if a person is given gradual increases in the dosage of isoproterenol, a drug that imitates adrenaline, &#8230; <a href="/2016/06/01/the-powers-of-the-mind-1/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There is a graph that has stayed alive in Jerry&#8217;s mind for decades. It was in a study designed to see what happens if a person is given gradual increases in the dosage of isoproterenol, a drug that imitates adrenaline, the familiar &#8220;fight or flight&#8221; hormone. It is used primarily to deal with abnormally  slow and weak heartbeat  ( bradycardia), and heart block.</p>
<p>(Heart Block is an abnormal heart rhythm in which the heart beats too slowly. In this condition, the electrical signals that tell the heart to contract are blocked between the heart&#8217;s upper and lower chambers.)</p>
<p>The study appears to have been a routine one of the &#8220;dose-response curve&#8221;, to observe changes in heart rate as the dosage of the drug was gradually increased. Isoproterenol works by making changes in the junctions between the nervous system  and the heart muscle.</p>
<p>Not surprisingly, heart rate increased with each increment of the drug dosage, but there was one person whose heart followed the expected pattern as the dose was increased from zero to .1 on to .5 micrograms, but then began slowing down as the dose continued to be increased to 1.0, 2.0, and on to 4.0 micrograms.</p>
<p>The heart rate of the unusual person went from around 68 beats per minute (bpm) before any drug was given, to above 80 bpm at a dosage but then went down steadily to end up at around 53 bpm when the drug was at its top level. At this top dosage the other participants had a heart rate around 90 bpm.</p>
<p>What was going on? When the researchers asked the outlier that question, she said she had become bored and started meditating just before bher heart rate slowed down.</p>
<p>On occasion, there are reports of remarkable bodily control on the part of people who have devoted a great deal of their lives engaged in training that results in unusual control of mind over body. For example a Yogi, the Swami Rama was studied at the Menninger Clinic, and was able to make one part of his hand warm up while cooling a nearby part. He also showed that he could stop his heart from pumping while connected to an electronic device that measured his physiological reactions. This device would make it impossible to do any tricks to give an unreal impression of  bodily control.</p>
<p>If you want more detail on Swami Rama, the person who acted as his personal assistant in the  United States wrote a book, &#8220;Swami&#8221;, about him. It appears to be out of print, but inexpensive copies are available at Abebooks.com.</p>
<p>A lesson that we can take from such accomplishments is that regular practice of effective procedures such as meditation  can lead to our developing skills that enable us to gain remarkable control over our minds and bodies.</p>
<p>The woman who lowered her heart rate was able to challenge and defeat the biological system that underlies fight or flight. It is a system that also underlies &#8220;losing one&#8217;s temper&#8221; and even violent acts under some circumstances. It also underlies such things as stage fright, and a score of other things that we might want to bring under our control.</p>
<p>It is interesting to know that the woman who controlled her heart was self- trained. It is usually best to have a trainer, but some people can do well even on their own. The take-home message is that self-control is probably within your reach. The key is &#8220;practice, practice, practice&#8221;.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Path to Greater Resilience: From Attitudes to Skills and to Habits.</title>
		<link>/2015/09/09/the-path-to-greater-resilience-from-attitudes-to-skills-and-to-habits/</link>
		<comments>/2015/09/09/the-path-to-greater-resilience-from-attitudes-to-skills-and-to-habits/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2015 20:41:26 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Attitudes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Habits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1982</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[When we discussed the Sense of Coherence in our previous post, we said that it was a match for the first factor in our three factor model of resilience. In both popular culture (e.g. Rev. Normal Vincent Peale’s “The Power &#8230; <a href="/2015/09/09/the-path-to-greater-resilience-from-attitudes-to-skills-and-to-habits/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When we discussed the Sense of Coherence in our previous post, we said that it was a match for the first factor in our three factor model of resilience.</p>
<p>In both popular culture (e.g. Rev. Normal Vincent Peale’s “The Power of Positive Thinking” which had a huge impact in the United States and elsewhere) and scientifically developed theory (e.g. Barbara Frederickson’s book, “Positivity”), the value of positivity has been recognized as playing a major role in lives well-lived.</p>
<p>But we see a distinction between attitudes of positivity and positive skills that are closely connected to those attitudes.</p>
<p>Probably most people would predict that positive attitudes and thoughts are related to resilience. But having skills such as knowing ways to calm and soothe yourself when distressed have been given less attention. In addition, many of us possess the needed skills, but do not implement them.</p>
<p>Once we take the skills to the point where we actually implement them when they are needed, we have reached the third level of using resilience tools, the level of habit.</p>
<p>In sum, we have to go from attitudes to skills and on to habits.</p>
<p>Isn’t this a lot of work? It can be, but for the most part the process is very enjoyable, even exhilarating at times.</p>
<p>Do we need to say that we think you should give it a try?</p>
<p>If you decide to do that, <a href="/2014/12/22/prepare-for-your-later-life-by-accumulating-skills-and-habits-of-resilience/">this</a> and <a href="/2014/10/08/build-your-toughness-and-become-more-resilient/">this</a> will help get you started.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2015%2F09%2F09%2Fthe-path-to-greater-resilience-from-attitudes-to-skills-and-to-habits%2F&amp;linkname=The%20Path%20to%20Greater%20Resilience%3A%20From%20Attitudes%20to%20Skills%20and%20to%20Habits." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2015/09/09/the-path-to-greater-resilience-from-attitudes-to-skills-and-to-habits/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Recovery from Stress: Use Resilience Resources You Already Have to Calm and Sooth Yourself.</title>
		<link>/2014/02/27/recovery-from-stress-use-resilience-resources-you-already-have-to-calm-and-sooth-yourself/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2014 21:18:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1617</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Your mental and biological reactions to stress are attempts to help you survive and go on to live a rich life. Stress left unchecked can destroy you. On the other hand, experiencing a level of stress from which you can &#8230; <a href="/2014/02/27/recovery-from-stress-use-resilience-resources-you-already-have-to-calm-and-sooth-yourself/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Your mental and biological reactions to stress are attempts to help you survive and go on to live a rich life. Stress left unchecked can destroy you. On the other hand, experiencing a level of stress from which you can fairly quickly recover can even make you stronger and more resilient.</p>
<p>The often disturbing mental and biological reactions to stress can be hard to take, but they reflect the best solutions you, and even your biological ancestors, have been able to come up with to deal with life’s challenges.</p>
<p>If you cannot imagine that the stress reactions are helpful and adaptive, think of regular exercise. Exercise is good for you, but is also stressful. It is good for you <strong><em>because </em></strong>it is stressful, and you <strong><em>can handle it.</em></strong></p>
<p>When you exercise, you trigger basic aspects of the classic “fight or flight response”. But if you choose your exercise wisely, you can recover quickly and fully, and your mind and body will eventually change in ways that enable you to take that level of stress in your stride.</p>
<p>If you crank the exercise stress up slowly you are likely to improve your resilience. If you push yourself too much, you can expect to exceed the protective influence of your current resilience skills. If you keep that up, you will eventually experience some kind of breakdown.</p>
<p>On the other hand if you pace yourself carefully, you can improve how quickly and fully you recover from stress. You can become more resilient.</p>
<p>We only mean to use exercise as an <em>example</em> of controlled stress. Though exercise is, indeed, a valuable way to deal with stress, that is not our main message in this post.</p>
<p>Our main point is that, unless stress is extreme and/or perpetuated for a long time, whether you know how to calm down stress reactions, to return to your normal baseline quickly and fully is far more important  than the stress itself to determine whether stress leaves you stronger or breaks you.</p>
<p>In the last few posts, we have focused on techniques that have been tested in people’s lives sometimes for centuries, and have also been shown to be effective when tested scientifically. Specifically, we have explained how to do mantra meditation, and how to practice “loving kindness”. Both of these have been shown to make for a better life.</p>
<p>Before you can use these methods, there is a “learning curve” you must go through to use them. We strongly advocate that you learn how to use them. But there are also methods that most people already know how to use, but that are often not given the respect they deserve. We have described some of these methods <a href="/2010/11/04/natural-stress-defeaters/">here</a>. They include things that do not require you to learn new skills. We derived them by keeping track, over more than a decade, of publications that show how ordinary people, without any special training,  deal with stress.</p>
<p><span id="more-1617"></span></p>
<p>Briefly, examples include:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong><em>Contact comfort with pets or with people</em></strong>, e.g. cuddling with a pet or loved one; getting a massage.</li>
<li><strong><em>Pleasant, engrossing distraction</em></strong>, e.g. watching comedies, getting out into nature.</li>
<li><strong><em>Soothing sensory stimulation</em></strong>, e.g. taking a hot bath or shower, listening to calming music.</li>
<li><strong><em>Physical activity</em></strong>, e.g. dancing, taking a walk or exercising until you are tired.</li>
<li><strong><em>Contemplative relaxation</em></strong>, e.g. meditation, Yoga.</li>
<li><strong><em>Spiritual activities</em></strong>, e.g. praying, attending religious services.</li>
</ul>
<p>You can add to this whatever you already know works for you. Think over things that have calmed you in the past, and use them when you are distressed.</p>
<p>The trick is to get yourself to actually DO them. For advice on how to do that, click <a href="/2010/12/06/getting-yourself-to-act-on-what-you-learn-about-building-resilience/">here</a>.</p>
<p>The take-home message is to learn the real value of simple things that calm and sooth you, and to make sure you actually do those things when you need them.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F02%2F27%2Frecovery-from-stress-use-resilience-resources-you-already-have%2F&amp;linkname=Recovery%20from%20Stress%3A%20Use%20Resilience%20Resources%20You%20Already%20Have%20to%20Calm%20and%20Sooth%20Yourself." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Can We Make Ourselves Biologically Younger?</title>
		<link>/2013/10/17/can-we-make-ourselves-biologically-younger/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2013 05:47:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Benefits of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mindfulness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience and Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1516</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Some years ago we became aware of the important role of telomeres in aging, and the role of stress in speeding up the aging process. Telomeres are genetic components that are linked to biological aging. Usually, the older you are &#8230; <a href="/2013/10/17/can-we-make-ourselves-biologically-younger/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Some years ago we became aware of the important role of telomeres in aging, and the role of stress in speeding up the aging process. Telomeres are genetic components that are linked to biological aging. Usually, the older you are the shorter your telomeres become.</p>
<p>What did this have to do with resilience? Well, resilience controls stress, and it turns out that higher levels of stress result in increased shortening of telomeres. So your calendar age is not the only determinant of how old your cells are. Stress is a highly significant influence.</p>
<p>In fact, women who reported being highly stressed were biologically, as indexed by telomere length, about ten years older than those who did not report high stress.</p>
<p>In one of our early resilience workshops, one person in the group asked an obvious question that hadn’t occurred to us. “Is there anything that can enable us to <strong><em>lengthen</em></strong> our telomeres?&#8221; We paused, and had to say that we did not know.</p>
<p>Since that time, a good deal of research has shown that we can indeed lengthen our telomeres through lifestyle changes.</p>
<p>We were working on our usual exhaustive examination of the scientifically respectable evidence that people can lengthen their telomeres when we discovered the following interview of Dr. Dean Ornish, who recently completed a study on how the telomeres can be lengthened. We decided to re-post his video, which does a very good job of explaining what we need to do to lengthen our telomeres. We weren&#8217;t likely to improve, in a short post, on what he says in this interview. And it isn&#8217;t just a promotion of his own work; he talks about a wide range or research pointing in the same direction as his.</p>
<p><iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/QPpJU8Je-lE" frameborder="0" width="420" height="315"></iframe></p>
<p>It appears that telomeres can indeed be lengthened, and that well established healthy lifestyle changes can produce the lengthening.</p>
<p>Naturally attempts are being made to develop a kind of &#8220;Fountain of Youth&#8221; pill that can lengthen telomeres. We would recommend that such pills be viewed with great caution. It&#8217;s one thing to do things we already know are good for you and thus lengthen telomeres and quite another to take a new pill that needs lengthy testing.</p>
<p>As we have pointed out previously in this blog, the body is a highly complex, interactive ecosystem. Change one thing and many other unpredictable changes are likely to occur. The enzyme, telomerase stimulates growth of telomeres. But there is a lot of telomerase in certain malignant tumors. So who can say what kinds of side effects might result from artificial tampering?</p>
<p>On the other hand, sensible exercise, eating a healthy diet, learning to live peacefully with others, and calming ourselves through meditation have been around for centuries, and we know that their side effects improve lives</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F10%2F17%2Fcan-we-make-ourselves-biologically-younger%2F&amp;linkname=Can%20We%20Make%20Ourselves%20Biologically%20Younger%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Map of the Path to Increased Resilience.</title>
		<link>/2013/06/20/a-map-of-the-path-to-increased-resilience/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2013 05:19:14 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Attitudes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1392</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Underlying our posts is a three-factor model of resilience which was derived from research done as part of my role as a professor. Our posts tend to be on specific attitudes or actions that are statistically confirmed aspects of one &#8230; <a href="/2013/06/20/a-map-of-the-path-to-increased-resilience/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Underlying our posts is a three-factor model of resilience which was derived from research done as part of my role as a professor. Our posts tend to be on specific attitudes or actions that are statistically confirmed aspects of one of the three factors. That is not because we select them only if they match our model. Our model just matches the data.</p>
<p>The blog was not started to publicize or support the model. It started as an outlet to keep me from constantly adding new findings to a book Debbie and I wrote to teach people how to improve their resilience.</p>
<p>To identify the core factors that underlie resilience we used a method called factor analysis. Done correctly, it can reveal the deep structure of whatever you are studying. So, for example, if you used it on three dimensional objects, like boxes, it would tell you that there are three dimensions, height, width and length.</p>
<p>We determined the dimensions of resilience and found that there were three. We also replicated that finding in two additional studies, and both of them confirmed the three dimensions.</p>
<p>To explain the factors here would be redundant, since we have already done that in <a href="/2011/01/11/the-three-core-factors-that-can-make-you-more-resilient/">this post</a>.</p>
<p>For now, we will discuss the number one factor that improves resilience.</p>
<h2>What good is this to you?</h2>
<p>Knowing the core dimensions will help you pinpoint all you can do to improve your resilience.</p>
<p>The number one influence on resilience is developing resilience-promoting  <strong><em>attitudes</em></strong> and <strong><em>skills</em></strong>.  These account for so much of resilience that, for a while, I was tempted to think of Factor One alone as just plain resilience, and ignore the other two factors. But too much evidence showed that those factors can be crucial for many people.</p>
<p>So what are the attitudes and skills you should try to develop?</p>
<p><span id="more-1392"></span></p>
<ul>
<li>Being optimistic and hopeful instead of pessimistic and hopeless.</li>
<li>Seeing distressing or painful life events as problems to be solved instead of things to be lamented and cursed.</li>
<li>Looking for and maybe even finding meaning in what we do and what we experience instead of just slogging through life.</li>
<li>Learning how to sooth, calm and replenish yourself, and then <strong><em>applying what you have learned </em></strong>to your everyday life when you are distressed, and also when you are feeling okay. (The latter is important in order to develop <strong><em>habits</em></strong> of resilience.).</li>
</ul>
<p>Some of the attitudes under factor one that help us be more resilient are</p>
<ol start="1">
<li>Being optimistic and hopeful versus viewing life with pessimism or despair.</li>
</ol>
<p>Here are posts that tell you how to do that:</p>
<p><a href="/2011/01/01/less-pessimism-and-more-optimism-will-build-your-resilience/">Increasing your optimism.</a></p>
<p><a href="/2012/08/02/reducing-negativity-in-your-mind-and-your-life/">Decreasing your negativity.</a></p>
<ol start="2">
<li>Viewing our lives, our choices, and our actions as meaningful versus seeing them as meaningless.</li>
</ol>
<p>Here is a post to help you do that.</p>
<p><a href="/2011/11/28/finding-meaning-and-purpose-can-help-you-deal-with-distress-no-matter-how-extreme/">Finding  meaning.</a></p>
<ol start="3">
<li>Taking a problem-solving attitude toward stressful situations and anticipating predictable complications.</li>
</ol>
<p>Here is a post that shows you how to do that:</p>
<p><a href="/2012/08/02/reducing-negativity-in-your-mind-and-your-life/">Problem-Solving Attitude.</a></p>
<ol start="4">
<li>Learning and applying  the skills that sooth and replenish you instead of taking actions that make things worse.</li>
</ol>
<p>There are many posts that show how to do that:</p>
<p><a href="/2011/03/02/basic-mindfulness-technique/">Training yourself in mindfulness.</a></p>
<p><a href="/2011/06/02/tactical-breathing-can-stop-stress-on-the-spot/">Breath control for resilience.</a></p>
<p><a href="/2010/12/06/a-key-step-in-resilience-training-is-learning-deep-relaxation/">Learning deep relaxation.</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F06%2F20%2Fa-map-of-the-path-to-increased-resilience%2F&amp;linkname=A%20Map%20of%20the%20Path%20to%20Increased%20Resilience." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Overthinking No More.</title>
		<link>/2013/05/13/overthinking-no-more/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2013 15:46:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Compassion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Understanding]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1370</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I don’t remember where I first ran into the concept of overthinking, but it appealed to me. Both Debbie and I understand the limitations of the parts of the brain that underlie thinking. We also are aware of the often &#8230; <a href="/2013/05/13/overthinking-no-more/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><!--[if gte mso 9]><xml>
<o:OfficeDocumentSettings>
<o:AllowPNG/>
</o:OfficeDocumentSettings>
</xml><![endif]--></p>
<p><!--[if gte mso 9]><xml>
<w:WordDocument>
<w:View>Normal</w:View>
<w:Zoom>0</w:Zoom>
<w:TrackMoves/>
<w:TrackFormatting/>
<w:PunctuationKerning/>
<w:ValidateAgainstSchemas/>
<w:SaveIfXMLInvalid>false</w:SaveIfXMLInvalid>
<w:IgnoreMixedContent>false</w:IgnoreMixedContent>
<w:AlwaysShowPlaceholderText>false</w:AlwaysShowPlaceholderText>
<w:DoNotPromoteQF/>
<w:LidThemeOther>EN-US</w:LidThemeOther>
<w:LidThemeAsian>X-NONE</w:LidThemeAsian>
<w:LidThemeComplexScript>X-NONE</w:LidThemeComplexScript>
<w:Compatibility>
<w:BreakWrappedTables/>
<w:SnapToGridInCell/>
<w:WrapTextWithPunct/>
<w:UseAsianBreakRules/>
<w:DontGrowAutofit/>
<w:SplitPgBreakAndParaMark/>
<w:EnableOpenTypeKerning/>
<w:DontFlipMirrorIndents/>
<w:OverrideTableStyleHps/>
</w:Compatibility>
<m:mathPr>
<m:mathFont m:val="Cambria Math"/>
<m:brkBin m:val="before"/>
<m:brkBinSub m:val="&#45;-"/>
<m:smallFrac m:val="off"/>
<m:dispDef/>
<m:lMargin m:val="0"/>
<m:rMargin m:val="0"/>
<m:defJc m:val="centerGroup"/>
<m:wrapIndent m:val="1440"/>
<m:intLim m:val="subSup"/>
<m:naryLim m:val="undOvr"/>
</m:mathPr></w:WordDocument>
</xml><![endif]--><!--[if gte mso 9]><xml>
<w:LatentStyles DefLockedState="false" DefUnhideWhenUsed="true"
DefSemiHidden="true" DefQFormat="false" DefPriority="99"
LatentStyleCount="267">
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="0" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Normal"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="heading 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 7"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 8"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="9" QFormat="true" Name="heading 9"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 7"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 8"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" Name="toc 9"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="35" QFormat="true" Name="caption"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="10" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Title"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="1" Name="Default Paragraph Font"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="11" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Subtitle"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="22" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Strong"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="20" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Emphasis"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="59" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Table Grid"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Placeholder Text"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="1" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="No Spacing"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Revision"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="34" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="List Paragraph"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="29" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Quote"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="30" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Intense Quote"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3 Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid Accent 1"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3 Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid Accent 2"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3 Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid Accent 3"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3 Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid Accent 4"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3 Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid Accent 5"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="60" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Shading Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="61" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light List Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="62" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Light Grid Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="63" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 1 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="64" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Shading 2 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="65" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 1 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="66" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium List 2 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="67" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 1 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="68" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 2 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="69" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Medium Grid 3 Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="70" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Dark List Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="71" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Shading Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="72" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful List Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="73" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" Name="Colorful Grid Accent 6"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="19" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Subtle Emphasis"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="21" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Intense Emphasis"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="31" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Subtle Reference"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="32" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Intense Reference"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="33" SemiHidden="false"
UnhideWhenUsed="false" QFormat="true" Name="Book Title"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="37" Name="Bibliography"/>
<w:LsdException Locked="false" Priority="39" QFormat="true" Name="TOC Heading"/>
</w:LatentStyles>
</xml><![endif]--><!--[if gte mso 10]>


<style>
 /* Style Definitions */
 table.MsoNormalTable
	{mso-style-name:"Table Normal";
	mso-tstyle-rowband-size:0;
	mso-tstyle-colband-size:0;
	mso-style-noshow:yes;
	mso-style-priority:99;
	mso-style-parent:"";
	mso-padding-alt:0in 5.4pt 0in 5.4pt;
	mso-para-margin:0in;
	mso-para-margin-bottom:.0001pt;
	mso-pagination:widow-orphan;
	font-size:10.0pt;
	font-family:"Calibri","sans-serif";}
</style>

<![endif]--></p>
<p>I don’t remember where I first ran into the concept of overthinking, but it appealed to me. Both Debbie and I understand the limitations of the parts of the brain that underlie thinking. We also are aware of the often unrecognized strengths of the “emotional brain”, which is commonly regarded as a giving birth to mere “fluff”.</p>
<p>Emotion is certainly not “fluff”.<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Descartes-Error-Emotion-Reason-Human/dp/014303622X/ref=sr_1_3?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1368458741&amp;sr=1-3&amp;keywords=antonio+damasio"> Antonio and Hannah Da Massio</a> have shown that we need cooperation between the emotional brain and the thinking brain in order to deal with the real world. They showed that people with brain injuries that left both their thinking and their emotional brains intact, but blocked them from cooperating with each other resulted in smart people with extremely poor judgment.</p>
<p>These people could do very well on IQ tests, and even give intelligent answers to questions like “How many giraffes are there in the United States” that require creative and complicated thinking strategies.</p>
<p>So, when I ran into several articles about overthinking, I already knew that placing too much emphasis on thinking and too little on feeling and emotions would lead to poor outcomes. So the word “overthinking” grabbed my attention.</p>
<p>The go-to book on overthinking is one called “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Women-Who-Think-Too-Much/dp/0805075259/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1368459003&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=women+who+think+too+muchhttp://">Women Who Think Too Much</a>” by Prof. Susan Noel-Hoeksema. (Why just women? She pointed out that women are more likely than men to overthink. That is true, but actually, the few available research <a href="http://www.refocuser.com/2009/08/9-ways-to-stop-overthinking-everything/">sources</a> indicate a small, though statistically significant difference. So the book is also useful for guys).</p>
<p>As I began working my way through the book, I was impressed, and I recommended it to Debbie.</p>
<p>But, eventually I saw that reading the book is like taking a ride on a roller coaster, with the excitement and fun of learning alternating with pages of tedium. (This was my experience, not necessarily the objective truth.)</p>
<p>The best thing about the book is that it is full of methods for reducing overthinking.</p>
<p>So, here is my take:</p>
<p><span id="more-1370"></span></p>
<p>What is overthinking? Professor Noel-Hoeksema describes it as “going over and over your negative thoughts and feelings, kneading them like dough. She applies the term the “yeast effect”.  “Just as yeasty bread dough will double in size after it’s been kneaded, our negative thoughts expand, grow, and begin to take up all the space around them in our minds.”</p>
<p>We have always emphasized the damaging effects of stress amplification in limiting resilience. That last thing you should do when times are harsh is to alienate your supporters, tear yourself down, exaggerate your hopelessness… You get the idea- when you are in a distressing situation, you need someone who is on your side, but also smart about what helps and what hurts.</p>
<p>Clearly it doesn’t sound like a good thing to overthink. Research has linked it to depression. “When sadness is amplified instead of managed, it can take you down paths to hopelessness, self-hate, and immobility.”</p>
<p>It also increases anxiety, which can lead to a nasty physiological and psychological avalanche, ending in chronic arousal that “wears down the body” and eventually makes it hard for you to deal with even mildly challenging situations. All we can say is “Amen”.</p>
<p>So what can you do about overthinking? Here is a mix of examples from her book and some others that we think are also useful:</p>
<ul>
<li>Look for interpretations of distressing events that are not as damning as the ones that first come to mind.  Could nasty, critical comments about you be wrong, even silly and more about the critic than about you?</li>
<li>You should accept and attend to your negative feelings. But don’t be ruled by them. This is possibly the most important thing you can learn about scary feelings; you can have them and just keep going with what you judge to be in your best interest.</li>
<li>Don’t wait for someone else to rescue you; get going on ways to take care of yourself. Focus on what you can do for yourself, and if someone else helps, be thankful for their caring, but realize that it is the delicious frosting on the cake.</li>
<li>Brainstorm for possible ways to change your situation. The first few solutions you come up with are probably a tiny fraction of what you can discover if you unleash your creativity.</li>
<li>Start with something small. Small change adds up.</li>
<li>Don’t let uncertainly stop you from acting. Move forward even though you are uncertain about whether your solution will work. Doing <strong><em>something</em></strong> at the very least gives you dignity.</li>
<li>When you are having catastrophic thoughts about yourself, ask if these thoughts are merely echoing the unsupportive words of others who spoke without looking out for your interests.</li>
<li>Focus on your <strong><em>feelings</em></strong>, attend to what you are feeling in your body. This is usually the best source of what you really need to know in order to find an answer that can help you.</li>
<li>Don’t forget to exercise, even if it is for only a few minutes per day. Exercise improves
<ul>
<li>Stress-related aspects of your physiology.</li>
<li>The positivity and clarity of your thoughts.</li>
<li>Your level of calmness.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2013%2F05%2F13%2Foverthinking-no-more%2F&amp;linkname=Overthinking%20No%20More." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Some Positive Things in Your Life That You May Not Have Noticed</title>
		<link>/2012/07/18/1084/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 18 Jul 2012 04:38:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1084</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[A couple of posts ago, we said that most of us are “swimming in positives, but not attending to them”. Given how difficult life is for so many people these days, it might seem to be an absurd claim. So &#8230; <a href="/2012/07/18/1084/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A couple of posts ago, we said that most of us are “swimming in positives, but not attending to them”. Given how difficult life is for so many people these days, it might seem to be an absurd claim. So we will spend some time giving illustrations of why we say that.</p>
<p>An excellent example is in a voiceover that starts the movie “Love Actually”. The person speaking is the Prime Minister of England, who is a person full of wisdom and heart.</p>
<p>Here it is as text:</p>
<p>“Whenever I get gloomy with the state of the world, I think about the arrivals gate at Heathrow Airport. General opinion&#8217;s starting to make out that we live in a world of hatred and greed, but I don&#8217;t see that. It seems to me that love is everywhere. Often, it&#8217;s not particularly dignified or newsworthy, but it&#8217;s always there &#8211; fathers and sons, mothers and daughters, husbands and wives, boyfriends, girlfriends, old friends. When the planes hit the Twin Towers, as far as I know, none of the phone calls from the people on board were messages of hate or revenge &#8211; they were all messages of love. If you look for it, I&#8217;ve got a sneaking suspicion&#8230; love actually is all around.”</p>
<p>However, Debbie and I both felt that it had more impact as a video, so it’s embedded below.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/j0O2FfpAP0Q?rel=0" frameborder="0" width="640" height="360"></iframe></p>
<p>A second illustration is a blog entry called “<a href="http://www.marcandangel.com/2011/01/03/40-extraordinary-things-happening-right-now/">40 Extraordinary Things Happening Right Now</a>”, from a site called “Marc and Angel Hack Life: Practical Tips for Productive Living”.  It’s a useful site for anyone trying to be more positive. Here are the first 10 “Extraordinary Things”:</p>
<p><span id="more-1084"></span></p>
<ol start="1">
<li>A soldier of sorts is diligently fighting the fight so you don’t have to.</li>
<li>Someone who suffered from a severe injury last year is back on their feet.</li>
<li>A small group of people are building something that will soon make the impossible possible.</li>
<li>Somewhere on Earth a double rainbow is stretched from one end of the horizon to the other.</li>
<li>One of the next Billboard-chart-topping musical artists is patiently rehearsing in her garage.</li>
<li>A piece of literature is being written that will eventually change your perspective on life.</li>
<li>Young children all over the world are singing and dancing before they even realize there is anything that isn’t music.</li>
<li>A friend is helping a friend rise above thoughts of suicide.</li>
<li>Someone is thinking what you’re thinking, but hasn’t said anything yet either.</li>
<li>Two people in your hometown are falling in love.</li>
</ol>
<p>Actually, you could make up your own list, and that would be a very good way for you to attend to currently missed positives in your own life.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2012%2F07%2F18%2F1084%2F&amp;linkname=" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Another Path to More Positivity.</title>
		<link>/2012/07/01/another-path-to-more-positivity/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2012 23:36:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Physical Contact]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1062</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Our last post showed how to increase the positives in your life by learning to notice them when they are right at hand. We all have many things to be grateful for, so it should be easy to practice gratitude &#8230; <a href="/2012/07/01/another-path-to-more-positivity/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="/2012/06/20/increasing-your-positives/">Our last post</a> showed how to increase the positives in your life by learning to notice them when they are right at hand. We all have many things to be grateful for, so it should be easy to practice gratitude and thus retrain our brains to notice and appreciate these things.</p>
<p>In today’s post we will describe a second, easy way to increase positives. It involves getting benefit from people, things, and activities that are available in your ordinary life. It can be a pet that is always happy to see you and shows it, or that loves cuddling with you. Anything that draws you away from the stresses of life, gives you pleasure, makes you laugh, etc. is a potential source of positivity.</p>
<p>In a <a href="/2010/11/04/natural-stress-defeaters/">previous post</a> we summarized a list that Debbie and I have gathered over many years, of things ordinary people do to deal with stress. As it happens, almost all of those also increase your positivity.</p>
<p>Let’s take a closer look at that list of de-stressors and learn some tricks that can help us make use of them.</p>
<p><span id="more-1062"></span></p>
<p>Contact Comfort.</p>
<p>“Curling up on the sofa with a cup of tea and my black cat” and “Having a small, neurotic dog whose only wish is to curl up next to you” are good examples involving pets. Research shows that petting a dog, cat, or even a horse, lowers the animal’s heart rate and blood pressure while also lowering ours.</p>
<p>“Cuddling with my fiancé”, “Getting a massage”, “Asking for and accepting nurturing” are also in this category.</p>
<p>Pleasant, Engrossing Distraction.</p>
<p>“Shopping for something you like”, “Watching comedies” and “Getting out into nature” are examples in this category.</p>
<p>Soothing Sensory Stimulation.</p>
<p>“Listening to music”, “Taking a hot bath or shower”, are good examples.</p>
<p>Of course, you can, and should come up with your own preferred ways to get contact comfort, pleasant, engrossing distraction or soothing sensory stimulation.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, just picking what works for us is not enough. We may just not get around to actually making use of them. We have to come up with what Shawn Achor calls “Activation Energy” to turn our knowledge into action. Activation Energy is the energy it takes to trigger an action.</p>
<p>Achor himself decided to learn how to play the guitar, then failed to follow up on the decision.Then he examined the barriers that kept him from fulfilling his decision. He had the guitar in a closet, and that made it easier to forget about the practice than to carry it out.</p>
<p>So he put the guitar in plain sight. Obviously, this greatly reduced the amount activation energy needed to cue him to practice.</p>
<p>This worked. He practiced regularly.</p>
<p>In this interview, he gives several more examples of how to get activation energy to work for you.</p>
<p><object style="height: 390px; width: 640px;" width="640" height="360" classid="clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000" codebase="http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0"><param name="allowFullScreen" value="true" /><param name="allowScriptAccess" value="always" /><param name="src" value="http://www.youtube.com/v/8IdR76uegDg?version=3&amp;feature=player_detailpage" /><param name="allowfullscreen" value="true" /><param name="allowscriptaccess" value="always" /><embed style="height: 390px; width: 640px;" width="640" height="360" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" src="http://www.youtube.com/v/8IdR76uegDg?version=3&amp;feature=player_detailpage" allowFullScreen="true" allowScriptAccess="always" allowfullscreen="true" allowscriptaccess="always" /></object></p>
<p>So be sure to arrange things to make it easy for you to use contact comfort, pleasant engrossing distraction, and soothing sensory experiences to your advantage. Ask what comes between you and utilizing the pleasant techniques? How can you work around the obstacles?</p>
<p>Once you figure those things out, you can readily increase your ratio of positives to negatives.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2012%2F07%2F01%2Fanother-path-to-more-positivity%2F&amp;linkname=Another%20Path%20to%20More%20Positivity." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>When Life Becomes a Tsunami of Stress</title>
		<link>/2012/03/14/when-life-becomes-a-tsunami-of-stress/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2012 15:00:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Benefits of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Effective Communication]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Expressing Feelings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Physical Contact]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=971</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[One test of the usefulness of our program and techniques is whether we really practice what we preach. We are not perfect models of what we believe in, nor are we people of super-resilience. I think in an earlier post &#8230; <a href="/2012/03/14/when-life-becomes-a-tsunami-of-stress/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One test of the usefulness of our program and techniques is whether we really practice what we preach. We are not perfect models of what we believe in, nor are we people of super-resilience. I think in an earlier post I acknowledged that my life was far from handing me a cornucopia of resilience skills, and I think I am safe in saying that would also be true for Debbie.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, there were things in our early experiences that helped us develop a fighting spirit and a sense that we can improve by learning what we need to do and doggedly putting what we learned into practice.</p>
<p>For some months we have been dealing with extremely stressful situations. I cannot be explicit about them because that would violate the privacy of others, including others that we care deeply about. I think it’s okay if I say that it involves the approaching death of someone who has been important part of our lives. This is aggravated by dementia of a beloved member of our family, and intense pressure put on even the tiniest of fractures between members of the extended family.</p>
<p>So what has helped us to deal with these things?</p>
<p><span id="more-971"></span></p>
<p>We have both increased our use of deep relaxation. We listen to one of the short audio recordings we designed ourselves, narrated by Debbie. These take only 10-20 minutes.</p>
<p>Even fitting this into our pressured schedules can be hard, but it is well worth the effort. These sessions take us to a level of relaxation that drastically reduces our stress responses.</p>
<p>In spite of there being a lot of interference with sticking to exercise regimens, we both have continued to exercise. Exercise reduces stress reactions in many ways; it reduces stress enhancing bodily chemicals and increases natural bodily chemicals that calm and sooth us.</p>
<p>One of our ways of exercising is to hike in wooded areas which we are fortunate to have tucked away even in our metropolitan area. We usually take our dog, Luke, and his intense enjoyment of being off leash in a place full of surprises and fascinating odors, helps us to experience the joys of being in nature.</p>
<p>Speaking of our dog, he shows clear signs of feeling our distressing experiences very deeply. Dogs, and many other animals, are geniuses at sensing distress in members of their “pack”. So we decided to have what (I blush to admit this) we have dubbed “lovey-dovey time”, just before bed time. He quickly learned that when we say “It’s lovey-dovey time”, both of us are going to lie down beside him and massage and pet him for a while. He, who is normally a very rough and tumble dog, becomes soft and gentle during those sessions.</p>
<p>Research shows that when you pet an animal, the animal’s heart rate and blood pressure go down, and so does yours. Debbie and I both have marveled at how much better we feel during and after these sessions. We had read about it in research studies, but experiencing it is something else.</p>
<p>Debbie and I have an understanding that we’ve got each other’s backs, and that is a core purpose in our lives.</p>
<p>In our last post, we discussed the positive impact of emotional support at home. We have extended that beyond home.</p>
<ul>
<li>Every night we go through a debriefing between the two of us, thus augmenting each other’s individual perspective.</li>
<li>We have extended this theme of support to the extended family by planning coping strategies as a group, with everyone’s viewpoint getting a hearing.</li>
<li>We have steadily worked to create a store of past experiences of support and trust throughout the extended family, so we can speak more frankly with each other than would otherwise be possible.</li>
<li>Whenever possible we have been cooperative with family members who might have reason to oppose us.</li>
</ul>
<p>We still have to take hits; our phone rings over and over again, often making it impossible to relax at night. That is one of the costs incurred by being positive and constructive with all of the people who have a stake in this. Because we have developed our means of individual support and support of each other, we can afford these intrusions, even though they add to our stress load.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2012%2F03%2F14%2F971%2F&amp;linkname=When%20Life%20Becomes%20a%20Tsunami%20of%20Stress" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Depressed, Anxious, Being Hard on Yourself? New Insights about the Value of Learning to Be both Self-Compassionate and Self-Soothing.</title>
		<link>/2012/02/16/depressed-anxious-being-hard-on-yourself-new-insights-about-the-value-of-learning-to-be-both-self-compassionate-and-self-soothing/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2012 04:10:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Self-Criticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mindfulness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Physical Contact]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Compassion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=956</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Most of us are aware that we have an inner critic that can make it hard to enjoy life, and, in the more severe instances, induce such things as anxiety and depression. We have written several posts about the inner &#8230; <a href="/2012/02/16/depressed-anxious-being-hard-on-yourself-new-insights-about-the-value-of-learning-to-be-both-self-compassionate-and-self-soothing/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Most of us are aware that we have an inner critic that can make it hard to enjoy life, and, in the more severe instances, induce such things as anxiety and depression.</p>
<p>We have written several posts about the inner critic and how to deal with it through changing your inner self-talk.</p>
<p>We have also encouraged the use of <em>mindfulness meditation. </em>With mindfulness we observe the flow of our experiences with compassion and acceptance, the opposite of self-criticism.</p>
<p>This post is about an important new insight into what it may take to stop unhelpful self-criticism. It involves learning to be compassionate toward the inner critic, which is, after all, an aspect of ourselves. This means to understand that the self-criticism is something you learned in order to adapt to the environment in which you grew up.</p>
<p>In addition we must also learn ways to sooth ourselves.</p>
<p><span id="more-956"></span></p>
<p>According to British psychologist, <a href="http://www.compassionatemind.co.uk/resources/Compassion_Group_Therapy_Paper.pdf">Paul Gilbert</a>, besides reducing the critical self-talk, we need to shift from feelings of “self-directed hostility, contempt, and self-loathing” to   “feelings of self-reassurance, warmth, and self-soothing”.</p>
<p>“Some high self-critics could understand the logic of CBT and generate alternative thoughts to self-criticism but rarely felt reassured by such efforts”.  (CBT is cognitive behavior therapy; a self-help version can be found <a href="../../../../../2011/02/20/to-increase-your-resilience-avoid-being-too-hard-on-yourself/">here</a>.)</p>
<p>In his view, besides changing our self-talk, many of us need to learn ways to sooth ourselves, and thus to experience the warm feelings that accompany self-compassion and self-soothing.</p>
<p>But how do we do that?  Check out our post on “<a href="../../../../../2010/11/04/natural-stress-defeaters/">Natural Stress Defeaters</a>” for some simple methods of self-soothing that have worked for others, and that you can easily bring into your own life. Also <a href="../../../../../2010/12/06/a-key-step-in-resilience-training-is-learning-deep-relaxation/">deep relaxation</a> produces feelings of relaxation and warmth, and it, too, is easy to fit into your life. The previous link has a free audio that is designed to help you to feel warmer and more at peace.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.compassionatemind.co.uk/8.html">Dr. Gilbert</a> provides many mental exercises crafted to induce the desired feelings of warmth and peacefulness. They can be found in his book “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Compassionate-Mind-Approach-Lifes-Challenges/dp/1572248408/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1329364432&amp;sr=1-1">The Compassionate Mind</a>”.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2012%2F02%2F16%2Fdepressed-anxious-being-hard-on-yourself-new-insights-about-the-value-of-learning-to-be-both-self-compassionate-and-self-soothing%2F&amp;linkname=Depressed%2C%20Anxious%2C%20Being%20Hard%20on%20Yourself%3F%20New%20Insights%20about%20the%20Value%20of%20Learning%20to%20Be%20both%20Self-Compassionate%20and%20Self-Soothing." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
