<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Physical Contact &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/physical-contact/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Another Path to More Positivity.</title>
		<link>/2012/07/01/another-path-to-more-positivity/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2012 23:36:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Physical Contact]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Positivity/Negativity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1062</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Our last post showed how to increase the positives in your life by learning to notice them when they are right at hand. We all have many things to be grateful for, so it should be easy to practice gratitude &#8230; <a href="/2012/07/01/another-path-to-more-positivity/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="/2012/06/20/increasing-your-positives/">Our last post</a> showed how to increase the positives in your life by learning to notice them when they are right at hand. We all have many things to be grateful for, so it should be easy to practice gratitude and thus retrain our brains to notice and appreciate these things.</p>
<p>In today’s post we will describe a second, easy way to increase positives. It involves getting benefit from people, things, and activities that are available in your ordinary life. It can be a pet that is always happy to see you and shows it, or that loves cuddling with you. Anything that draws you away from the stresses of life, gives you pleasure, makes you laugh, etc. is a potential source of positivity.</p>
<p>In a <a href="/2010/11/04/natural-stress-defeaters/">previous post</a> we summarized a list that Debbie and I have gathered over many years, of things ordinary people do to deal with stress. As it happens, almost all of those also increase your positivity.</p>
<p>Let’s take a closer look at that list of de-stressors and learn some tricks that can help us make use of them.</p>
<p><span id="more-1062"></span></p>
<p>Contact Comfort.</p>
<p>“Curling up on the sofa with a cup of tea and my black cat” and “Having a small, neurotic dog whose only wish is to curl up next to you” are good examples involving pets. Research shows that petting a dog, cat, or even a horse, lowers the animal’s heart rate and blood pressure while also lowering ours.</p>
<p>“Cuddling with my fiancé”, “Getting a massage”, “Asking for and accepting nurturing” are also in this category.</p>
<p>Pleasant, Engrossing Distraction.</p>
<p>“Shopping for something you like”, “Watching comedies” and “Getting out into nature” are examples in this category.</p>
<p>Soothing Sensory Stimulation.</p>
<p>“Listening to music”, “Taking a hot bath or shower”, are good examples.</p>
<p>Of course, you can, and should come up with your own preferred ways to get contact comfort, pleasant, engrossing distraction or soothing sensory stimulation.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, just picking what works for us is not enough. We may just not get around to actually making use of them. We have to come up with what Shawn Achor calls “Activation Energy” to turn our knowledge into action. Activation Energy is the energy it takes to trigger an action.</p>
<p>Achor himself decided to learn how to play the guitar, then failed to follow up on the decision.Then he examined the barriers that kept him from fulfilling his decision. He had the guitar in a closet, and that made it easier to forget about the practice than to carry it out.</p>
<p>So he put the guitar in plain sight. Obviously, this greatly reduced the amount activation energy needed to cue him to practice.</p>
<p>This worked. He practiced regularly.</p>
<p>In this interview, he gives several more examples of how to get activation energy to work for you.</p>
<p><object style="height: 390px; width: 640px;" width="640" height="360" classid="clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000" codebase="http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0"><param name="allowFullScreen" value="true" /><param name="allowScriptAccess" value="always" /><param name="src" value="http://www.youtube.com/v/8IdR76uegDg?version=3&amp;feature=player_detailpage" /><param name="allowfullscreen" value="true" /><param name="allowscriptaccess" value="always" /><embed style="height: 390px; width: 640px;" width="640" height="360" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" src="http://www.youtube.com/v/8IdR76uegDg?version=3&amp;feature=player_detailpage" allowFullScreen="true" allowScriptAccess="always" allowfullscreen="true" allowscriptaccess="always" /></object></p>
<p>So be sure to arrange things to make it easy for you to use contact comfort, pleasant engrossing distraction, and soothing sensory experiences to your advantage. Ask what comes between you and utilizing the pleasant techniques? How can you work around the obstacles?</p>
<p>Once you figure those things out, you can readily increase your ratio of positives to negatives.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2012%2F07%2F01%2Fanother-path-to-more-positivity%2F&amp;linkname=Another%20Path%20to%20More%20Positivity." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>When Life Becomes a Tsunami of Stress</title>
		<link>/2012/03/14/when-life-becomes-a-tsunami-of-stress/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2012 15:00:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Benefits of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Effective Communication]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Expressing Feelings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Physical Contact]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=971</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[One test of the usefulness of our program and techniques is whether we really practice what we preach. We are not perfect models of what we believe in, nor are we people of super-resilience. I think in an earlier post &#8230; <a href="/2012/03/14/when-life-becomes-a-tsunami-of-stress/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One test of the usefulness of our program and techniques is whether we really practice what we preach. We are not perfect models of what we believe in, nor are we people of super-resilience. I think in an earlier post I acknowledged that my life was far from handing me a cornucopia of resilience skills, and I think I am safe in saying that would also be true for Debbie.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, there were things in our early experiences that helped us develop a fighting spirit and a sense that we can improve by learning what we need to do and doggedly putting what we learned into practice.</p>
<p>For some months we have been dealing with extremely stressful situations. I cannot be explicit about them because that would violate the privacy of others, including others that we care deeply about. I think it’s okay if I say that it involves the approaching death of someone who has been important part of our lives. This is aggravated by dementia of a beloved member of our family, and intense pressure put on even the tiniest of fractures between members of the extended family.</p>
<p>So what has helped us to deal with these things?</p>
<p><span id="more-971"></span></p>
<p>We have both increased our use of deep relaxation. We listen to one of the short audio recordings we designed ourselves, narrated by Debbie. These take only 10-20 minutes.</p>
<p>Even fitting this into our pressured schedules can be hard, but it is well worth the effort. These sessions take us to a level of relaxation that drastically reduces our stress responses.</p>
<p>In spite of there being a lot of interference with sticking to exercise regimens, we both have continued to exercise. Exercise reduces stress reactions in many ways; it reduces stress enhancing bodily chemicals and increases natural bodily chemicals that calm and sooth us.</p>
<p>One of our ways of exercising is to hike in wooded areas which we are fortunate to have tucked away even in our metropolitan area. We usually take our dog, Luke, and his intense enjoyment of being off leash in a place full of surprises and fascinating odors, helps us to experience the joys of being in nature.</p>
<p>Speaking of our dog, he shows clear signs of feeling our distressing experiences very deeply. Dogs, and many other animals, are geniuses at sensing distress in members of their “pack”. So we decided to have what (I blush to admit this) we have dubbed “lovey-dovey time”, just before bed time. He quickly learned that when we say “It’s lovey-dovey time”, both of us are going to lie down beside him and massage and pet him for a while. He, who is normally a very rough and tumble dog, becomes soft and gentle during those sessions.</p>
<p>Research shows that when you pet an animal, the animal’s heart rate and blood pressure go down, and so does yours. Debbie and I both have marveled at how much better we feel during and after these sessions. We had read about it in research studies, but experiencing it is something else.</p>
<p>Debbie and I have an understanding that we’ve got each other’s backs, and that is a core purpose in our lives.</p>
<p>In our last post, we discussed the positive impact of emotional support at home. We have extended that beyond home.</p>
<ul>
<li>Every night we go through a debriefing between the two of us, thus augmenting each other’s individual perspective.</li>
<li>We have extended this theme of support to the extended family by planning coping strategies as a group, with everyone’s viewpoint getting a hearing.</li>
<li>We have steadily worked to create a store of past experiences of support and trust throughout the extended family, so we can speak more frankly with each other than would otherwise be possible.</li>
<li>Whenever possible we have been cooperative with family members who might have reason to oppose us.</li>
</ul>
<p>We still have to take hits; our phone rings over and over again, often making it impossible to relax at night. That is one of the costs incurred by being positive and constructive with all of the people who have a stake in this. Because we have developed our means of individual support and support of each other, we can afford these intrusions, even though they add to our stress load.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2012%2F03%2F14%2F971%2F&amp;linkname=When%20Life%20Becomes%20a%20Tsunami%20of%20Stress" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Depressed, Anxious, Being Hard on Yourself? New Insights about the Value of Learning to Be both Self-Compassionate and Self-Soothing.</title>
		<link>/2012/02/16/depressed-anxious-being-hard-on-yourself-new-insights-about-the-value-of-learning-to-be-both-self-compassionate-and-self-soothing/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2012 04:10:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Self-Criticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mindfulness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Physical Contact]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Compassion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=956</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Most of us are aware that we have an inner critic that can make it hard to enjoy life, and, in the more severe instances, induce such things as anxiety and depression. We have written several posts about the inner &#8230; <a href="/2012/02/16/depressed-anxious-being-hard-on-yourself-new-insights-about-the-value-of-learning-to-be-both-self-compassionate-and-self-soothing/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Most of us are aware that we have an inner critic that can make it hard to enjoy life, and, in the more severe instances, induce such things as anxiety and depression.</p>
<p>We have written several posts about the inner critic and how to deal with it through changing your inner self-talk.</p>
<p>We have also encouraged the use of <em>mindfulness meditation. </em>With mindfulness we observe the flow of our experiences with compassion and acceptance, the opposite of self-criticism.</p>
<p>This post is about an important new insight into what it may take to stop unhelpful self-criticism. It involves learning to be compassionate toward the inner critic, which is, after all, an aspect of ourselves. This means to understand that the self-criticism is something you learned in order to adapt to the environment in which you grew up.</p>
<p>In addition we must also learn ways to sooth ourselves.</p>
<p><span id="more-956"></span></p>
<p>According to British psychologist, <a href="http://www.compassionatemind.co.uk/resources/Compassion_Group_Therapy_Paper.pdf">Paul Gilbert</a>, besides reducing the critical self-talk, we need to shift from feelings of “self-directed hostility, contempt, and self-loathing” to   “feelings of self-reassurance, warmth, and self-soothing”.</p>
<p>“Some high self-critics could understand the logic of CBT and generate alternative thoughts to self-criticism but rarely felt reassured by such efforts”.  (CBT is cognitive behavior therapy; a self-help version can be found <a href="../../../../../2011/02/20/to-increase-your-resilience-avoid-being-too-hard-on-yourself/">here</a>.)</p>
<p>In his view, besides changing our self-talk, many of us need to learn ways to sooth ourselves, and thus to experience the warm feelings that accompany self-compassion and self-soothing.</p>
<p>But how do we do that?  Check out our post on “<a href="../../../../../2010/11/04/natural-stress-defeaters/">Natural Stress Defeaters</a>” for some simple methods of self-soothing that have worked for others, and that you can easily bring into your own life. Also <a href="../../../../../2010/12/06/a-key-step-in-resilience-training-is-learning-deep-relaxation/">deep relaxation</a> produces feelings of relaxation and warmth, and it, too, is easy to fit into your life. The previous link has a free audio that is designed to help you to feel warmer and more at peace.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.compassionatemind.co.uk/8.html">Dr. Gilbert</a> provides many mental exercises crafted to induce the desired feelings of warmth and peacefulness. They can be found in his book “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Compassionate-Mind-Approach-Lifes-Challenges/dp/1572248408/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1329364432&amp;sr=1-1">The Compassionate Mind</a>”.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2012%2F02%2F16%2Fdepressed-anxious-being-hard-on-yourself-new-insights-about-the-value-of-learning-to-be-both-self-compassionate-and-self-soothing%2F&amp;linkname=Depressed%2C%20Anxious%2C%20Being%20Hard%20on%20Yourself%3F%20New%20Insights%20about%20the%20Value%20of%20Learning%20to%20Be%20both%20Self-Compassionate%20and%20Self-Soothing." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Touch Enhances Health and Well-Being</title>
		<link>/2010/11/04/touch-enhances-health-and-well-being-2/</link>
		<comments>/2010/11/04/touch-enhances-health-and-well-being-2/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2010 03:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Physical Contact]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=391</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[…a pediatrician named Henry Bakwin took charge of the pediatric ward at Bellevue hospital. When Bakwin took command of the ward, there was a sign on its door saying that no one was to enter unless they had scrubbed twice. &#8230; <a href="/2010/11/04/touch-enhances-health-and-well-being-2/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>…a pediatrician named Henry Bakwin took charge of the pediatric ward at Bellevue hospital. When Bakwin took command of the ward, there was a sign on its door saying that no one was to enter unless they had scrubbed twice. Bakwin had that sign removed and replaced with one that said “Do not enter this nursery without picking up a baby.” Nurses were instructed to hold the babies on their laps and cuddle them periodically. Despite the greater likelihood of contact with germs, infection rates dropped! Apparently physical contact trumped sterilization.</em></p>
<p><em>“…when people seek out contact comfort when stressed, they are following a path that is probably deeply engrained in our brains. There is much more to be said about the benefits of contact comfort, but I want to save that for later. Next it is time for something completely different.”</em></p>
<p>****************************************</p>
<p>A story in James Lynch’s book <span style="text-decoration: underline;">The Broken Heart</span> has stuck in my mind for several decades. Lynch was studying the heart’s response to human contact in hospital coronary care and trauma units. This was an extensive study, involving many patients, but the example that stayed with me was the story of a 54-year old man who died after 14 days in intensive care.</p>
<p>This man had a history of anxiety attacks and alcoholism. No one came to visit him during his 14 days in the hospital. Toward the end, he was comatose. A machine did his breathing for him. His heartbeat lacked the rhythm found in normal hearts, so it could no longer adequately carry out its task of pumping the blood needed by other organs.</p>
<p>As Lynch observed his chaotic heartbeat on a screen, a nurse came in and took the man’s hand. His heartbeat immediately became dramatically slower and more regular as she comforted him. When she released his hand and went on to other duties, the irregularities quickly returned. Simple physical touch had worked wonders for his dying heart.</p>
<p>This calming of the heart in response to touch was observed by Lynch in patient after patient. In this particular case the person doing the touching was an unfamiliar human being. Other evidence gathered by Lynch and many others showed that it probably would have had an even greater impact if a pet, especially a familiar one, had been touching him. In general, there is evidence that when humans pet animals, heart rate and blood pressure go down in both of them.</p>
<p>Another set of findings reveals even more about the power of contact on our health. In the early 1900’s death rates for hospitalized babies were remarkably high. A report that came out in 1915 indicated that infants admitted to 10 American asylums (a term used then for foundling homes and orphanages) had death rates from 31.5 to 75 percent.</p>
<p>The response to this was to institute elaborate procedures for keeping the wards as sterile as possible. Staff wore meticulously sterilized white gowns and gloves. Picking the babies up was viewed as increasing the risk of infection. To avoid contamination, in some institutions babies were fed with propped up bottles and had to eat without being held.</p>
<p>In this context a pediatrician named Henry Bakwin took charge of the pediatric ward at Bellevue hospital. When Bakwin took command of the ward, there was a sign on its door saying that no one was to enter unless they had scrubbed twice. Bakwin had that sign removed and replaced with one that said “Do not enter this nursery without picking up a baby.” Nurses were instructed to hold the babies on their laps and cuddle them periodically. Despite the greater likelihood of contact with germs, <em>infection rates dropped!</em> Apparently physical contact trumped sterilization.<br />
<span id="more-391"></span></p>
<p>The work of psychologist Harry Harlow strengthened evidence of the importance of contact. Harlow ran a primate laboratory at the University of Wisconsin’s Department of Psychology. He needed monkeys for his research, but they were difficult and expensive to obtain. Furthermore, they commonly arrived in a diseased condition. Many of them died.</p>
<p>Harlow decided to find out how to breed his own monkeys. Out of concern about diseases, Harlow attempted to raise newborn monkeys in a sterilized environment that inadvertently came very close to repeating the failed methods of children’s asylums. The animals were raised by humans with meticulous care, including excellent diets. Monkeys raised in this way appeared to be deranged. For them every new thing they encountered was a major catastrophe. They curled their bodies in a fetal position and rocked, often compulsively sucking parts of their bodies. When the time came for them to breed, they could not cope with the potential mate, seemingly overwhelmed by its presence.</p>
<p>Eventually Harlow and his colleagues conducted the now famous (or, for many, infamous) experiments in which baby monkeys were raised in the presence of a soft, cuddly artificial “mother” who provided no food, and a cold, wire “mother” with a baby bottle attached to it. Most psychologists those days would have predicted with certainty that the monkeys would attach to the wire mother that was a source of food. To the contrary, they clung to the cloth mother and only moved to the wire one for brief feeding sessions. I have seen a picture of one of these monkeys clinging to the soft mother while stretching over to get milk from the wire mother.</p>
<p>Monkeys raised with any kind of artificial mothers appeared to be very abnormal, but those raised without a soft, cuddly artificial mother behaved in bizarrely abnormal ways. In later work, monkeys raised without a mother but with another baby monkey as cage-mate clung to each other so intensely that, when allowed to leave the cage, they would not let go of each other and rolled out of the cage in a two-monkey ball.</p>
<p>So when people seek out contact comfort when stressed, they are following a path that is probably deeply engrained in our brains. There is much more to be said about the benefits of contact comfort, but I want to save that for later. Next it is time for something completely different.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2010/11/04/touch-enhances-health-and-well-being-2/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
