<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Cognitive Reappraisal &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/cognitive-reappraisal/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Reconsidering Your Initial View of Stressful Situations Can Help You Respond with Greater Resilience.</title>
		<link>/2014/11/20/reconsidering-your-initial-view-of-stressful-situations-can-help-you-respond-with-greater-resilience/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2014 05:17:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cognitive Reappraisal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1773</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Inevitably life confronts us with situations that are hard to handle. Sometimes our ability to handle them falls far short, and we are forced to go through a period in which we struggle and take some painful hits. If we &#8230; <a href="/2014/11/20/reconsidering-your-initial-view-of-stressful-situations-can-help-you-respond-with-greater-resilience/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Inevitably life confronts us with situations that are hard to handle. Sometimes our ability to handle them falls far short, and we are forced to go through a period in which we struggle and take some painful hits.</p>
<p>If we manage to get through such situations “in one piece”, we can be strengthened instead of being defeated.  When that happens, we have increased our resilience.</p>
<p>There are many different ways to come out on top of our struggles, or at least to keep them from utterly defeating us. If you take a quick trip through our 100+ posts in this blog, you will almost certainly find some that you can use as tools for getting through experiences you may encounter in the future.</p>
<p>A tool that has been occupying our attention lately is “Cognitive Reappraisal”.  It will be the central focus of this post.</p>
<p>What is cognitive reappraisal? It is a way to regulate our emotions. It calls on us to focus on finding alternative interpretations of what we are going through. This includes appraisals of the events that trigger our emotional reaction, the bodily responses that have been triggered, and of any other aspect of the total experience.</p>
<p><span id="more-1773"></span></p>
<p>To reappraise, we look for interpretations that shift us toward a more positive experience. For example, when having an experience that could be viewed as threatening we may have a hard time viewing it any other way. With reappraisal, we search for interpretations that help us see our situation as a challenge rather than a threat, and may even shift us from fear and hopelessness to excitement.</p>
<p>Cognitive reappraisal really works. Here are a few examples of its outcomes:</p>
<ul>
<li>It improves performance on difficult tasks, e.g. <a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022103109002200">taking high stakes tests</a> that can determine access to a good career.</li>
<li>It can enable you to <a href="http://www.wjh.harvard.edu/~nock/nocklab/Jamieson-2013.pdf">use the energy and power of your physiological responses to stress</a> into positive ones that are linked to excitement rather than fear or rage.</li>
<li>It can increase your <a href="http://rmkaplan.bol.ucla.edu/Robert_M._Kaplan/1983_publications_files/0071.pdf">ability to endure painful situations</a>, e.g. a painful medical procedure.</li>
</ul>
<p>Notice that these examples cover a wide range of situations.  We have no reason to think that reappraisal applies only to a few specific circumstances.</p>
<h3><strong>What, Specifically Do We Reappraise?</strong></h3>
<p>We can reappraise our interpretation of the stressful <strong><em>event</em></strong>.</p>
<p>This involves looking for appraisals that are more encouraging, helpful, and supportive.</p>
<p>How do you find these new interpretations?</p>
<ol>
<li>Simply consider alternative interpretations of what has happened. Try to come up with a list of several alternative ones.</li>
</ol>
<p>Often we are very convinced that our first interpretation is the one and only realistic one. There is good evidence human judgments are often wrong. Our minds are subject to many cognitive biases. Furthermore, being certain about our judgments has little to do with how accurate they are.</p>
<p>This is worth a try: Imagine someone with a different personality who tends to be more positive than you and think about how that person might interpret what happened.</p>
<ol>
<li>Realize that you can “contain” your reactions to stress.</li>
</ol>
<p>Being in a stressful, scary situation need not mean that the only option you have is to escape from that situation. Many stage performers get intensely anxious before doing a performance. Some, even some of the greatest performers, vomit from the anxiety. Yet they step right out on the stage and wow the audience.</p>
<p>You can have intense feelings and urges to flee, then breathe deeply and do what the situation requires by allowing the feelings to be there, and observing them, but not letting them to take over control of what you do.</p>
<ol>
<li>You can reappraise the meaning of your physiological reactions to the stressful situation.</li>
</ol>
<p>e.g. The “fight or flight” response is <strong><em>adaptive.</em></strong> This means it can <strong><em>help you</em></strong> function well in difficult situations by sending the right chemicals to your organs that help your body perform at its highest levels. What you experience while under stress is an amalgam of the body’s reactions and the interpretations you add to them.</p>
<p><strong><em>Mastering the art of interpretation is the key to turning negative responses to stress into positive ones.</em></strong></p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=&amp;linkname=Reconsidering%20Your%20Initial%20View%20of%20Stressful%20Situations%20Can%20Help%20You%20Respond%20with%20Greater%20Resilience." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Build Your “Toughness” and Become More Resilient</title>
		<link>/2014/10/08/build-your-toughness-and-become-more-resilient/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2014 23:28:15 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Cognitive Reappraisal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Exercise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Toughness]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1758</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In the late 1980s, a Professor from the University of Nebraska published an important article on something he called “toughness”. He pointed out that the prevalent belief of experts was that the “arousal” that is stimulated by stress is just &#8230; <a href="/2014/10/08/build-your-toughness-and-become-more-resilient/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the late 1980s, a Professor from the University of Nebraska published an <a href="http://digitalcommons.unl.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1215&amp;context=psychfacpub&amp;sei-redir=1&amp;referer=http%3A%2F%2Fscholar.google.com%2Fscholar%3Fhl%3Den%26q%3Ddienstbier%2Btoughness%26btnG%3D%26as_sdt%3D1%252C26%26as_sdtp%3D#search=%22dienstbier%20toughness%22">important article</a> on something he called “toughness”. He pointed out that the prevalent belief of experts was that the “arousal” that is stimulated by stress is just plain BAD. (This word “arousal” in ordinary parlance usually refers to sex, but here it means having the brain highly activated and the body prepared for action, the kind of action that enables you to confront a threat and either escape or defeat it).</p>
<p>The Professor, Richard Dienstbier, summarized a wide range of research showing that this arousal could damage you, but could also toughen you. In some cases it can even be exhilarating and good for your health.</p>
<p>This is where the technical sense of “arousal” and the sexual sense of it converge. During sex the body responds in many of the same ways it responds to threats, for example, with fast and strong heartbeats and elevated blood pressure. It also recovers quickly and fully.</p>
<p>Quick and full recovery are at the heart of toughness and resilience.</p>
<p>If you do not recover, and have high arousal over long periods with few times at rest, THAT is damaging.</p>
<p>So if you are a person who suffers from constant distress, what can you do? Here are a few examples.</p>
<ol>
<li>Develop the Knowledge and Skills that Enable You to Recover promptly from Stress for example, learn how to <a href="/2010/12/06/a-key-step-in-resilience-training-is-learning-deep-relaxation/">relax <em>deeply</em></a><em>.</em></li>
<li>Practice some form of <a href="/2014/01/15/a-simple-way-to-sooth-and-comfort-yourself/">meditation</a>.</li>
<li>Exercise regularly, and include aerobic exercise such as brisk walking, jogging, or cycling.</li>
</ol>
<p>Just click the links and you will find instructions how to do each of the listed techniques.</p>
<p>Further Possibilities: Exposure Training</p>
<p>Dienstbier’s work focused attention on the key role of recovery from stress, but that is not all it did. It also led us to see <em>how valuable exposure to stressors could be</em>. Being exposed to stress from which you can recover promptly will make you physiologically tougher.</p>
<p>This is exactly what we do when we engage in regular exercise that is moderate.</p>
<p>We can do the same sort of thing with just about any kind of stressor. For example, most people find public speaking very stressful, and many of them join <a href="http://www.toastmasters.org/">Toastmasters</a>, where they regularly give speeches to groups of people who are also working to develop their public speaking skills.</p>
<p>Cognitive Reappraisal</p>
<p>Two things interact to produce stress reactions. First is the event itself, and second is our interpretation of the event. The interpretation can be at least as important as the event. Dienstbier makes use of a well-known model of stress reactions (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a8FEMHCRowM">Lazarus and Folkman</a>). Their view is that we make two appraisals, a ”primary appraisal” and a “secondary appraisal.&#8221; Primary is an appraisal of the level of threat the stressor presents. Secondary is an appraisal of the resources you have to cope with the stressor.</p>
<p>If you judge that a stressor is beyond what you can manage, you are facing a <strong>threat</strong>. If you judge that you can handle the stressor, you are dealing with a <strong>challenge</strong>. And challenges can be opportunities to toughen yourself, and maybe even have fun.</p>
<p>Appraisals need not be set in concrete. They are, after all, in our minds. A good deal of research has been focused on teaching people to <strong>reappraise</strong> life events, and it turns out that these reappraisals can really improve performance.</p>
<p>To clarify the concept of reappraisal, imagine a student who does poorly on an important exam. The student interprets this failing as evidence that s/he is “stupid” and “hopeless”.</p>
<p>Now suppose the student is guided to consider that the failure was due to lack of skills of note taking, studying, and/or test taking. The new appraisal implies that there are things s/he can do to perform better the next time. Now a threat has been changed to a challenge.  And dealing with it can make the student tougher.</p>
<p>Cognitive reappraisal has a wide range of applications. Good research has shown that is helpful in dealing with PTSD, fighting food temptations, reducing negative feelings, and reducing anxiety. And this is very far from a complete list.</p>
<p>We will be saying more about cognitive reappraisal in future posts.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2014%2F10%2F08%2Fbuild-your-toughness-become-more-resilient%2F&amp;linkname=Build%20Your%20%E2%80%9CToughness%E2%80%9D%20Become%20More%20Resilient" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
