<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Women&#8217;s Resilience &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/womens-resilience/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Sleeplessness: Should You Medicate of Meditate?</title>
		<link>/2011/11/15/sleeplessness-should-you-medicate-of-meditate/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2011 16:28:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Perfectionism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Self-Criticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mindfulness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Understanding]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Women's Resilience]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=858</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I think it is safe to say that a large majority of us gravely underestimate the powers of our minds and overestimate the powers of medicine. Whether your problem is sleeplessness, pain or some other potentially overwhelming challenge, your mind, &#8230; <a href="/2011/11/15/sleeplessness-should-you-medicate-of-meditate/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think it is safe to say that a large majority of us gravely underestimate the powers of our minds and overestimate the powers of medicine. Whether your problem is sleeplessness, pain or some other potentially overwhelming challenge, your mind, especially if you train and develop its powers, can work wonders in corralling and controlling your problem.</p>
<p>Fortunately the title of this post implies a false dichotomy. Why not meditate AND medicate? Why not do what you can to control your problem by training your mind and then minimize the use of medical interventions.</p>
<p>Why should you take the trouble to train your mind? Well, the human body is a complex ecosystem. Every attempt to control such a system by tampering with its inner workings triggers an avalanche of unpredictable results. Our body’s complexity makes it subject to what has been called “<a href="http://www.imho.com/grae/chaos/chaos.html">the butterfly effect</a>”.  The butterfly effect refers to the fact that the tiny effect of a butterfly flapping its wings in China may change the weather in, say, Los Angeles. (Click the link above for a more detailed explanation.)</p>
<p>This effect implies that complex systems can be heavily influenced by tiny variations in factors that scientists would usually see as negligible. The butterfly effect clarifies why all medicines have “side effects”, and also why It is wise to minimize the risks of putting alien substances into our bodies.</p>
<p>In light of this, I had a strong reaction to a recent article in the New York Times <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/06/fashion/mothers-and-sleep-medication.html?_r=2&amp;src=rechp">referring to sleep medications as “mother’s little helper”.</a></p>
<p>There are useful non-medical ways to deal with sleeplessness and they can powerfully improve the effects of medical treatment while minimizing the risks entailed in taking medication. For example most of the sleepless mothers described in the New York Times article could not sleep because they were obsessively ruminating over tasks that needed to be done.</p>
<p>Meditation can help reduce such rumination. While meditating you deal with mental distractions by gently and compassionately returning your mind to the object on which you are meditating.</p>
<p>Think of it in terms of deeply ingrained stimulus-response bonds; the thought is the stimulus and it demands that you respond. One illustrative example from the Times article is a mother who said “There’s always the worry another e-mail has come in” (stimulus). &#8220;It’s hard to resist getting up and checking your emai&#8221;l (response).</p>
<p>But when you meditate, you learn over and over not to do things like taking that last peek; instead you train your mind to go back to your chosen object of meditation. This breaks the stimulus-response bond. Think of it, there are probably thousands of thoughts that create in you an urge to take action, but your meditation breaks the bond between thought and action.  It reduces the linkage to the point where the response becomes optional instead of compulsive. That will make you calmer.</p>
<p>Earlier we posted <a href="../../../../../2011/03/02/basic-mindfulness-technique/">a traditional way of doing mindfulness meditation</a>, and also an <a href="../../../../../2010/12/06/a-key-step-in-resilience-training-is-learning-deep-relaxation/">audio</a> that can have a similar effect. Nether of these aids take up much of your time. You should consider trying one or both of them.</p>
<p>This is only one small way of changing how your mind works. We will be discussing many more in later posts.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2011%2F11%2F15%2Fsleeplessness-should-you-medicate-of-meditate%2F&amp;linkname=Sleeplessness%3A%20Should%20You%20Medicate%20of%20Meditate%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Special Announcement of Our Upcoming Program on Resilience Training for Women</title>
		<link>/2011/02/14/special-announcement-of-our-upcoming-program-on-resilience-training-for-women/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Feb 2011 04:43:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Women's Resilience]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=587</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Debbie and I will be doing a resilience training program for women under the aegis of Jewish Family Services, Kansas City. The program will consist of five 2hr sessions in March and April, 2011. More information is available on this &#8230; <a href="/2011/02/14/special-announcement-of-our-upcoming-program-on-resilience-training-for-women/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Debbie and I will be doing a resilience training program for women under the aegis of Jewish Family Services, Kansas City. The program will consist of five 2hr sessions in March and April, 2011.</p>
<p>More information is available on this blog under the tab Events/Training. Click  After opening that tab, click &#8220;Upcoming Events&#8221;.</p>
<p>For other details and enrollment information, a flier is available through Jewish Family Services, KC or by clicking <a title="Resilience Training for Women_flier" href="https://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;pid=explorer&amp;chrome=true&amp;srcid=0B9vDXAJZZ67JYWNjY2U5YWEtNDdhNS00ZmNhLWI1M2UtYjdmNjg5MWVjMTk0&amp;hl=en&amp;authkey=CI_rqIwE" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Case for Resilience Training for Women.</title>
		<link>/2011/02/08/a-case-for-resilience-training-for-women/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2011 18:50:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Women's Resilience]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=569</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Last year we conducted a resilience training program for women and it was a great experience for us. Focusing on issues of particular interest to women was an eye-opener, even when we were getting most of the information from our &#8230; <a href="/2011/02/08/a-case-for-resilience-training-for-women/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Last year we conducted a resilience training program for women and it was a great experience for us. Focusing on issues of particular interest to women was an eye-opener, even when we were getting most of the information from our own book manuscript. Once we were focused on women in particular, it became clear that a surprising amount of the research we discussed in our book was about women. Here we list many of those, and some others that are important to both women and men.</p>
<p>We came to the conclusion that women in particular need to build their resilience and thus neutralize the effects of stress. Here are some reasons why we think that:</p>
<ul>
<li>In an important study, women who hid their thoughts and feelings (“Self-Silenced”) during marital conflict were four times as <a href="http://uk.reuters.com/article/idUKKIM05985320070820">likely to die</a> during the ten year study as women who spoke up. Men did not show the same effect. Resilience training includes learning the skills needed to express yourself without causing unnecessary trouble.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Highly stressed women have chromosomes that reflect over a <em>decade</em> of extra aging when compared to those of women who are low in stress. (For more on this click <a href="http://www.pnas.org/cgi/reprint/101/49/17312">here</a>).</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>The most damaging pattern of stress is when your stress hormones go up and stay up for a long time. With resilience these hormones may go up but recovery is prompt. Research done in Sweden by <a href="http://www.abebooks.com/servlet/BookDetailsPL?bi=4085112582&amp;searchurl=an%3Dhans%2Bselye%26sts%3Dt%26x%3D33%26y%3D9">Marianne Frankenhaeuser</a> shows that working women as well as working men have high stress hormone levels during the workday, but for men these levels drop after work. For women they are less likely to do so, especially if they have children. If they can’t arrange for a more equitable sharing of work at home, women need to learn skills that bring those levels down in the evening.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Researchers found that couples with high levels of stress hormones in the first year of their marriages were 30% more likely to be <a href="http://www.psych.ndsu.nodak.edu/hilmert/Classes/Psyc787/Week%207/K_Glaser_2003.pdf">divorced 10 years later</a>. Those high in stress who were still married were twice as likely to have troubled marriages.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Women with high levels of stress hormones are three times more likely to have <a href="http://www.webmd.com/baby/news/20060221/stress-may-up-early-miscarriage-risk">miscarriages</a></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>In one study, women with high levels of stress hormones had significantly lower bone density in the back and thigh. For more details click <a href="http://www.journals.elsevierhealth.com/periodicals/bps/article/S0006-3223%2804%2901376-9/abstract">here</a>.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>When stressed, both men and women are less able to think clearly, are more forgetful, and more likely to miss information important for them to do well in life and deal effectively with others. For an extensive review of stress and cognition <a href="http://human-factors.arc.nasa.gov/flightcognition/Publications/IH_054_Staal.pdf">click here</a>.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Stress hormones <a href="http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2000/11/001120072314.htm" target="_self">increase abdominal fat</a>, especially internal fat. High levels of internal abdominal fat are associated with cardiovascular disease in both men and women.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>People who have to be caregivers of elders with dementia (disproportionately women) tend to have suppressed immunity, and it stays suppressed for years after the loved one dies. Biological indicators of age indicated that the caregivers’ on average lost four to eight years of their <a href="http://researchnews.osu.edu/archive/telomeres.htm">lifespan</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p>This is far from a complete list. Still we think it makes a compelling case for women to devote some of their energy to becoming as resilient as they can be.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2011%2F02%2F08%2Fa-case-for-resilience-training-for-women%2F&amp;linkname=A%20Case%20for%20Resilience%20Training%20for%20Women." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
