<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Avoiding Perfectionism &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/avoiding-perfectionism/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Resilience Factor Two: Hypersensitivity, Self-Criticism and What You Can Do About Them.</title>
		<link>/2013/07/10/resilience-factor-two-hypersensitivity-self-criticism-and-what-you-can-do-about-them/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2013 03:03:36 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry and Debbie Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Attitudes of Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Hypersensitivity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Perfectionism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Self-Criticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resilience Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Compassion]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1413</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The second most important resilience factor has to do with some very self-defeating things that people do that make them less resilient. It involves amplifying stress instead of getting it in control. I see it all the time; something distressing &#8230; <a href="/2013/07/10/resilience-factor-two-hypersensitivity-self-criticism-and-what-you-can-do-about-them/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The second most important resilience factor has to do with some very self-defeating things that people do that make them less resilient. It involves amplifying stress instead of getting it in control.</p>
<p>I see it all the time; something distressing happens and people react by tearing themselves down with self-criticism, and often go on to spread the criticism to, and generate fights with the very people who could help them recover quickly, which would be the path of resilience and both mental and physical health.</p>
<p>The core pattern of the factor was over-reacting to even small errors or failings by worrying about what we have done and how other people might react to our missteps. This leads to worrying about and criticizing ourselves for real or imagined failings.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QE1vnHfOcnU">This animation</a>, voiced by Jennifer Lopez, may help you to see the kinds of criticisms and attacks we have in mind. Similar examples can be found <a href="/2011/03/22/self-compassion-and-resilience/">here</a>.</p>
<p><span id="more-1413"></span></p>
<p>Our focus is on resilience, the positive things you can do to deal with stress and live a better life, so we are not interested in lamenting what is wrong with things we do, but with how we stay strong, healthy, and live well even if we have messed up.</p>
<p>We pondered and discussed Factor 2 (which we dubbed, perhaps clumsily, “Hypersensitivity, Self-Criticism/Perfectionism) for many years, frequently attempting to pinpoint the positive, resilience-promoting patterns implied by its negative, depleting ways.</p>
<p>Doing this blog and constantly looking for new approaches to enhance resilience led us to see what that resilience-promoting factor was.</p>
<p>We discovered an important body of research on self-compassion. If you are self-compassionate, you are not likely to be severely and unreasonably critical of your mistakes.</p>
<p>Self-compassion is the closest we are likely to find to the opposite of the intense and unreasonable self-criticism and demanding perfectionism reflected in Factor 2.</p>
<p>To give you a better sense of what factor two is about, here are some patterns embedded in it.</p>
<p>If you change on any of these patterns, you are also changing your standing on the factor itself. Here are more details:</p>
<ul>
<li>Self-Evaluations that are Critical and Unreasonably Demanding versus Reasonable Self-Compassion, and Realistic yet Loving, and Accepting Self-Evaluations.</li>
<li>Worry/Rumination versus, Focusing on the Present, and Taking Things One at a Time.</li>
<li>Unreasonable Expectations/Perfectionism. The more resilient polarity of this is recognizing that we all have limitations and that errors are natural in human life and deserve compassion. Failures, handled well, can even help by teaching us better ways of managing our lives.</li>
</ul>
<p>Knowing the factors is useful, but knowing ways you can change where you stand on them is more important. In a number of our previous blog posts we have discussed what to do if you need to improve on these patterns:</p>
<ol start="1">
<li>Learn how to offer yourself warmth and non-judgmental understanding rather than belittling your pain or berating yourself with self-criticism. <a href="/2012/01/03/from-negative-thinking-and-self-criticism-to-positive-thinking-and-self-compassion/?#more-891">This previous post</a> explains a useful way to reduce your self-negativity.</li>
<li>The ordinary human mind is chaotic; there is ancient expression that “The mind is a drunken monkey”. If you are a strong self-critic, you need to help yourself become more even-minded, and meditation will do that. <a href="/2011/03/02/basic-mindfulness-technique/">Here</a> is one of our earlier posts on a very popular, effective method of meditation.</li>
<li>Some things you can do to help with perfectionism are in <a href="/2011/02/20/to-increase-your-resilience-avoid-being-too-hard-on-yourself/">this post</a>.</li>
</ol>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=&amp;linkname=Resilience%20Factor%20Two%3A%20Hypersensitivity%2C%20Self-Criticism%20and%20What%20You%20Can%20Do%20About%20Them." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sleeplessness: Should You Medicate of Meditate?</title>
		<link>/2011/11/15/sleeplessness-should-you-medicate-of-meditate/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2011 16:28:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Adversity and Resilience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Perfectionism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Self-Criticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deep Relaxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Resilience Topic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mindfulness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Soothing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Understanding]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Women's Resilience]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=858</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I think it is safe to say that a large majority of us gravely underestimate the powers of our minds and overestimate the powers of medicine. Whether your problem is sleeplessness, pain or some other potentially overwhelming challenge, your mind, &#8230; <a href="/2011/11/15/sleeplessness-should-you-medicate-of-meditate/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think it is safe to say that a large majority of us gravely underestimate the powers of our minds and overestimate the powers of medicine. Whether your problem is sleeplessness, pain or some other potentially overwhelming challenge, your mind, especially if you train and develop its powers, can work wonders in corralling and controlling your problem.</p>
<p>Fortunately the title of this post implies a false dichotomy. Why not meditate AND medicate? Why not do what you can to control your problem by training your mind and then minimize the use of medical interventions.</p>
<p>Why should you take the trouble to train your mind? Well, the human body is a complex ecosystem. Every attempt to control such a system by tampering with its inner workings triggers an avalanche of unpredictable results. Our body’s complexity makes it subject to what has been called “<a href="http://www.imho.com/grae/chaos/chaos.html">the butterfly effect</a>”.  The butterfly effect refers to the fact that the tiny effect of a butterfly flapping its wings in China may change the weather in, say, Los Angeles. (Click the link above for a more detailed explanation.)</p>
<p>This effect implies that complex systems can be heavily influenced by tiny variations in factors that scientists would usually see as negligible. The butterfly effect clarifies why all medicines have “side effects”, and also why It is wise to minimize the risks of putting alien substances into our bodies.</p>
<p>In light of this, I had a strong reaction to a recent article in the New York Times <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/06/fashion/mothers-and-sleep-medication.html?_r=2&amp;src=rechp">referring to sleep medications as “mother’s little helper”.</a></p>
<p>There are useful non-medical ways to deal with sleeplessness and they can powerfully improve the effects of medical treatment while minimizing the risks entailed in taking medication. For example most of the sleepless mothers described in the New York Times article could not sleep because they were obsessively ruminating over tasks that needed to be done.</p>
<p>Meditation can help reduce such rumination. While meditating you deal with mental distractions by gently and compassionately returning your mind to the object on which you are meditating.</p>
<p>Think of it in terms of deeply ingrained stimulus-response bonds; the thought is the stimulus and it demands that you respond. One illustrative example from the Times article is a mother who said “There’s always the worry another e-mail has come in” (stimulus). &#8220;It’s hard to resist getting up and checking your emai&#8221;l (response).</p>
<p>But when you meditate, you learn over and over not to do things like taking that last peek; instead you train your mind to go back to your chosen object of meditation. This breaks the stimulus-response bond. Think of it, there are probably thousands of thoughts that create in you an urge to take action, but your meditation breaks the bond between thought and action.  It reduces the linkage to the point where the response becomes optional instead of compulsive. That will make you calmer.</p>
<p>Earlier we posted <a href="../../../../../2011/03/02/basic-mindfulness-technique/">a traditional way of doing mindfulness meditation</a>, and also an <a href="../../../../../2010/12/06/a-key-step-in-resilience-training-is-learning-deep-relaxation/">audio</a> that can have a similar effect. Nether of these aids take up much of your time. You should consider trying one or both of them.</p>
<p>This is only one small way of changing how your mind works. We will be discussing many more in later posts.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2011%2F11%2F15%2Fsleeplessness-should-you-medicate-of-meditate%2F&amp;linkname=Sleeplessness%3A%20Should%20You%20Medicate%20of%20Meditate%3F" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Self-Compassion and Resilience</title>
		<link>/2011/03/22/self-compassion-and-resilience/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2011 19:03:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Hypersensitivity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Perfectionism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Self-Criticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Compassion]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=614</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Earlier, I explained that there are three factors that indicate whether people are resilient. For this post, I want to go back to the second resilience factor, discussed previously, about not being too hard on yourself. Many of us attack &#8230; <a href="/2011/03/22/self-compassion-and-resilience/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Earlier, I explained that there are <a href="../../../../../2011/01/11/the-three-core-factors-that-can-make-you-more-resilient/">three factors that indicate whether people are resilient</a>. For this post, I want to go back to the second resilience factor, discussed previously, about <a href="../../../../../2011/02/20/to-increase-your-resilience-avoid-being-too-hard-on-yourself/">not being too hard on yourself</a>.</p>
<p>Many of us attack ourselves when we are down. Here are some words <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Mental-ABCs-Pitching-Performance-Enhancement/dp/1888698292/ref=sr_1_3?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1300375346&amp;sr=1-3">Harvey Dorfman</a>, a major league pitching coach heard his extremely talented athletes apply to themselves: “idiot,” “loser,” “dummy,” “gutless,” and “I stink,” “I can’t,” “I don’t have it,” and “I’m clueless.” Notice that these are nasty and inaccurate. Even if on a given occasion they had made a mistake, they wouldn’t be major league pitchers if they were losers, idiots, etc.</p>
<p>Recently Glamor Magazine did a <a href="http://www.glamour.com/health-fitness/2011/02/shocking-body-image-news-97-percent-of-women-will-be-cruel-to-their-bodies-today">survey of women’s attitudes toward their bodies</a>, and here are some things the surveyed women had to say about themselves: “You are a fat, worthless pig.” “You’re too thin. No man is ever going to want you.” “Ugly. Big. Gross.” Ninety-seven percent of surveyed women had at least one such thought per day and, on average, the women had close to one of these thoughts per waking hour.</p>
<p>As a full-time professor I used to lecture on overweight, obesity, and weight loss. I always marveled at the intense attention students, especially women, gave as I spoke. Very lovely, well-formed women whom any sensible person would see as attractive were intensely interested in how to lose weight. And they were more than willing to listen to a paunchy professor tell them how to do that!</p>
<p>People who tend to speak abusively to themselves diminish their level of resilience, and so presumably lose at least some of the many advantages of being resilient. We are talking, after all, about the second most important resilience factor.</p>
<p>If, when under stress, we are nasty to ourselves, we just ratchet up the mental and physical stress reactions, and slow our recovery.</p>
<p>Recently the New York Times ran an article centering on <a href="http://well.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/02/28/go-easy-on-yourself-a-new-wave-of-research-urges/">the work of Kristin Neff on Self-Compassion</a>. By going to <a href="https://webspace.utexas.edu/neffk/pubs/listofpublications.htm">Dr. Neff’s website</a>, I saw that this topic has been the subject of a lot of research, not just by her, but by many others. Somehow I had missed it, despite my constant efforts to find <em>everything</em> relevant to resilience.</p>
<p>Her work took me one step further in clarifying what that second resilience factor is. It is about being compassionate toward yourself. To me that feels richer than merely putting an end to being mean to yourself. Compassion is not just the absence of meanness. It implies treating yourself in a caring, understanding, and loving way.</p>
<p>I am going to end this post with a valuable quotation from a <a href="https://webspace.utexas.edu/neffk/pubs/JRP.pdf">paper by Dr. Neff</a> that clarifies the concept of self-compassion:</p>
<p>“If individuals are self-compassionate when confronting suffering, inadequacy or failure, it means that they offer themselves warmth and non-judgmental understanding rather than belittling their pain or berating themselves with self-criticism.”</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2011%2F03%2F22%2Fself-compassion-and-resilience%2F&amp;linkname=Self-Compassion%20and%20Resilience" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>To Increase Your Resilience, Avoid Being Too Hard On Yourself.</title>
		<link>/2011/02/20/to-increase-your-resilience-avoid-being-too-hard-on-yourself/</link>
		<comments>/2011/02/20/to-increase-your-resilience-avoid-being-too-hard-on-yourself/?#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 20 Feb 2011 17:42:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Perfectionism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Avoiding Self-Criticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Self-Compassion]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=598</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In a previous post we described the three core factors that underlie resilience. Mostly we have talked about the first factor. The second factor has to do with: Treating your minor mistakes as awful and catastrophic. Being excessively self-critical. Setting &#8230; <a href="/2011/02/20/to-increase-your-resilience-avoid-being-too-hard-on-yourself/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In a previous post we described the three core factors that underlie resilience. Mostly we have talked about the first factor. The second factor has to do with:</p>
<ol>
<li>Treating your minor      mistakes as awful and catastrophic.</li>
<li>Being excessively self-critical.</li>
<li>Setting unrealistically      high standards that are usually unattainable.</li>
</ol>
<p>In plain language, it is being too hard on yourself. It is very likely to make you less resilient and more vulnerable.</p>
<p>The three item list above is identical to what many researchers who explore this topic simply call “perfectionism” or “maladaptive perfectionism”.</p>
<p>Perfectionists cannot tolerate even the smallest mistakes, berate themselves for any slip ups, and view results that are less than perfect as completely unacceptable. Clearly, perfectionism can make <strong><em>anything</em></strong> stressful.</p>
<p>The resilience-training alternatives to these three items are</p>
<p>1.                <em>Learning</em> to treat your minor mistakes realistically, with tolerance and acceptance.</p>
<p>2.                <em>Learning</em> to question and forcefully challenge the self-critical voice inside you, replace the criticism with ideas about how to do better in the future.</p>
<p>3.                <em>Learning</em> that having unrealistically high standards is not admirable or a path to success.</p>
<p>There are many levels of perfectionism. The severe ones are best dealt with in treatment with a qualified therapist. For example, perfectionistic people who are so thwarted that they have become severely depressed should consider therapy. That doesn’t exclude self-training. In fact, therapists commonly refer clients to our resilience training, as an adjunct to their therapy.</p>
<p>Most of us who stress ourselves by being too perfectionistic can improve considerably in one of two ways:</p>
<p>1.                Regularly and steadfastly challenging thoughts that point to unfair and unrealistic internal demands. If, when you make a mistake, your inner critic claims you are stupid or your action is going to result in catastrophic losses, or even that you would be better off dead, don’t take that lying down. Be your own defense attorney and demand solid evidence for the critic&#8217;s claims.</p>
<p>2.                Practicing some form of mindfulness meditation.</p>
<p>Here is a <a href="http://hubpages.com/hub/Dont-Be-Beaten-Down-by-Self-Critical-Thoughts">good account of how to challenge and diminish your self-critical thoughts</a>. In the next post we will describe our preferred method of mindfulness meditation. You should also take a look at the book “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Pursuit-Perfect-Chasing-Perfection-Happier/dp/0071608826">The Pursuit of Perfect: How to Stop Chasing Perfection and Start Living a RICHER, HAPPIER Life</a>”, by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tal_Ben-Shahar">Tal Ben-Shahar</a>. It is a book with heart, combining a narrative of his personal struggle to overcome perfectionism with science-based, helpful techniques.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2011%2F02%2F20%2Fto-increase-your-resilience-avoid-being-too-hard-on-yourself%2F&amp;linkname=To%20Increase%20Your%20Resilience%2C%20Avoid%20Being%20Too%20Hard%20On%20Yourself." target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2011/02/20/to-increase-your-resilience-avoid-being-too-hard-on-yourself/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
