<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Uncategorized &#8211; On Resilience</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/uncategorized/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Surgical Preparation</title>
		<link>/2016/08/31/surgical-preparation/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2016 21:20:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2128</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Basic Paths to Becoming More Resilient</title>
		<link>/2010/12/06/the-basic-paths-to-becoming-more-resilient/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2010 06:53:39 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=461</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Highlights: “Often, anti-stress programs come close to being useless. Their goal is off the mark and their method of creating change is misguided. “When you are told something in order to change your emotion system, the telling goes to the &#8230; <a href="/2010/12/06/the-basic-paths-to-becoming-more-resilient/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2><em>Highlights:</em></h2>
<p><em>“Often, anti-stress programs come close to being useless. Their goal is off the mark and their method of creating change is misguided.</em></p>
<p><em>“When you are </em><em>told something in order to change your emotion system, the telling goes to the cognitive compartment of your brain. To control emotions and primitive bodily reactions, your brain has to pass those messages on through slow, winding pathways from the cognitive compartment to the emotion compartment.”</em></p>
<p><em>“…To move beyond mere “lip service”, you have two more steps:</em></p>
<ul>
<li><em>to develop </em><em>skills that reflect your new knowledge about resilience and</em></li>
<li><em>to practice those skills until they become habits.”</em></li>
</ul>
<p>************************************************************************</p>
<p>Often, anti-stress programs come close to being useless. Their goal is off the mark and their method of creating change is misguided. They focus too much on the goal of removing stress from your life rather than <em>strengthening yourself</em> against life’s inevitable sources of stress, Instead we have to learn how to <em>recover</em> from stress quickly and fully. We have to develop the skills needed to be <em>resilient</em>.</p>
<p>This old quotation summarizes the point exceptionally well:</p>
<p><em>“,,,the stability of a thing, just like that of a man, does not consist in its being shielded from all disturbances and thus preserving a precarious balance; it consists in the ability to recover from disturbances that inevitably will occur and to regain lost balance.” Wolfgang Langewiesche (1944)</em>.</p>
<p>Another problem with many stress management programs is that they merely <em>tell you what to do.</em> “Telling” is one of the least effective ways to get people to change.</p>
<p><span id="more-461"></span></p>
<p>Wait a minute! Isn’t getting an expert to tell you what to do exactly what you should want? That’s what advice columnists do, isn’t it? Isn’t that what we expect from psychologists? It must be effective.</p>
<p>It may be better than nothing, but only occasionally do we get some advice that we actually use for anything other than telling other people about the interesting advice we got.</p>
<p>If advice worked very well, life would be much easier for those who seek it all the time. Unfortunately, advice is only helpful for a narrow range of problems.</p>
<p>Telling someone how to get from point A to point B is likely to help in reaching the desired destination. In contrast, <em>telling</em> people to change their feelings, skills and habits is not likely to create any real change. Only training and practice can do that.</p>
<p>What makes the difference between the “how to get from A to B” problem and the “how to thrive in the face of stress” problem? From the point of view of brain organization, these tasks are completely different.</p>
<p>In the first half of the twentieth century the great Harvard neuroanatomist, J.W. Papez, published a classic paper in which he pointed out that the brain is naturally divided into three main compartments, one that underlies cognition (thought, speech, higher mental functions), one that underlies physical movement, and one that underlies the physiological reactions of emotion. Connections <em>within </em>each of these compartments are large and fast, much like freeways. Connections <em>between them are smaller, slower, and often roundabout, </em>like country roads.</p>
<p>When you are <em>told</em> something that is supposed to change your emotion system, the telling goes to the cognitive compartment of your brain. To control emotions and primitive bodily reactions, your brain has to pass those messages on through slow, winding pathways from the cognitive compartment to the emotion compartment.</p>
<p>Often the message gets lost somewhere, or is so degraded by the time it arrives in the emotion system that it has little impact. Thus you can know a lot about what would make you feel better, yet find that the knowledge has little effect. You can <em>know</em> that it makes no sense for your heart to pound and your hands to sweat, but, still, it pounds and they sweat.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, when you listen to or read information about what must be done to control stress reactions, you are laying a <em>foundation</em> for becoming more resilient. But you need something more.</p>
<p>To move advice beyond mere “lip service”, you have two more steps:</p>
<ul>
<li>to develop <em>skills</em> that reflect your new knowledge about resilience and</li>
<li>to practice those skills until they become habits.</li>
</ul>
<p>The best way to get through those two steps is to follow the old adage, “practice, practice, practice”.  In order to get through those steps, you need to understand specifics about what you need to learn, and also to know how to motivate yourself to use them.</p>
<p>As they used to say in the old days, “stay tuned” for our discussions of those specifics about what you need to learn, and the “how to” of motivation.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2010%2F12%2F06%2Fthe-basic-paths-to-becoming-more-resilient%2F&amp;linkname=The%20Basic%20Paths%20to%20Becoming%20More%20Resilient" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Getting Yourself To Act On What You Learn About Building Resilience</title>
		<link>/2010/12/06/getting-yourself-to-act-on-what-you-learn-about-building-resilience/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2010 06:52:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jerry Sheridan]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Effective Resilience Training]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=457</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Highlights: It is important to get clear about the deeply held values that make your change of habits personally valuable. To do that, you have to spend some time looking into yourself and asking what you will get out of &#8230; <a href="/2010/12/06/getting-yourself-to-act-on-what-you-learn-about-building-resilience/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2><em>Highlights:</em></h2>
<p><em>It is important to get clear about the deeply held values that make your change of habits personally valuable. To do that, you have to spend some time looking into yourself and asking what you will get out of making the desired changes.</em></p>
<p><em>In addition to this self-analysis, we advocate using a tested method called “mental contrasting”. Mental contrasting involves imagining how you and your life will be different after the changes and specifically contrasting the new you in the new life to the way you and your life are now. This approach has been shown to help people stick with their goals.</em></p>
<p>************************************************************************</p>
<p>If you are anything like me, and far too many people are when it comes to the things I am about to discuss, you often fail to do things you know will help when you are stressed. This is a major reason why people can be given wonderful lists of things to do that will make them more resilient, and just let the list fade out of their lives.</p>
<p>I recently got a copy of Tal Ben-Shahar’s interesting book “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Happier-Learn-Secrets-Lasting-Fulfillment/dp/0071492399">Happier</a>” Ben-Shahar is apparently the originator of Harvard’s very popular course in Happiness. The most popular course at Harvard is based on Ben-Shahar’s work. “Happier” is a nice introduction to Ben-Shahar’s approach to becoming happier.</p>
<p>“Happier” has an interesting section on creating rituals. This section goes directly at the problem of getting yourself to do the things that are in your best interest. I found it especially interesting because Debbie and I have just finished a book that also includes a section on how to get yourself to do the procedures. It is always nice to find someone who is thinking along the same lines you are. Creating rituals is a good way to describe a core part of what we had written.</p>
<p>Ben-Shahar quotes Jim Loehr and Tony Schwartz on the value of building rituals: “Building rituals requires defining very precise behaviors and performing them at very specific times- motivated by deeply held values” ( For details, click <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0743226755/ref=pd_lpo_k2_dp_sr_1?ie=UTF8&amp;cloe_id=d4512d12-301d-4329-a745-5b90f7055505&amp;attrMsgId=LPWidget-A2&amp;pf_rd_p=486539851&amp;pf_rd_s=lpo-top-stripe-1&amp;pf_rd_t=201&amp;pf_rd_i=0743226747&amp;pf_rd_m=ATVPDKIKX0DER&amp;pf_rd_r=0H">here</a>). That is an excellent brief statement of what we need to do if we want to change our level of resilience. In fact, it is an excellent statement of how to build new habits in general.</p>
<p><span id="more-457"></span></p>
<p>Debbie and I see the path to change within a framework created by Rick Snyder in his work on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C._R._Snyder">hope</a>. He divides hope into “will” and “way”. Will corresponds to the “deeply held values” of Loehr and Schwartz. It is important to get clear about the deeply held values that make your change of habits personally valuable. To do that, you have to spend some time looking into yourself and asking what you will get out of making the desired changes.</p>
<p>In addition to this self-analysis, we advocate using a tested method called “<a href="http://www.psych.nyu.edu/oettingen/Oettingen,%20G.,%20&amp;%20Gollwitzer,%20P.%20M.%20%282009%29.%20Making%20goal%20pursuit%20effective.pdf">mental contrasting</a>”. Mental contrasting involves imagining how you and your life will be different after the changes and specifically contrasting the new you in the new life to the way you and your life are now. This approach has been shown to help people stick with their goals. For example, middle-aged women who used this method to help then stick with an exercise program ended up doing twice as much exercise as those who just got instructions about how to exercise.</p>
<p>Another thing that Ben-Shahar and we share in common is recommending that only a few changes be attempted at any one time. He suggests no more than one or two rituals should be developed at a time, and we suggest no more than three. Either of these suggestions is just a rough guide, but the key idea is that you are less likely to succeed if you overwhelm yourself.</p>
<p>In our book, Debbie and I also share with him the conviction that writing your intentions out and keeping records of your results will help, and that when you fail to practice you should regard it as a mere slip and a signal to renew your commitment and practice.</p>
<p>Some additional advice we give is: a. If possible practice at the same time every day, or at least schedule when you will practice, b. Try to make your practice as pleasant as possible, c. Arrange your practice setting to be pleasant. This often takes only minor adjustments, d. Try to arrange for other people to join you or support you in your change enterprise.</p>
<p>So if you look at the list of activities people use to deal with stress and find some of them appealing, don’t just make a vague decision to put them into practice. Apply the principles covered here to enhance your success.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save?linkurl=%2F2010%2F12%2F06%2Fgetting-yourself-to-act-on-what-you-learn-about-building-resilience%2F&amp;linkname=Getting%20Yourself%20To%20Act%20On%20What%20You%20Learn%20About%20Building%20Resilience" target="_blank"><img src="http://static.addtoany.com/buttons/share_save_256_24.png" alt="Share" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
