<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>Comments on: How to Avoid “Neurotic Stupidity” and Build Resilience at the Same Time</title>
	<atom:link href="/2011/03/30/how-to-avoid-neurotic-stupidity-and-build-resilience-at-the-same-time/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/2011/03/30/how-to-avoid-neurotic-stupidity-and-build-resilience-at-the-same-time/</link>
	<description>Strategies to recover from stress quickly</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2016 16:41:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.4.29</generator>
	<item>
		<title>By: Cheryl</title>
		<link>/2011/03/30/how-to-avoid-neurotic-stupidity-and-build-resilience-at-the-same-time/?#comment-432</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cheryl]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2011 04:04:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=620#comment-432</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[What comes to mind is always the &quot;adaptive&quot; aspect of anything like this that must be considered.  When our focus is narrowing, what is the adaptive value of it?  Since it is considered a move away from normalacy or high functioning or a high quality of life, then it would be good to find out why it&#039;s happening.  Normally we are in a high stress situation or event that causes this type of adaptation (Neurotic Stupidity/narrowing of focus).  So if we can discover it&#039;s cause, then we can more easily move away from the stressor/s.  

When working with young children we found that we&#039;d get them all relaxed and happy and playful, then send them home to a horrid family situation.  The result was that they came back more traumatized than before.   It seemed that getting them all relaxed and happy made them more vulnerable to the traumatic or chaotic environments they were in at home.  We took away their armour so to speak.  

I think that it&#039;s important not to take away a person&#039;s armour until they can escape the chaos or traumatic situation they are in.  There is a reason that military training includes a desensitization to pain, torture, and fatigue.  Not that I am advocating staying in or training people or children to be able to tolerate abusive environments --- certainly not!  However, I think we can create vulnerability when the person actually needs the &#039;numbness&#039; temporarily to survive a difficult situation.  

Correct the situation and then relax, unless the person needs to feel the pain in order to leave a bad situation -- like an adult in an abusive relationship.  Relaxation training does make one more sensitive to their environment; it lowers the threshold to pain.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What comes to mind is always the &#8220;adaptive&#8221; aspect of anything like this that must be considered.  When our focus is narrowing, what is the adaptive value of it?  Since it is considered a move away from normalacy or high functioning or a high quality of life, then it would be good to find out why it&#8217;s happening.  Normally we are in a high stress situation or event that causes this type of adaptation (Neurotic Stupidity/narrowing of focus).  So if we can discover it&#8217;s cause, then we can more easily move away from the stressor/s.  </p>
<p>When working with young children we found that we&#8217;d get them all relaxed and happy and playful, then send them home to a horrid family situation.  The result was that they came back more traumatized than before.   It seemed that getting them all relaxed and happy made them more vulnerable to the traumatic or chaotic environments they were in at home.  We took away their armour so to speak.  </p>
<p>I think that it&#8217;s important not to take away a person&#8217;s armour until they can escape the chaos or traumatic situation they are in.  There is a reason that military training includes a desensitization to pain, torture, and fatigue.  Not that I am advocating staying in or training people or children to be able to tolerate abusive environments &#8212; certainly not!  However, I think we can create vulnerability when the person actually needs the &#8216;numbness&#8217; temporarily to survive a difficult situation.  </p>
<p>Correct the situation and then relax, unless the person needs to feel the pain in order to leave a bad situation &#8212; like an adult in an abusive relationship.  Relaxation training does make one more sensitive to their environment; it lowers the threshold to pain.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
</channel>
</rss>
